<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    

Acknowledgement	
Foreword	
Baumstark in Lexicon für Theologie und Kirche Vol 2:318-319	
Compilation	
Content and Organisation	
Order of Entries	
Style	
Annotations	
Acknowledgments	
Abbreviations	
Part ONE	
Generalia	
Historic Printings	
Biblia Sacra Arabica	
Paris Polyglot	
London Polyglot	
Editions, Chrestomathies	
Art, paleography, codicology	
Part Two	
Christian-Arabic	
Generalia	
Pentateuch	
Al-Harith ibn Sinan	
Marqus ibn al-Qunbar	
Pentateuch Catena	
Historical Books	
Prophets	
Pethion ibn Ayyub	
Al-alam	
Sapiental books	
Violet Fragment	
Hafs al-Quti	
Al-harith ibn sinan	
Other old testament	
Gospels	
Diatesseron	
Hibbatallah	
Isaak Velasquez	
Other new testament	
Acts	
Hebrews	
Corinthians	
Galatians	
James	
Johannine Epistles	
Revelation	
Deuteroncanonicals/ Apocrypha	
Judaeo-Arabic	
general	
Pentateuch	
Early non-saadianic	
Saadiah	
YbE	
YbY	
AbS	
Historical Books	
Prophets	
Sapiental Books	
Other old testament	
Samaritan	
Muslim reception	
ibn al-Layth	
al-jahiz	
ibn al-rabban	
al-yaʿqūbī (d. 897/98)	
al-Tabari	
Abū Nuʿaim	
Ibn Hazm	
Ibn Qutayba	
al-Ghazali	
al-Biqāʿī	
ibn Khaldun	
Pseudo-Scriptures	
rest	

 
Abbreviations
GCAL 			G. Graf, Geschichte des christlichen arabischen Literatur, vol. 1 (Vatican City, 1944), pp. 85-195.
BA	Schnurrer, Christian Friedrich von, Bibliotheca arabica (Halae ad Salam: typis et sumtu I. C. Hendelii, 1811
BAV	Bibliotheca Apostolica Vaticana
BL 	British Library
BLM	Bibliotheca Medicea Laurentiana 
BNF	Bibliothèque nationale de France
COP	Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate
HCPE	Darlow, T. H., and Horace Frederick Moule. Historical catalogue of the printed editions of Holy Scripture in the library of the British and foreign Bible society (London: The Bible house.,1903).
JBL 	Journal of Biblical Literature
OC	Oriens Christianus
PO	Smitskamp, R., Philologia orientalis: a description of books illustrating the study and printing of Oriental languages in 16th and 17th century Europe (Leiden: Brill, 1992)
ZAW			Zeitschrift für die Alttestamentliche Wissenschaft
ZfHB			Zeitschrift für Hebraeische Bibliographie
ZDMG			Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenländischen Gesellschaft

Part ONE
Generalia 
[#] Adang, Camilla, “Torah,” in Encyclopaedia of the Qur’ān, McAuliffe, Jane Dammen (ed.), Leiden: Brill, 2006, vol. 5, pp. 300-311.
[#] Adang, Camilla, Sabine Schmidtke and Meira Polliack, “The Task of Translation | L’onore della traduzione | La tâche de la traduction,” Oasis: Rivista semestrale della Fondazione Internazionale/ Oasis: A Biannual Journal of the Oasis International Foundation 17 (2013), pp. 90-97. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Violet fragment</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Istanbul</place>, Süleymaniye, Carullah 3</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Cambridge</place>, CUL, T-S Ar. 1a.55.</mssGroup>
[#] Adler, Jacob Georg Christian, Bibliotheca Biblica. Serenissimi Würtenbergensium Ducis olim Lorckiana, Altona: J.D.A. Eckhardt, 1787, pp. 1-13 and 134-139. 
Lists printed Arabic versions and Polyglot Bibles.
[#]-------, Kurze Uebersicht seiner biblischkritischen Reise nach Rom, Altona: J.D.A. Eckhardt, 1783, pp. 13, 23, 67-69, 73, 133-138, 148-162, 173-184 and 208-212.
The author reports and describes his manuscript finds in various libraries on his journey to Rome. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vienna</place>, ÖNP, NF. 97 (cited as Lambecii codex XLIV)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Venice</place>, St. Mark, Cod. 11</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. Or. Or. 57 (formerly 12) and 112 (olim 21)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 5 and Syr. 10, Barberini, Or. 1, Borg. Ar. 129.</mssGroup>
[#] Aßfalg, Julius, “Arabische christliche Literatur,” in Die Religion in Geschichte und Gegenwart: Handwörterbuch für Theologie und Religionswissenschaft, 3. ed., Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 1957, Vol. 1, cols. 529-531.
[#] ------, “Arabische B[ibelübersetzungen],” in Lexikon für Theologie und Kirche, 2. Ed., Freiburg im Breisgau: Herder & Co. GMBH Verlagsbuchhandlung, 1958, vol. 2, cols. 394-396.
An update of Baumstark [#].
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 154 and 155</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 28, 468, and 605</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 234</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 2291.</mssGroup>
[#]------,“Bibelübersetzungen,” in Kleines Wörterbuch des Christlichen Orients, Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1975, pp. 78-79.
------, Trans. Krüger, Paul, “Versions bibliques,” in Petit dictionnaire de l'orient chrétien, Turnhout:Brepols, 1991, p. 465.
 [#] Barsoum, Ignatius Aphram, The Scattered Pearls: A History of Syriac Literature and Sciences, trans. and ed. Matti Moosa, Piscataway:Gorgias Press, 2003), pp. 62-64.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 112 (formerly 21)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate</place>, Bibl. 23</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 145</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF. Ar. 42</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Birmingham</place>, Mingana, Chr. Ar. 431</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>and an unspecified Ms. from the monastery of St. Matthew.</mssGroup>
[#] Baumstark, Anton, Die christlichen Literaturen des Orients, Leipzig: Göschen‘sche Verlagshandlung, 1911, Vol. 2, pp. 12-15.
[#]------, “Arabische B[ibelübersetzungen],” in Lexikon für Theologie und Kirche, 1. Ed., Freiburg im Breisgau: Herder & Co. GMBH Verlagsbuchhandlung, 1931, vol. 2, cols. 317-319.
[#] Bailey, Kenneth E., “Allah in Translations of the Bible,” The Bible Translator: Technical Papers 52 (2001), pp. 301-305.
[#]------, “The Arabic Versions of the Bible” (in Arabic), Near East Theological Review 5 (1982), pp. 155-243.
Presents the most famous manuscripts and historic printings. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13, Ar. 71, Ar. 95, and Copt. 9</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Sinai</place>, Ar. 151.</mssGroup>
[#] Ben-Shammai, Haggai,",מקראת, תרגומים, ערבית", in האנציקלופדיה העברית, Vol. 24, cols. 304-305.
[#] Binay, Sara and Stefan Leder (eds.), Translating the Bible into Arabic: historical, text-critical and literary aspects, Beiruter Texte und Studien 131, Beirut: Ergon Verlag Würzburg in Kommission, 2012.
[#] Blau, Joshua, ",מקרא, תרגומים, תתרגומיים נוצריים לערבית", in האנציקלופדיה העברית, Jerusalem/Tel Aviv:ha-Ḥevra le-hozaʾat Enṣiqlodediyot, , Vol. 24,  cols. 305-306.
[#] ------, “תרגומים ערביים,” in Rabin, Chaim (ed.), תרגומי מקרא. פרקי מבוא, Jerusalem: Mossad Bialiq, 1984, pp. 157-163.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, RNL, D 226</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 467 and Ar. 468</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Bryn Mawr College Library</place>, BV 47 (formerly Zurich Or. 94).</mssGroup>
[#] Botte, Bernard, “Versions orientales de la Bible, Versions arabes,” in Supplément au Dictionnaire de la Bible, Paris: Libraire Letouzey et Ané, 1960. Cols. 807-810. 
Mss. <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1475 and Add. 9060</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 82 and 155</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Or. Quart. 2101</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 5.</mssGroup>
 [#] Brock, Sebastian P., “Übersetzungen ins Arabische,” in Theologische Realenzyklopädie 6, Berlin/New York: de Gruyter, 1980, pp. 209-211. 
	Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Bryn Mawr College Library</place>, BV 47 (formerly Zurich Or. 94), Birmingham, 	Mingana, Chris. Ar. Add. 137 </mssGroup>
[#] Brockelmann, Carl, Geschichte der chistlichen Litteraturen des Orients, Leipzig, C. F. Amelangs Verlag, 1909, pp. 67-68.
[#] Burkitt, F.C. “Arabic Versions,” in A Dictionary of the Bible, ed. J. Hastings et al., vol. 1 (London/ New York, 1898-1904), pp. 136-138.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13 and Copt. 9</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leipzig</place>, Universitätsbibliothek, Tisch. 12</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 75 and Ar. 154</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Harl. 5474 and 5505, and Arund. Or. 15</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ar. NS. 327.</mssGroup>
??? k, ii, 31 in the Propaganda fide collection, most o
[#]------, “Arabic, Other Versions,” Text and Versions, Encyclopaedia Biblica, col. 5012
[#] Caubet Iturbe, Francisco Javier, “Biblia, Versiones,” in Gran Enciclopedia Rialp, Vol. 4, pp. 177.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13, Borg. Ar. 95</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 74</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, or. oct. 1108.</mssGroup>
 [#] Coquin, René-G. “Langue et littérature arabes chrétiennes,” in Micheline Albert, et al., Christianismes orientaux. Introduction à l’étude des langues et des littératures, Paris: Les Éditions du Cerf, 1993, pp. 52-54.
[#] Davidson, Samuel, A Lectures on Biblical criticism: exhibiting a systematic view of that science, Edinburgh: Clark, 1839, pp.69-73.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Poc. 289</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Harl. 5505 (cited as 5503!).</mssGroup>
------, A treatise on Biblical criticism: exhibiting a systematic view of that science, Edinburgh: A. and C. Black, 1852, pp. 668-675.
Largely based on the item above.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Poc. 289</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 5505 (cited as 5503!)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13.</mssGroup>
[#] Editorial Staff, “Bible, Translations, Modern Versions, Arabic,” in Encyclopaedia Judaica, 1st ed., Vol. 4, col. 887.
 [#] Esbroeck, Michel van, “Les versions orientales de la Bible: Une orientation bibliographique,” in Jože Krašovec (ed), The Interpretation of the Bible. The International Symposium in Slovenia, Journal for the Study of the Old Testament Supplement Series 289 (Sheffield: Sheffield Academic Press, 1998), pp. 399-509. There pp. 402-415 on Christian Arabic versions.
Mentions a long list of manuscript sources. 
 [#] Fox, Everett, “Bible, Translations, Modern Versions, Arabic,” in Encyclopaedia Judaica, 2. Ed., Vol. 3, pp. 627.
Almost entirely based on 1st ed., see [#].
[#] Furat, Ahmed Subhı, “Zebûr,” in İslâm Ansiklopedisi, 13. vol, pp. 481-482. 
Ms.: Violet Fragment
[#] Gehman, Henry S., “The Arabic Bible in Spain,” Speculum 1 (1926), pp. 219-221.
On Isaac Velaquez [chapter] and John of Seville’s alleged translation of the Bible into Arabic.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 238 and Ar. 234.</mssGroup>
[#] Goldmann, M., “Bibel, Bibelübersetzungen, Arabische,” in Encyclopaedia Judaica, Vol. 4, cols. 586-590.
[#] Gottfried Eichhorn, Johann, Einleitung in das Alte Testament, vol. 2 (Göttingen, 1823), pp. 230-319 (= §§ 275-302).
pdf
 [#] Gottheil, Richard, “Bible Translations, Arabic versions,” The Jewish Encyclopedia, Vol. 3, pp. 188-190.
[#] Goussen, Heinrich, Die christlich-arabische Literatur der Mozaraber, Leipzig: Harrassowitz, 1909, pp. 8-18.
Transl. Monferrer Sala, Juan Pedro, La literatura árabe cristiana de los mozárabes, Córdoba: Servicio de Publ. de la Univ. de Córdoba, 1999. There at pp. 17-29.
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Staatsbibliothek Ar. 238 (pl. on p. 31 and Ar. 234</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL Add. 9060 (pls. on pp. 26-27), Add. 9061 (pl. on p. 30), and Or. 3706</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Madrid</place>, BNE Ms. 4971 (pls. on pp. 24-25) and Ms. 3484</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Archive of the Cathedral of Leon</place>, Cod. 35 (olim Escurial, Ms. H, IV, 10) and Cod. 1026</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leipzig</place>, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. 1059</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 5 (pls. on pp. 28-29). </mssGroup>
[#] Graf, Georg, Die christlich-arabische Literatur bis zur fränkischen Zeit (Ende des 11. Jahrhunderts): Eine Literaturhistorische Skizze, Freiburg im Breisgau: Herdersche Verlagshandlung, 1905.
Predecessor of the following item, with fewer references to sources. 
[#] ------. Geschichte der christlichen arabischen Literatur, 5 vols. Città del Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1944-1949, Vol. 1, pp. 85-195.
The most comprehensive survey up to date; includes an abundance of primary manuscript sources and secondary literature.
[#]------. Der Sprachgebrauch der ältesten Christlichen-arabischen Literatur, Leipzig. 1905.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, Ar. 13</mssGroup>;14; Borg, K II 31; Leipzig, UBL, Tischend. 31; Sinai, Ar. 75;154;155; St. Petersburg. A.N.S. 327;Munich, Staatsbibliothek Ar. 238 and Ar. 234
An examination of the linguistic features of the Arabic Christian literature through certain pericopes of several manuscripts.
[#] S.H. Griffith, The Bible in Arabic: The Scriptures of the “People of the Book” in the Language of Islam (Princeton and Oxford, forthcoming 2013).
[#] ------, “The Bible in Arabic,” in The Cambridge History of the Bible (new ed.; forthcoming).
[#] ------, “Les premières versions arabes de la Bible et leurs liens avec le syriaque,” in Franç Briquel Chatonnet and Philippe Le Moigne (eds.), L’ancien Testament en syriaques, Paris: Geuthner, 2008, pp. 221-246.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Violet fragment</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Sinai</place>, Ar. 1, Ar. 74, Ar. 151, and Ar. 589</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1316.</mssGroup>
 [#]------, “Übersetzungen ins Arabische,” in Religion in Geschichte und Gegenwart: Handwörterbuch für Theologie und Religionswissenschft, 4th ed., Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 1998), Vol. 1, col. 1498.
[#] Groussow, W., “Versions de la Bible,” in Dictionnaire Encyclopédique de la Bible, Turnhout/Paris: Brepols, 1960, col. 1908. 
	See below for the following edition [#]. 
[#] Hage, Wolfgang, “Bibelübersetzungen, Arab[ische],” in Kaufhold, Hubert (ed.), Kleines Lexikon des Christlichen Orients, Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 2007, p. 101.
[#] Halkin, Abraham Solomon, “Bible, Translations, Ancient versions, Arabic,” in Encyclopaedia Judaica, 1. Ed., Vol. 4, cols. 863-864.
[#] Hary, Benjamin, “Bible Translations, Judeo-Arabic Shurūḥ (since the Fourteenth Century),” in Norman A. Stillman (ed.), Encyclopedia of Jews in the Islamic World, Vol. 1, pp.  469-472.
[#] Henninger, Joseph, “Arabische Bibelübersetzungen vom Frühmittelalter bis zum 19. Jahrhundert,” Neue Zeitschrift für Missionswissenschaft 17.3 (1961), pp. 201-233.
Based on GCAL [#].
[#] Horovitz, J., “Tawrāt,” in Enzyklopaedie des Islam, vol. 4, pp. 764-766. (reprinted in Wensinck, A.J. and J.H. Kraemers (eds.), Handwörterbuch des Islam, Leiden: Brill, 1941, pp. 744-746).
[#] Horovitz, J., “Tevrat,” in İslâm Ansiklopedisi, vol. 12.1, pp. 219-221. 
Translation of previous.
[#] ------, “Zabūr,” in Enzyklopaedie des Islam, vol. 4, pp. 1282-1283. (reprinted in Wensinck, A.J. and J.H. Kraemers (eds.), Handwörterbuch des Islam, Leiden: Brill, 1941, pp. 815-818).
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[#] Horovitz, J. and R. Firestone, “Zabūr,” in Encyclopaedia of Islam, 2nd ed., vol. 11, pp. 372-373.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[#] Hoskins, Franklin E., A Completed Chapter in Bible History, First Font Reference Arabic Bible (1917)
Available in Cambridge, Bible Society
[#] Hug, Johann Leonard von, Einleitung in die Schriften des Neuen Testaments, 4th ed., Stuttgart/Tübingen: J.G. Cotta’scher Verlag, 1847, pp. 378-402. (trans. Daniel Guildfort Wait), An introduction to the writings of the New Testament, London: C. & J. Rivington, 1827, Vol. 1, pp. 247-254.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vienna</place>, Nationalbibliothek, Or. 43</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13 and Copt. 9</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>French Library</place>, cod. 17, olim. 332 (Pauline epistles). </mssGroup>
H. Hyvernat, “(Versions) arabes,” in Dictionnaire de la Bible, ed. F. Vigouroux, vol. 1 (Paris, 1895), coll. 845-856.
See above
[#] Jellicoe, Sidney, The Septuagint and Modern Study, Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1968 (several reprints, Winona Lake: Eisenbrauns), pp. 266-268.
Part two, Ch. VIII offers a brief account on “the Arabic version”. Mostly on the Pentateuch and Daniel in the Paris Polyglot, as the source of the siglum A (versio arabica) in the Biblia Hebraica.
 [#] Kahle, Paul, Die Arabischen Bibelübersetzungen: Texte mit Glossar und Literaturübersicht, Leipzig: J.C. Hinrichs’sche Buchhandlung, 1904.
Contains excerpts of historic printings (# eli smith, propaganda), as well as a selection of Christian, Judaeo-Arabic and Samaritan traditions. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF Ar. 1, Ar. 5, and Ar. 6</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Wolfenb</place>, Oxford</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Bodl. Cod. II Usserii</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>St Petersburg</place>, 179</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cambridge</place>, UL Ms. 714</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Barberini Or. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Or. Fol. 534 and Or. Qu. 828</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library Or. 377</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML Or. 112 (formerly 21).</mssGroup>
[#] Karoui, Said, “Die arabische Bibel und ihre Rezeption in der arabischen Literatur – Eine bibliographische Skizze,” Oriens Christianus, 83 (1999), pp. 130-146.
 [#] Kirschner, Bruno and Sigmund Jampel, “Bibelübersetzungen in orientalische Sprachen,” in Jüdisches Lexikon, Vol. 1, cols. 1009-1010.
[#] Koningsverld, Pieter Sjoerd van, The Latin-Arabic glossary of the Leiden University Library. A Contribution to the Study of Mozarabic manuscripts and Literature, Leiden: c.v. elve/Labor Vincit,1977, pp. 52-56, 61-
Discusses several biblical translations of Mozarabic origin, such as that of Ḥafṣ b. al-Qūṭī [#] and ibn Balashk [#] 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Ambrosiana?</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 5</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Add. 9060 and Add. 9061: Escurial, Ms. Ar. 1625 and Ms. Ar. 1626</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Madrid</place>, BNE, Ms. 4971</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Cod. Ar. 238</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 214</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Lat. 12900 (formerly Chapter of the Cathedral of Siguenze, Ms. 150). </mssGroup>
[#] Lazarus-Yafeh, Hava, “Tawrāt,” in Encyclopaedia of Islam, 2nd ed., vol. 10, pp. 393-395.
[#] Lipiński, É., “Versions arabes,” in Dictionnaire encyclopédique de la Bible, 3rd ed., Turnhout: Brepols, 1987, cols. 1320-1321.
Updated version of [#].
[#] Livingstone, E.A., (ed.), “Arabic Versions of the Bible,” in The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church, Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 96.
 [#] Margolis, Max L., The Story of Bible Translations, Philadelphia: Jewish Publication Society of America, 1917, pp. 53-55.
[#] Meinardus, Otto, Two Thousand Years of Coptic Christianity Cairo: American University in Cairo Press,1999, pp. 41-42.
Mentions Ḥunayn b. Isḥāq, Abū al-Fatḥ ʿAbd Allāh ibn Faḍl [chapter xxx], al-ʿAlam [chapter], al-Asʿad Abū Faraj Hibat Allāh [chapter], Yūḥannā al-Qaylūbī and early printings [chapter]. 
[#] Metzger, Bruce M., “Early Arabic Versions of the New Testament,” Matthew Black and William A. Smalley (eds.), On Language, Culture and Religion: In Honor of Eugene A. Nida, The Hage/Paris: Mouton, 1974, pp. 157-168.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13, Borg. Ar. 95</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai Ar. 70</place>, Ar. 72, Ar. 73, Ar. 74, Ar. 151, Ar. 154, Ar. 155</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St. Petersburg</place>, Imperial Library, Cod. 226, Paris, BNF, Anc. F. 27 (current shelfmark) and Suppl. Ar. 27 (Coisl. 239), Vatican, BAV, Lat. 12900 (formerly Chapter of the Cathedral of Siguenze, Ms. 150).</mssGroup>
 [#] ------, The Early Versions of the New Testament: Their Origin, Transmission, and Limitations (Oxford, 1977), pp. 14-17, 257-268. 
Chapter VI.I The Arabic Versions is based on [#].
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>In addition to the list above</place>, the following manuscripts are mentioned: Vatican, BAV, Ar. 14, Borg. Ar. 250</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate</place>, Bibl. 202</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl. Ar. e. 163</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Sbath 1020.</mssGroup>
[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro, "La Biblia en árabe: entre el texto y sus contextos," in Martínez Delgado, José (ed.), El viaje lingüístico de la Biblia. Granada, 2011, pp. 149-167.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, St. Catherine’s, Ar. 1, Ar. 2, Ar. 4, Ar. 72, and Ar. 151</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13. </mssGroup>
[#] Monferrer Sala, Jedro Pedro, “Manuscritos árabes cristianos en España: Notas preleminares,” M.J. Viguera and C. Castillo (eds.), Los manuscritos árabes en España y Marruecos: homenaje de Granada y Fez a Ibn Jaldún, Granada: Junta de Andalucía, Consejería de cultura, 2005, pp. 193-208.
Refers to biblical material, e.g. the translations of Saadiah [chapter], Ḥafs b. al-Qūṭī [chapter ], Isaak Velasquez [chapter], and al-Ḥārith b. Sinān [chapter].
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Mss. Munich</place>, Staatsbibliothek Ar. 238 and Ar. 234</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL Add. 9061</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Archive of the Cathedral of Leon</place>, Cod. 35, Fez, Khizānat al-Qarawiyīn, Ms. 730</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leipzig</place>, University Library, Cod. Or. 1059D</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Escurial</place>, Cod. 1857 and Cod. 1625.</mssGroup>
Monferrer-Sala, J.P. “De nuevo sobre Iohannes Hispalensis y la primera versión árabe de las ‘Sagradas Escrituras’ izada en al-Andalus.” Revista del Instituto Egipcio de Estudios Islámicos 31 (1999): 77-105.
Morozov, D.A. “Biblija i arabskaja filologija v Rossii (1773-1991)” [The Bible and Arabic Philology in Russia (1773-1991)]. Pages 538-542 in Rossija i Khristianskij Vostok. Issue 2-3. Moscow, 2004 [English summary on p. 677].
________. “Biblija i arabskaja filologija v Rossii (1991-2010)” [La Bible et la philologie arabe en Russie (1991–2010)]. Simvol 58 (2010): 179-197.
[#] Muscat, Anna, “Alfons Marija Galea: Translator of the Bible,” in Sant, Carmel, Bible translation and language. Essays into the history of Bible translation in Maltese, (ed.) Abela, Anthony, Melita Theologica Supplementary Series 2, Malta: Faculty of Theology, University of Malta, 1992, pp. xxx.
Fernleihe?
[#]------ “xxxx,” in Sijon 6 (1974) 54-59. 
Fernleihe?
[#] Nasrallah, Joseph, Histoire du mouvement littéraire dans l’église melchite du Ve au XXe siècle. Contribution à l'étude de la littérature arabe chrétienne, 4 vols. (Louvain: Peeters [et al.], 1979-1996). 
Vol. 2.1 (634-750), p. 101 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Violet fragment and Moscow</place>, State Library, Ms. 432.</mssGroup>
Vol. 2.2 (750-Xe s.), pp. 184-185: On some ancient pre-10th century manuscripts of Arabic translations of the Psalms and New Testament. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Gr. 32, Gr. 34, Gr. 35, Gr. 36, Ar. 8, Ar. 10, Ar. 50, Ar. 70, Ar. 72, Ar. 73, Ar. 74, Ar. 75, Ar. 151, Ar. 155</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 13, Ar. 14, Ar. 6725</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Ar. 13</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Borg. Ar. 95</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>and Syr. 278</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Moscow</place>, State Library, Ms. 432 (given incorrectly as Leningrad, Ms. 432)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Moscow</place>, State Library, Ms. 432</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Laud. Or. 258 (formerly A 147) and Laud. Or. 243 (formerly A 146)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Escurial</place>, Arabic 1857</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate</place>, Bibl. 14 and Bibl. 27</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Sauveur</place>, Ms. 224</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Birmingham</place>, Mingana, Arab. Chr. 121. </mssGroup>
Vol. 3.1 (969-1250), pp. 216-220: On translations of parts of the Bible by ‘Abdallāh b. al-Faḍl for liturgical use: Psalter and Odes, Gospel Lectionary, Acts and Epistles, Prophets (extracts from the Old Testament).
Mss.: <mssGroup>Sbath 411</mssGroup>; <mssGroup></mssGroup>
Vol. 4.1 (1516-1724), pp. 244-245.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 468 and St Petersburg, Institut of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226. </mssGroup>
[#] Nestle, Eberhard, “Bibelübersetzungen, arabische,” in Realencyklopädie für Protestantische Theologie und Kirche, 3rd ed., Leipzig:J.C. Hinrichs’schen Buchhandlung, 1897), vol. 3 pp. 90-95. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 377</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>BM Or. 1041</place>, Or. 1476, Or. 1302</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Poc. 70, Poc. 285, and Hunt. 206. </mssGroup>
[#] North, Eric M. (ed.), The Book of Thousand Tongues. Being Some Account of the Translation and Publication of All or Part of the Holy Scriptures into more than Thousand Languages and Dialects with over 1100 Examples from the Text, New York/London: Harper & Brothers Publishers, 1938 (republished Detroit: Tower Books, 1971), pp. 52-55.
Largely on printings. 
C. Peters, “Grundsätzliche Bemerkungen zur Frage der arabischen Bibeltexte,” in Rivista degli Studi Orientali 20 (1942), 129-143.
pdf
[#] Phillips, Wendell, “Text, Versions,” in Miller, Madeleine S., and J. Lane Miller, Black’s Bible Dictionary, London: A. and C. Black Limited, 1973, p. 748.
E. Pococke, “Praefatio in qua variantium in Pentateucho Arabico lectionum ratio redditur,” in 
[#] Polliack, Meira, “Bible Translations, Judeo-Arabic (Ninth to Thirteenth Century),” in Norman A. Stillman (ed.), Encyclopedia of Jews in the Islamic World, Vol. 1, pp. 464-469.
[#] Rahlfs, Alfred, Septuaginta: Societatis Scientiarum Gottingensis auctoritate editit, Vol. 1, Genesis, Stuttgart: Priviligierte Würtenbergische Bibelanstalt Stuttgart, 1926, p. 24.
Mentions the transcription of Ms. Paris, BNF Ar. 9 by Walter Reimpell, which is the possession of the Septuaginta-Unternehmen and has been used for collation.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 9</mssGroup>
[#] Roberts, Bleddyn J., The Old Testament Text and Versions, Cardiff: University of Wales press, 1951, pp. 196, 266-269.
[#] ------, “Orientalische Bibelübersetzungen, die arabischen Ü[bersetzungen]” in Die Religion in Geschichte und Gegenwart: Handwörterbuch für Theologie und Religionswissenschaft, 3. ed., Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 1957, Vol. 1, cols. 1200-1201.
Rödiger, J., Commentatio qua vulg. Opinio de interpret. Arab. librorum Vet. Test. Ex graeca Alexandrina refutatur (1824)
[#] Roth, Norman, “Bible Translations, Jewish, Translations into Arabic,” in Norman Roth (ed.), Medieval Jewish Civilization: An encyclopedia, p. 106.
[#] Samir, Samir Khalil, “Old Testament, Arabic Versions of the,” in The Coptic Encyclopedia, Vol. 6, pp. 1827-1835.
With many references to manuscript sources.
[#] Sant, Carmel, Bible translation and language. Essays into the history of Bible translation in Maltese, (ed.) Anthony Abela, Melita Theologica Supplementary Series 2, Malta: Faculty of Theology, University of Malta 1992.
Fernleihe bestellt
[#]------, “Il-Bibbja bil-Malti,” in Sijon 6 (1973), pp. 27-31.
Includes a list of printed Maltese Bibles.
T. Sarrouf, Περὶ τῶν ἀραβικῶν μεταφράσεων καὶ ἐκδόσεων τῆς θείας γραφῆς.  In Πεντηκονταετηρὶς τῆς θεολογικῆς Σχολῆς τοῦ Σταυροῦ (Jerusalem, 1913).
[#] Sasson, Ilan, “Bible, Translations, Ancient versions, Arabic,” in Encyclopaedia Judaica, 2nd ed., Vol. 3, pp. 603-606.
[#] Sharkey, Heather J., “Sudanese Arabic Bibles and the politics of translation,” The Bible Translator 62 (2011), pp. 37-45.
[#] Saydon, Peter Paul, “Philological and Textual Notes to the Maltese Translation of the Old Testament,” Catholic Biblical Quarterly 23 (1961), pp. 249-257.
 [#]------, “History of the Maltese Bible,” Melita Theologica 10 (1957), pp. 1-15.
Gives an historical survey of printed Maltese Bibles and discusses selected features in their translation techniques. 
[#] ------, “il-Kotba Mqaddsa bil-Malti,” in Lehen il-Malti 15 (1945), pp. 37-44.
 [#]------, “The Earliest Biblical Translation from Hebrew into Maltese,” in The Sundial 10-12 (1937), pp. 526-536.
 [#] ------, “The First Maltese Translation of the New Testament (1847-1947),” in The Sundial 8 (1947), pp. 10-13.
[#] Schaick, A. van, “Bijbelvertalingen, arabische,” in Bijbels Woordenboek, 2nd ed., Roermond/ Maaseik: J.J. Romen & Zonen, 1954-1957, col. 248.
------, “Bijbelvertalingen, arabische,” in Bijbels Woordenboek, 3rd ed., Roermond/ Maaseik: J.J. Romen & Zonen, 1966-1969, col. 189. 
[#] Schnurrer, Christian Friedrich, Dissertatio de Pentateucho Arabico Polyglotto Disputatio Philologica (Tübingen, 1780); Reprint, Dissertationes Philologico-Criticae (Gotha and Amsterdam, 1790), pp. 191-238, 501-504.
[#] ________, Bibliotheca Arabica (Halle, 1811), pp. 339-397.
[#] Scrivener, Frederick Henry, A Plain Introduction to the Criticism of the New Testament, 2d ed., Cambridge: Deighton Bell and Co., 1883, pp. 366-367. 3 ed. pp. 161-164.
Enumerates several bilingual manuscripts that contain an Arabic version. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Venice</place>, St. Mark 11 (Venet. 11) and 27 (Venet. 539)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Greek monastery Jerusalem Cod. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 243.</mssGroup>
[#] Simonsohn, U. “The Biblical Narrative in the Annales of Sa‘īd ibn Baṭrīq and the Question of Medieval Byzantine-Orthodox Identity.” Islam and Christian-Muslim Relations 22.1 (2011): 37-55.
[#] Spuler, Bertold, “Arabisch-Christliche Literatur,” in Theologische Realenzyklopädie 3, Berlin/New York: de Gruyter, 1978, p. 578.
[#] Steuernagel, Carl, Lehrbuch der Einleitung in das Alte Testament, Tübingen: Verlag von J.C.B. Mohr (Paul Siebeck), 1912, pp. 44, 58, 66.
[#] Swete, Henry Barclay, An Introduction to the Old Testament in Greek, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1902, pp. 110-111. Reprint New York: Ktav Publishing House, Inc, 1968. 
[#] Thompson, John A., “The Major Arabic Bibles,” in The Bible Translator 6 (1955), pp. 1-12, 51-55, 98-106, 146-150.
On the major printed Arabic Bibles and their sources.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 468, Copt. 9 and Borg. Syr. 49</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Rome</place>, Casanatense, Ar.-Carsh. 2 </mssGroup>
[#] Ṭranjān, Jamīl Ḥannā, al-Kitāb al-muqaddas fī al-lugha al-ʿarabiyya, Cairo: Nile Mission Press, 1936.
[#] Tregelles, S.P., “Arabic Versions,” in A Dictionary of the Bible Comprising Its Antiquities, Biography, Geography, and Natural History. Vol. 3. 2nd ed. London: John Murray, 1893, pp. 1614-1616.
[#] Troupeau, Gérard, “La Littérature Arabe Chrétienne,” Cahiers de Civilisation Médiévale 14 (1971), pp. 1-20. There at p.12.
[#] de Vaux, Carra, “Indjīl,” in Enzyklopaedie des Islam, 1st ed., Vol. 2, pp. 535-537, (reprinted in Wensinck, A.J. and J.H. Kraemers (eds.), Handwörterbuch des Islam, Leiden: Brill, 1941, pp. 210-212).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13.</mssGroup>
 [#] ------, “İnjil,” in İslâm Ansiklopedisi, vol, 5.2, pp. 991-995. 
A Turkish translation of [#].
[#] de Vaux, C., and G.C. Anawati, “Indjīl,” in Encyclopaedia of Islam, 2nd ed., vol. 3, pp. 1205-1208.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 2348</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 17 and Ar. 18.</mssGroup>
[#] Zewi, Tamar, “Incomplete Topicalization in Biblical and modern Hebrew and several Arabic Bible Translations”, Australian Journal of Linguistics 19 (1999), pp. 241-253.
Discusses selected translation techniques in Saadiah Gaon’s translation and an unspecified modern one.
 [#] Walton, Brian, (ed.), Biblia Sacra Polyglotta (London, 1657), vol. 6, pp. 1-80 [paginated separately].
B. Walton, “De Lingua Arabica et Scripturae Versionibus Arabicis,” in Biblia Sacra Polyglotta [Prolegomena, XIV], vol. 1 (London, 1657), pp. 93-97 [Also reprinted separately from the Polyglot (Leipzig, 1777), pp. 633-664. See also, briefly, from Prolegomena V, §9, on p. 35 of original
[#] Weevers, John William, Septuaginta: Vetus Testamentutm Graecum, auctoritate Academiae Scientiarum Gottingensis editum, Vol. 1, Genesis, Göttingen: Vandenhoeck & Ruprecht, 1974, pp. 44-45.
Brief summary of primary and secondary sources
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library Or. 377 and 230</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF Ar. 9, 10, 11, and 16</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl. Poc. 219 and March. 440. </mssGroup>
 [#] Würthwein, Ernst, Der Text des Alten Testaments: Eine Einführung in die Biblia Hebraica, Stuttgart: Deutsche Bibelgesellschaft, 1988, pp. 114-115, 226-227 (Facs. 46).
The revised edition by Fischer, Alexander Achilles, Stuttgart: Deutsche Bibelgesellschaft 2009, does not add further material. 
Ms.: London, BL Add. 26116 
Blau in Targume Miqra

Historic Printings 
Check Fueck, 45-45
Aboussouan, Camille. 1982. Exposition Le Livre et le Liban jusqu'à 1900. Paris: Unesco.
Check adler
Levi della Vida 328-332
Darlow & Moule 1635,
Masch 
Bailey has a number of modern prints.
Add to Feghali to modern prints. 
Maltese
Balagna Coustou, Josée. 1984. L'imprimerie arabe en Occident: XVIe, XVIIe et XVIIIe siècles. Paris: Editions Maisonneuve & Larose.
1516
Giustiniani
[#] Bobzin, Hartmut. 1990. Agostino Giustiniani (1470-1536) und seine Bedeutung für die Geschichte der Arabistik. In XXIV. Deutscher Orientalistentag vom 26. bis 30. September 1988 in Köln. Ausgewählte Vorträge, edited by W. Diem and A. Falaturi. Stuttgart: F. Steiner Verlag Wiesbaden, 131-139.
[#] Bobzin, H, in Marzolph, Ulricht (ed.), Das gedruckte Buch im Vorderen Orient, Dortmund: xxx, 2002, p. 32-33.
[#] Lumini, Antonella (ed.), La Bibbia. Edizioni del XVI Secolo, XXX:XXX, 2000, pp. 133-135
Check for more literature
Mainz, in E. Hanebutt-Benz, Dagmar Glas, und G. Roper (eds.), Sprachen des Nahen Ostens und die Druckrevolution/ Middle Eastern Languages and the Print Revolution, Westhofen: xxxx, 2002, p.132.
[#] De Nave, Francine (ed.), Philologia Arabica. Arabische Studiën en Drukken in de Nederlanden in de 16de en 17de eeuw, Antwerpen: Museum Plantin-Moretus, 1986, pp.70-72. Check for more bibliography
[#] Thacher, John Boyd, Christopher Columbus: his life, his work, his remains, 2 vols., New York/London: G.P. Putnam’s sons , 1903, vol. 1, pp. 202-212. 
Gives a full account on the printing and an edition, with English translation, of the famous gloss on Ps 18:5 that contains the first mention of Christopher Columbus in print. 
[#] Vercellin, Giorgio, Venezia e l'origine della stampa in caratteri arabi. Padova: Il poligrafo, 2001, pp. 58-69.

1546 
Constantinople Polyglot
Cf. 
Wolf, Bibl. Hebr. 2, 354
Lelong masch 1, 363
Adlers reise, 221
1578 
Franciscus Junius 
Latin translation of Acts and Corr
1 John, Galatians, and Hebrews in manuscript, cf. Cuno, Franciscus Junius der Aeltere, Professor der Theologie und Pastor (1545-1602), Amsterdam, 1891, pp. 58-61. [see above, de Nave, pp. 100-101]
1582
Alphabetum Arabicum, Jacob Christman
Contains an excerpt of the Epistle to the Philippians 
[see above, de Nave, pp. 100-101]
1583
Epistola Pauli ad Galatas, item sex primaria capita Christianae religionis Arabice: quibus ad finem adiunctum est compendium grammatices Arabicae, authore Rutghero Spey. Addita quoque est interpretation Latina ad verbum (eodem authore) reddita, Heidelbergae: Excudebat Iacob Mylius, 1583.
Woodcut, Epistle to the Galatians in Arabic and Latin; edited by Rutgher Spey from an Arabic Ms. at the Palatine Library, Heidelberg. Today it is preserved as Vatican, BAV, 23. Appended with unacknowledged excerpts from Postel’s grammar. In the introduction he dwells on the missionary argument in order to persuade the Elector Palatine to erect an Arabic printing press. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 23</mssGroup>
	BA, pp. 339-341. 
	HCPE, Vol. 2, pp. 63
[#] Khoury, Raif  Georges, “G 1.6 Ruthger Speys Ausgabe des Paulus-Briefes an die Galater ist das erste mit arabischer Schrift gedruckte Buch in Deutschland,” in Mittler, Elmar (ed.), Bibliotheca Palatina. Katalog zur Ausstellung vom 8. Juli bis 2 November 1986 Heiliggeistkirche Heidelberg, Heidelberg: Edition Braus Heidelberg, 1986. Textband, p. 418-419. 

[see above, de Nave, pp. 104-105]
1590
Evangelium sanctum Domini Nostri Iesu Christi conscriptum a quatuor Evangelistis sanctis idest, Matthaeo, Marco, Luca, et Iohanne, Romae: In typographia Medicea 
Gospels in Arabic, edited by Giovan Battista Raymondi, intended for dissemination among Eastern Churches.  
	HCPE, Vol. 2, pp. 63
	BA, pp. 343-344
	[see above, lumini, pp. 252-253]
1591
Evangelium sanctum Domini Nostri Iesu Christi conscriptum a quatuor Evangelistis sanctis idest, Matthaeo, Marco, Luca, et Iohanne, Romae: In typographia Medicea 
Gospels in Arabic and Latin, see above. The bilingual version was intended for the European market. 
	HCPE, Vol. 2, pp. 63
BA, pp. 344-351
	[see above, lumini, p. 254]
Alder [#, see above], p. 73. 
Keywords: Gospels in Arabic and Latin, edited by Giovanni Battista Raymondi; 
1595
Specimen Characterum Arabicorum Officinae Plantinianae Franc. Raphelengij, Leiden: Franciscus Raphalengius, 1595. 
Contains specimens of Psalm 50 in Arabic. 
[see above, de Nave, pp. 129-131]
1608 
Kirsten, Petrus, tria specimina characterum arabicorum, Breslau 1608.
Contains John 17, as found in the Medici Gospels. 
1610
Quzḥayya Psalter 
Psalms in Karshūnī and Syriac, printed at the Monastery of Mar Antonius, Quzḥayya, supervised and sponsored by Sergius al-Rizzī, alumni of the Maronite College in Rome. The Arabic text is reprinted in de Largarde (1876, cf. # xxx).
	BA, pp. 351-354
HCPE, Vol. 2, pp. 79
Coakley, J.F., The Typograpy of Syriac: A historical catalogue of printing types, 1537-1958 (London: Oak Knoll Press/British Library, 2006), pp. 45-48.
	Döderlein, Johann Christoph. 1778/1779. Von Arabischen Psaltern. Repertorium fuer Biblische und Morgenlaendische Litteratur 2/4:1151-179/57-96.
Moukarzel, Joseph, “Le psautier syriaque garchouni édité à Qozhaya en 1610 :enjeux historiques et présentation du livre,” Mélanges de l’Université Saint-Joseph 63 (2010/11), pp. 511-xxx.
Nasrallah, 1-7, UB 3 A 10
Walbiner, Carsten 
1611
Epistola S. Judae Apostoli ex Mss. <mssGroup><place>Heidelbergensi arabico ad verbum translate</place>, Breslau: xxxx, 1611.</mssGroup>
Based on the same Ms. as Spey [#, see above], namely Vatican, BAV, Ar. 23.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 23.</mssGroup>
1612
D. Pauli Apostoli Epistola ad Titum, Arabicè, cum Ioannis Antonidae Alcmariani interlineari versione Latinâ ad verbum, Leiden: in officinal Platiniana Raphalendii, 1612. 
Epistle of Titus in Arabic and Latin, edited from a manuscript in the Bodleian Library. 
[see above, de Nave, p. 69]
Same manuscript as the one below? 
Johannis Apostoli & Evangelistae Epistolae Catholicae omnes, Arabicae ante aliquot secula factae, Ex antiquissimo Ms. exemplari descriptae et nunc demum Latinae redditae, Opera et studio Wilhelmi Bedwelli Halsingburgensis A Saxonis, Leiden: Ex Officina Platiniana Raphalengii, 1612. 
[see above, de Nave, pp. 69, 206-208]
1614
Liber Psalmorum Dauidis Regis et Prophetae: ex Arabico idiomae in Latinum translatus, Rome: ex typographia Savariana, excudebat Stephanus Paulinus, 1614. 
Vaccari, Alberto,. I Caratteri Arabi della "Typographia Savariana" Rivista degli Studi Orientali 10 (1923-25), pp. 37-47.
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, Ar. Xxx. </mssGroup>
1615
Erpenius, Thomas, Pauli Apostoli ad Romanos Epistola Arabice, Leiden: Typographia Erpeniana, 1615
[see above, de Nave, pp. 154-155]
1616 
Erpenius, Thomas, Jesu Christi Testamentum Arabice, Leiden: Typographia Erpeniana, 1616. 
[see above, de Nave, pp. 155-159]
Based on Or. 2369, Cambridge, University Library, G. 5. 33 and G. 5. 27
Mark translated into Latin by C. A. Bode, Lemgo, 1752. Manuscript today at Trinity College, Cambridge. ?
Reprints the Raimondi print.
1622 
Pentateuchus Mosis Arabicè, Leiden: ex typographia Erpenia, prostant Iohannem Maire, 1622. 
[see above, de Nave, pp. 164-167]
The edition is based on a manuscript from Scaliger‘s legacy. It contains a late Judaeo-Arabic translation that was transcribed in Arabic letters for the purpose of print. 
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library Or. 236</mssGroup>
1654
J.G. Nisselius and Th. Petraeus, eds., S. Jacobi Apostoli Epistolae Catholicae Versio Arabica & Aethiopica (Leiden, 1654).
________, S. Johannis Apostoli & Evangelistae Epistolae Catholicae Tres, Arabicae & Aethiopicae (Leiden, 1654).
________, S. Judae Apostoli Epistolae Catholicae Versio Arabice & Aethiopice (Leiden, 1654).
1663
Petraeus, Theodorus, Psalterium Davidis in lingua Coptica seu Aegyptiaca una cum versione Arabica, Leiden: Theodorus Petraeus, 1663. 
[see above, de Nave, pp. 190-191]
1703
Acta apostolorum epistola: Catholiccs et divi
Paulijussu sacr. cotigr. de prop, fide ad usum ecclesice nationis Maronitarum
edita cum Apocalypsi D. Joannis.
Arabic-Syriac

Biblia Sacra Arabica
A. Kleinhans, “De collaborationibus franciscanis in Bibliis arabicis anno 1671 editis,” in Antonianum 4 (1929), pp. 369-386.
Kowalsky, Nikolaus. 1969. Zur Vorgeschichte der arabischen Bibeluebersetzung der Propaganda von 1671. Neue Zeitschrift für Missionswissenschaft 16:268-274.
G. Mercati, “De versione bibliorum arabica a. 1671 edita,” in Revue Biblique n.s. 1 (1904), pp. 250-251.
A. Vaccari, “Un codice carsciunico della Casanatense e la Bibbia araba del 1671,” in Biblica 4 (1923), pp. 96-108.
________, “Una Bibbia araba per il primo Gesuita venuto al Libano,” in Mélange de l'Université St. Joseph 10 (1925), pp. 79-104.
________, “La storia d'una Bibbia araba,” in Biblica 11 (1930), pp. 350-355.
1751
Tukhi
Schelling, J.F., “Über die arabische Bibelausgabe von 1725”, in Johann Goffried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 10, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1782, pp. 154-164.
Paris Polyglot
Adrian Schenker, “The Polyglot Bibles of Antwerp, London, and Paris: 1568-1658.” In Magne Sæbø, ed., Hebrew Bible/Old Testament: The History of its Interpretation, vol. 2, From the Renaissance to the Enlightenment (Göttingen, 2008), pp. 774-784.
[#] Tychsen, D.G., “Über die Quelle aus welcher die Handschrift der arabischen Version in den Polylotten geflossen ist,” in Johann Goffried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 10, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1782, pp. 95-110.
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF Ar. 1, Florence, BML Or. 112 (formerly 21)</mssGroup>
 [] ------, “Untersuchung ob R. Saadjah Haggaon Verfasser der arabischen Uebersetzung des Pentateuchs in den Polyglotten sey,” in Johann Goffried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 11, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1782, pp. 82-112.

London Polyglot
1792
G. Roper, “The Vienna Arabic Psalter of 1792 and the Role of Typography in European-Arab Relations in the 18th Century and Earlier,” in J. Frimmel and M. Wögerbauer, eds., Kommunikation und Information im 18. Jahrhundert: Das Beispiel der Habsburgermonarchie. Wiesbaden, 2009. [pp.  77-89]
1850 
Shidyaq Psalter
Al-Baghdadi, Nadia, “The Cultural Function of Fiction: From Bible to Libertine Literature. Historical Criticism and Social Critique in Aḥmed Fāris al-Šidyāq,” Arabica 46 (1999), pp. 375-401.
[#]------, "Print, Script and the Limits of Free-thinking in Arabic Lettres of the 19th century : The case of al-Shidyaq." Al-Abhath 48-49 (2000): 99-122.
1851 
Shidyaq NT

1860 
Smith Van Dyck NT
[#] Hall, Isaac H., “The Arabic Bible of Drs. Eli Smith and Cornelius V. A. Van Dyck,” JAOS 11 (1882-85), pp. 276-286. 
 [#] Jessup, Henry Harris, “The Arabic Bible—Its Translation and the Translators,” in Fifty-Three Years in Syria, New York, Chicago, et al.: Fleming H. Revell Company, 1910, vol. 1, pp. 66-78.
[#] Leavy, Margaret R., Eli Smith and the Arabic Bible (New Haven: Yale Divinity School, 1993).
http://www.library.yale.edu/div/pub/OccPub4.pdf
[#] I.A. Saliba, “The Bible in Arabic: The 19th Century Protestant Translation,” The Muslim World 65 (1975): 254-263.
[#] Smith, Eli, “Aus einem Briefe von Dr. E. Smith,” ZDMG 10 (1856), pp. 813-814.
[#] Smith, Eli and C.V.A. van Dyck, Brief Documentary History of the Translation of the Scriptures into the Arabic Language by Rev. Eli Smith, D.D., and Rev. C.V.A. Van Dyck, D.D., Beirut: American Presbyterian Mission Press, 1900.
Contains reports of Smith and van Dyck as to the progress of the translation enterprise.
http://archive.org/details/briefdocumentary00pres 
 [#] Torrey, Charles, C., “A New Edition of the Arabic Bible,” The American Journal of Theology 23 (1919), pp. 105-107.
[#] Yaffe, A., “The American Mission Bible Translation to Arabic,” Pe‘amim 83 (2000), pp. 57-69 [in Hebrew].
[#] Wright, William. “The Late Dr. Van Dyck: The Translator of the Arabic Bible.” Sunday at Home (Jan 1896), pp. 215-216.
1865
Smith van Dyck bible 
Biblio, see above
1862 
St. Matthew in Algerian Arabic
1865
St. Matthew in Algerian Arabic
1876-1880 
Jesuit Bible
[#] Julien, M, La nouvelle mission de la Compagnie de Jésus en Syrie (1831-1895), Paris/Lyon:xxx, 1899, Vol. 2, pp. 110-113.
[#] al-Khūrī, Sāmī, “al-shaykh Ibrāhīm al-Yazījī wa-l-maṭbaʿa al-kāthūlīkiyya baina 1872 wa-1881,” al-Mashriq 65 (1991), pp. 127-128. 
1897
Luke in Tunisian arabic
1899
Luke in Tunisian Arabic
1902
Luke in Moroccan Arabic
1905
Luke in Egyptian arabic
1907
Parts of the new Testament in Moroccan Arabic
1908 
Luke in Algerian Arabic
Luke in Egyptian arabic
1911
St John’s in Algerian Arabic
Luke in Tunesian Arabic
1913
Acts in Algerian Arabic
1914
Genesis and Psalms in Moroccan Arabic
1918
1st epistle of John in Moroccan Arabic
1920
Matt in Moroccan Arabic
1923
Various parts of the new T in Egyptian arabic
Cor, Gal, Eph in Moroccan Arabic
1925 
Matt in Algerian Arabic 
Exodus in Egyptian Arabic
Epistles Philippians through to Philemon in Moroccan Arabic
1927
Mark in Sudanese Arabic
1929-1937
Saydon, il-Kotba Mqaddsa bil-Malti
Review http://journals.cambridge.org/download.php?file=%2F1566_7592F335ABE963E6DC995098BEC866B1_journals__BSO_BSO9_03_S0041977X00078733a.pdf&cover=Y&code=34b6c9d38a98344bff41ae708a1ef5e1
1931 
Mark  in Algerian Arabic
1932
NT in Egyptian Arabic
NT in Moroccan Arabic
1933
Psalms in Egyptian arabic
1935
Romans 
1935-1937
Romans, Cor, and Gal in Egyptian arabiv
Editions, Chrestomathies 
Link these later to the secondary literature 
[#] Blau, A Handbook of Early Middle Arabic (Jerusalem: The Max Schloessinger Memorial Foundation/ The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 2002), pp. 68-71, 95-96, 98-106, 145-154. 
Contains specimens of the Violet fragment (pp. 68-71), an Arabic translation of Daniel (pp. 95-96), Saadiah’s Tafsīr (pp. 98-106); and an early Judaeo-Arabic translation of the book of Proverbs (pp. 145-154). All accompanied by linguistic notes. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Violet fragment</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Sinai</place>, Ar. 2</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cambridge</place>, CUL, T-S Ar. 21.183 and Ar. 53.8, and Mosseri vi, 45</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ebr. II C 1-2.</mssGroup>
 [#] L. Cheikho, Chrestomathia arabica (Beirut, 1897), pp. 185-208. [contains several Old and New Testament selections from various sources]
Matt. 16:14-20, based on an unspecified 9th manuscript at the BO, which is missing today. 
[#] J. Derenbourg, ed., Œuvres complètes de R. Saadia Ben Iosef al-Fayyoûmî, vol. 1, Version arabe du Pentateuche (Paris, 1893).
H. Derenbourg and M. Lamberts, eds., Œuvres complètes de R. Saadia Ben Iosef al-Fayyoûmî, vol. 5, Version arabe du livre de Job (Paris, 1900).
________, Œuvres complètes de R. Saadia Ben Iosef al-Fayyoûmî, vol. 6, Version arabe des Proverbes (Paris, 1894).
[#] Bloch, Josef, Die samaritanisch-arabische Pentateuchübersetzung. Deuteronomium I-X, nach Handschriften in Berlin, Gotha, Kiel, Leiden und Paris mit Einleitung und Noten (Berlin: M. Poppelauer’s Buchhandlung, 1901).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Petersmann A3 and Or. Fol. 534</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Kiel</place>, Universitätsbibliothek, Ms. 14</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Barberini Or. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 5</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 1222</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Gotha</place>, Forschungsbibliothek, Ar. 1088.</mssGroup>
	Review: Kahle, Paul, ZfHB 6 (1902), pp. 6-9.
 [#] Drint, Adriana, The Mount Sinai Arabic Version of IV Ezra, 2 vols, CSCO Scriptores Arabici Vols. 48-49, (Louvain: Secrétariat du Corpus SCO, 1997).
A revised version of her PhD-Thesis, see below.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 7 and Ar. 589</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Spreng. 30</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Or. 251 and Hunt. 260</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 462 and Borg. Ar. 95</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate</place>, Bibl. 75, 77, 86, 89 and Theol. 286</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Beirut</place>, Bibliothèque Orientale, Ms. 419</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 51.</mssGroup>
[#] ------, The Mount Sinai Arabic Version of IV Ezra. Text, Translation and Introduction, PhD-Thesis, Rijksuniversiteit Groningen, 1959. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 7 and Ar. 589, Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Sprenger 30</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Or. 251 and Hunt. 260</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 462 and Borg. Ar. 95</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate</place>, Bibl. 75, 77, 86, 89 and Theol. 286</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Beirut</place>, Bibliothèque Orientale, Ms. 419</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 51.</mssGroup>

George Jacob, An Arabic Bible Chrestomathy with a Glossary (Berlin, 1888).
[] Georg Otho, Palaestra Linguarum Orientalium, hoc est quatur primorum capita Geneseos [incl. Arabic] (Frankfurt am Main, 1702). [Text on pp. 89-106, Arabic-Latin glossary on pp. 88-100 of Glossarium section.]
 
[#] ------, An Arabic Version of the Acts of the Apostles and the Seven Catholic Epistles from an Eighth or Ninth Century MS. in the Convent of St. Katherine on Mount Sinai, with a Treatise on the Triune Nature of God, and Translation from the Same Codex, Studia Sinaitica 7, (London: C.J. Clay and Sons, 1899) 
Reprinted: Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2004.
Reviewed: Ryssel, V., Theologische Literaturzeitung 20 (1895), cols. 321-327. 
Contains an edition of the text and several plates of the manuscript.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 154.</mssGroup>
[#] Lerchundi, J. and F.J. Simonet, Crestomatía arábigo-española, Granada: xxx, 1881, pp. viii-ix, 2-10. 
Contains an edition of parts of Madrid, BNE, Ms. 4971.
[#] Shehadeh, Hasib (ed.), The Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch, 2vols., Jerusalem The Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities: 1989-2002.
Review: Hopkins, Simon,מהדורה שלמה של התרגום הערבי לתורה נוסח שומרון. Cathedra 115 (2005), pp. 217-221.
					
				
			
		

[#] Frantsouzoff, Serge; Polosin, V. V. and Serikoff, N.I. (eds), The Petersburg Arabic Illuminated Psalter (St Petersburg: Kvarta, 2005).
Mss. <mssGroup><place>St. Petersburg</place>, Institut of Oriental Manuscripts, A 187.</mssGroup>
[#]------, The Arabic Psalter: A Supplement to the Facsimile Edition of Manuscript A187 “The Petersburg Arabic Illuminated Psalter." (St Petersburg: Kvarta, 2005)
Mss. <mssGroup><place>St. Petersburg</place>, Institut of Oriental Manuscripts, A 187.</mssGroup>
G.E. Post, فهرس الكتاب المقدس (Beirut, 1872-1875).
Ayad, Boulos Aya, ed., Sifr Ayyūb. Qām bi-tarjamatihi min al-suryānīya ila al-‘arabīya Tūmā Fusṭāṭī fi al-qarn al-tāsi‘ al-mīlādī (Cairo, 1975). [Edition of a ninth century translation of the Book of Job from Syriac into Arabic by Thomas of Fusṭāṭ, from St. Catherine’s Monastery, Mt. Sinai, ms. 514.]
[#] de Lagarde, Paul, Psalterium, Iob, Proverbia arabice, Göttingen: Typis Expressit Officina Academica Gottingensis, 1876.
Contains (1) four editions of the Psalms ([#] Savary de Breves; [#] Paris Polyglot; [#] Aleppo 1706; [#] that of Abdallāh b. al-Faḍl; (2) two editions of the Job (from a codex from Berlin and the Paris Polyglot); (3) Proverbs from the Paris Polyglot.
[#] ------, Psalmi 1-49 arabice (Göttingen, 1875). 
[#] Leemhuis, F., Klijn, A.F.J., and van Gelder, G.J.H., The Arabic Text of the Apocalypse of Baruch: Edited and Translated with a Parallel Translation of the Syriac Text (Leiden:Brill, 1986).
Contains an edition and translation of Ms. Sinai, Ar. 589.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 589.</mssGroup>
Review: 
von Sebastian Brock
Artikel Artikel
Sprache: English  
Veröffentichung: Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies, v52 n01 (19890224)
[#] Frank, Richard M., The Wisdom of Jesus Ben Sirach (Sinai ar. 155 IX-X cent.), 2 vols. (CSCO 357-358 = Scr. Arb. 30-31; Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1974).
Contains an edition and translation of the Arabic Ben Sira, as based on Ms. Sinai, Ar. 155.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 155. </mssGroup>
 [#] Wright, William (ed.), The Book of Jonah in Four Oriental Versions, namely Chaldee, Syriac, Aethiopic and Arabic, with Glossaries, London/Leipzig: Williams and Norgate/Brockhaus, 1857, pp. 109-148.
Based on a Ms. In the Bodleian. Which one?
Art, paleography, codicology
[#] Arnold, Thomas Walker, The Old and New Testaments in Muslim religious art, London: British Acad. by Oxford Univ. Press, 1932.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 387 (p. 13, pl. 1).</mssGroup>
[#] ------, “The pictorial art of the Jacobite and Nestorian Churches,” Byzantinische Zeitschrift 30 (1929), pp. 595-597.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 387.</mssGroup>
[#]------, Painting in Islam: a study of the place of pictorial art in Muslim culture, Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1928. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Add. 11856 (p. 58, pl. 8b) and Florence, BML, Or. 387.</mssGroup>
[#] Baumstark, Anton, "Erbe christlicher Antike im Bildschmuck eines arabischen Evangelienbuches des 14. Jahrhunderts," OC, III. Serie, 13 (1938), pp. 1-38.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 1571.</mssGroup>
[#] ------, “Frühchristlich-syrische Prophetenillustrationen durch stehende Autorenbilder” ," OC, III. Serie, 9 (1934), pp. 99-104.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Diez A. Fol. 41.</mssGroup>
[#] ------, “Ein apokryphes Herrenleben in mesopotamischer Federzeichnung vom Jahre 1299,” OC, NS 1 (1911), pp. 249-271. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 387. </mssGroup>
[#] ------, “Palaestinensia” Römische Quartalschrift 20 (1906), pp. 123-149, 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Add. 11850 and Jerusalem, Greek Patriarchate, Ar. 9. </mssGroup>
 [#] Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Die Wunder der Schöpfung. Handschrifen der Bayrischen Staatsbibliothek aus dem islamischen Kulturkreis, Wiesbaden: Harrossowitz, 2010. (English title: The Wonders of Creation. Manuscripts of the Bavarian State Library from the Islamic world)
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Cod. Ar. 233 (56-57) and Cod. Ar. 236 (pp. 58-59).</mssGroup>
[#] Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, Il Libro della Bibbia. Esposizione di Manuscritti e di Edizioni a Stampa della Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana dal Secolo III al Secolo XVI, Vatican: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1972.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Barberini, Or. 1 (p. 39, pl. 37) and Barberini, Or. 2 (p. 49, pl. 45), Ar. 13 (p. 13, pl. 14), Ar. 18 (p. 19, pl. 17), Copt. 9 (p. 38, pl. 35). </mssGroup>
[#] Brovenko, N. M, “An Arabic Bible in the Collection of the St. Petersburg Branch of the Institute of Oriental Studies: The Problems of Restoration,” Manuscripta Orientalia 4 (1998), pp. 35-38.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226.</mssGroup>
[#] Cramer, Maria, Koptische Buchmalerei. Illuminationen in Manuskripten des christlich-koptischen Ägypten vom 4. bis 19. Jahrhundert, Recklinghausen: Verlag Aurel Bongers, 1964.
Includes many biblical bilinguals. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Hunt 17 (pls. II, IV, XI, 97, and 101) and Marsh. Or. 6 (pls. 17 and 40)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Copt. 8 (pls. 95 and 100) and Copt. 9 (pls. V, X, XII, XIII, 18, 19, 87, and 98) and Copt. 12 (pl. 14)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1316 (pls. VI, XV, 30, 89, 94, 99, 104, 109, 110, 111, 119, 124, 132, 141, 142, and 155) and Or. 1317 (pl. 93)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF Copt. 2 (pl. 37) and Copt. 13 (pls. XIV, XVI, XVII, XVIII, 120, 125, 129, 133, 135, 136, and 143)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institute Catholique, Copt. Ar. 1 (pls. 92, 96, 103, 105, 106, 107, 108, 118, 121, 122, 123, 130, 131, 134, 138, 139, and 140), Cairo, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 92 (pls. 21, 22, and 23), Bibl. 91 (pls. 26 and 27), Bibl. 92 (pls. 33 and 34), Bibl. 94 (pls. 84 and 137), and Bibl. 95 (pl. 102).</mssGroup>
[#] Fleischer, Heinrich Leberecht, “Zur Geschichte der arabischen Schrift,” ZDMG 18 (1864), pp. 288-291 (reprinted in Kleinere Schriften, Leipzig: Verlag von S. Hirzel, 1888), Vol. 3, pp. 395-399).  
Furnishes a paleographic description of a codex in the possession of Tischendorf, containing an early version of Job. This manuscript is today Ms. London, British Library, Add. 26116. Cf. [#, see below] von Baudissin and [#, see below] Monferrer Sala. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, British Library, Add. 26116.</mssGroup>
[#] Franzsouzoff, Serge, “Les chiffres coptes dans les manuscrits arabes, chrétiens et musulmans,” forthcoming Parole d’Orient
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Russian National Library, Ar. N.S. 232 and Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226.</mssGroup>
[#] Garitte, Gérard, “Un évangéliaire grec-arabe du Xe siècle (cod. Sin. ar. 116),” in: Treu, Kurt et al. (eds.), Studia Codicologica, (Texte und Untersuchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur, 124, Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 1977), pp. 207-225.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 116.</mssGroup>
[#] Holter, Kurt, “Die Galen-Handschrift und Makamen des Ḥarīrī der Wiener Nationalbibliothek,” Jahrbuch der Kunsthistorischen Sammlungen in Wien 11 (1937), pp. 1-48.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 387.  </mssGroup>
[#] von Horstkamp-Sydow, Ernst, “Seltenheiten und Kuriositäten der Kaiserlichen Öffentlichen Bibliothek zu St. Petersburg,” Zeitschrift für Bücherfreunde 12 (1908-09), p. 26-34
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ar. N.S. 327 (pl. 8).</mssGroup>
[#] James, David, Qurʾāns of the Mamlūks (London: Alexandria Press in association with Thames and Hudson, 1988). 
Includes comparisons to Arabic Gospel manuscripts. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Coptic Orthodox Patriarche</place>, Bibl. 196</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 91</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Istanbul</place>, Topkapı Sarayı Library, Ahmet III 3519.</mssGroup>
Leroy 
[#] Leroy, Jules, “Un évangélaire arabe de la bibliothèque de Topqapi Sarayi à décor byzantin et islamique,” Syria 44 (1967), pp. 119-130.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Istanbul</place>, Topkapı Sarayı Library, Ahmet III 3519 (various plates).</mssGroup>
[#] Ministère d’Etat Affaires Culturelles, L’Art Copte en Égypte. 2000 ans de christianisme, Paris: Institut du Mond Arabe/ Gallimard, 2000. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 12 (p. 57) and Copt. 1 (pp. 77-78).</mssGroup>
[#] Nelson, Robert S., “An Icon at Mt. Sinai and Christian Painting in Muslim Egypt During the Thirteenth and Fourteenth Centuries,” Art Bulletin 65 (1983), pp. 201-218.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institut Catholique, Copt.-Ar. 1 (p. 204, pls. 4-7 and p. 209, pl. 15)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 12 (p. 216, pl. 28)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 90 (p. 215, pl. 8) and Bibl. 94 (p. 205, pl. 8).</mssGroup>
[#] Redin, Egor Kuz'mich, “Miniatiury apokrificheskago arabskago evangeliia detstva Khrista Lavrencianskoi bibloteki vo Florencii [The miniatures of the apocryphal Infancy Gospel at the Laurentian Library Florence],” Imperatorskoe Russkoe Archeologicheskoe Obshchestvo, Zapiski 7 (1895), pp. 57-71. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BMF, Or. 387.</mssGroup>
 [#] Smith Lewis, Agnes, and Margaret Dunlop Gibson, Forty-one facsimiles of dated Christian Arabic manuscripts. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1907
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 69 (p. 13, pl. 8), Ar. 82 (pp. 23-24, pl. 12), Ar. 91 (p. 49, pl. 25), Ar. 95 (p. 37, pl. 19), Ar. 97 (p. 19, pl. 10), Ar. 99 (pp. 45-48, pls. 23 and 24), Ar. 104 (p. 41, pl. 21), Ar. 106 (pp. 11-12, pl. 7), Ar. 122 (pp. 33-34, pl. 17)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1327 (p. 55, pl. 28).</mssGroup>
[#] Hunt, Lucy-Anne, “A Christian Arab Gospel Book: Cairo, Coptic Museum MS Bibl. 90 in its Mamluk Context,” Mamluk Studies Review 13:2 (2009), pp. 105-132
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institut Catholique, Copt.-Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 90 (pp. 124-129, pls. 1-6)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Istanbul</place>, Topkapı Sarayı Library, Ahmet III 3519 (pp. 130-132, pls. 7-9).</mssGroup>
[#]------, “Cultural Transmission: Illustrated Biblical Manuscripts from the medieval Eastern Christian and Arab Worlds,” in Sharpe John L. and Kimberly Van Kampen (eds.), The Bible as Book: The Manuscript Tradition (London and New Castle, DE, 1998), pp. 123-136 (reprinted in idem, Byzantium, Eastern Christianity and Islam: Art at the Crossroads of the Medieval Mediterranean (London: The Pindar Press, 2000), Vol. 2, pp. 1-22).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institut Catholique, Copt.-Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 94</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Diez A fol. 41</mssGroup>; ; Oxford, Bodleian Library, Hunt. 17 (p. 18, pl. 4); London, BL, Add. 11856 (p.19, pl. 5) and Istanbul, Topkapı Sarayı Library, Ahmet III 3519 (p. 20, pls. 6-7).
[#]------, “Introducing the Catalogue, in progress, of the illustrated Manuscripts in the Coptic Museum,” Parole de l’Orient 19 (1994), pp. 401-413 (reprinted in idem, Byzantium, Eastern Christianity and Islam: Art at the Crossroads of the Medieval Mediterranean (London: The Pindar Press, 2000), Vol. 2, pp. 353-364).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institut Catholique, Copt.-Ar. 1 and Cairo, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 75 (pp. 412-413, pls. 6-7), Bibl. 90 (pp. 410-411, pls. 4-5) and Bibl. 94 (pp. 408-</mssGroup>
[#]------, "Christian-Muslim Relations in Painting in Egypt of the Twelfth to mid-Thirteenth Centuries," Cahiers Archeologiques 33 (1985), pp. 111-155.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Hunt. 17 (p. 131, pls. 17-18)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institut Catholique, Copt.-Ar. 1 (p. 120, pl. 7</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 123</place>, pl. 8</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 124</place>, pl. 9, p. 125, pls. 10-11, p. 126, pls. 12-13</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 127</place>, pl. 14)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Copt. 8 and Copt. 9 (p. 132, pl. 19)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 93, Bibl. 94 (p. 128, pls. 15-16), and Bibl. 147.</mssGroup>
[#]------, “The Commissioning of a Late Twelfth Century Gospel Book: The Frontispieces of Ms Paris, Bibl. Nat. Copte 13,” Byzantinische Forschungen 10 (1985) pp. 113-140 (reprinted in idem, Byzantium, Eastern Christianity and Islam: Art at the Crossroads of the Medieval Mediterranean (London: The Pindar Press, 2000), Vol. 1, pp. 115-157).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Copt. 13</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institut Catholique, Copt.-Ar. 1 (p. 133-134, pl. 1-2)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Washington</place>, Freer Gallery, No. 55 (p. 135, pl. 3)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ar. NF. 327</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Hunt. 17</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and  Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 94.</mssGroup>
[#]-------, “Manuscript Production by Christians in 13th-14th Century Greater Syria and Mesopotamia and Related Areas”, Aram 9 (1997), pp. 289-336 (reprinted in idem, Byzantium, Eastern Christianity and Islam: Art at the Crossroads of the Medieval Mediterranean (London: The Pindar Press, 2000), Vol. 2, pp. 153-197)
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BMF, Or. 387 (p. 317, pl. 7)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 1571 (p. 318, pl. 9</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 319</place>, pl. 10</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 321</place>, pl. 13</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 325</place>, pl. 17</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 327</place>, pl. 19</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 3287</place>, pl. 20</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>p. 329</place>, pls. 22-23)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 92, and Istanbul, Topkapı Sarayı Library, Ahmet III 3519 (p. 335, pl. 29).</mssGroup>
[#]------, “Byzantine-Islamic influences in the illustration of MS Paris, Institut Catholique Copte-Arabe 1,” in XVI. Internationaler Byzantinistencongress, Akten 11/5, Jahrbuch der Östereichischen Byzantinistik 32/5 (1983), Vol. 5, pp. 339-341.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institut Catholique, Copt.-Ar. 1 (pls. 1-4) and BNF, Copt. 13</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 94 (pl. 5).</mssGroup>
[#]------, The Illustration of a Thirteenth – Century New Testament Manuscript from Cairo (Paris, Institut Catholique Copte-Arabe 1), (unpubl. Dissertation, University of London, London, 1981)
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, Institut Catholique, Copt.-Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Bibl. 94</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ar. N.S. 327</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Copt. 9.</mssGroup>
[#] Koningsveld, P. Sj. van, “Andalusian-Arabic Manuscripts from Christian Spain: A comparative Intercultural Approach,” Israel Oriental Studies 12 (1992), pp. 75-110.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 238 (no. 56)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Borg. Ar. 129 (no. 68) and Ar. 5 (no. ?).</mssGroup>
[#] Khoury, Raif  Georges, “G 1.5 Apostel-Briefe in arabischer Übersetzung,” in Mittler, Elmar (ed.), Bibliotheca Palatina. Katalog zur Ausstellung vom 8. Juli bis 2 November 1986 Heiliggeistkirche Heidelberg, Heidelberg: Edition Braus Heidelberg, xxxx. Textband, p. 418; Bildband, p.274.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 23.</mssGroup>
[#] Lafontaine-Dosogne, Jacqueline, “Recherches sur l'illustration de l'Évangile arabe de l'Enfance à Florence (Laur. Or. 387)”, The International Symposium on Armenian Art, (Erevan: Acad., 1981), Vol. 2, pp. 170-172
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 387</mssGroup>
[#]------, “The Cycle of the Infancy of Christ,” (ed.) Underwood, Paul A, The Kariye Djami, Vol. 4, Studies in the art of the Kariye Djami and its intellectual background (London: Routledge & Paul, 1975), pp. 195-241.
[#] ------, Le cycle des mages dans l'Evangile arabe de l'Enfance du Christ de Florence (Laur. Or. 387), Mélanges A. Abel, 2 vols, (Bruxelles: Publications du Centre pour l’Etude de Problèmes du Monde Musulman Contemporain, 1975), Vol. 2, pp. 287-294.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 387.</mssGroup>
[#] Pollock, James W., “Two Christian Arabic manuscripts in the Bryn Mawr Library,” Journal of American Oriental Society 110 (1990), pp.330-331.
On two manuscripts which were originally part of Arnold Mettler-Specker collection, on loan at Zurich library. They were auctioned in 1948 and eventually donated to Bryn Mawr College Library. One of them, formerly Ms. Zurich, Or. 94, contains a 9th century copy of the Psalms in Arabic [mentioned in GCAL:1, p. 114, #]. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Bryn Mawr College Library</place>, BV 47</mssGroup>
[#] Polosin, Valery, “The Arabic Bible: Turning Again to an Old Controversy,” Manuscripta Orientalia 6 (2000), pp. 3-18.
Contains a description of Ms. St Petersburg, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226 and its relations to Ms. Vatican, BAV, Ar. 467-468 (cf. [#] Vaccari and [#] Krachkovksi).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226 and Vatican, BAV, Ar. 467-468.</mssGroup>
[#] ________ and Efim Rezvan, “To the CD-ROM Edition of the St. Petersburg Arabic Bible,” Manuscripta Orientalia 3 (1997), pp. 40-47.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226 and Vatican, BAV, Ar. 467-468.</mssGroup>
[#] Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Jüdische Handschriften. Restaurieren. Bewahren. Präsentieren, Berlin: Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, 2002. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Ms or.fol. 1320 (pp. 48-49), Ms. or. fol. 534 (p. 59), 	 	 	</mssGroup>
[#] St. Catherine's Monastery at Mount Sinai: It's Manuscripts and their Conservation: Papers Given in Memory of Professor Ihor Ševčenko. [S.l.]: Saint Catherine's Foundation, 2011.
	Portrait of St. Luke (p. 49) from Sinai NF Arab. 14.
[#] Stocks, H., “Die Magierminiaturen des Cod. Med. Pal. 387, die literarische Ueberlieferung und der ‘Orientalische Typus,” Byzantisch-neugriechiesche Jahrbücher 2 (1921), pp. 329-343.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 387.</mssGroup>
[#] Theodoraki, G., Les Enluminures du ms. Copte 13 de la B.N., unpubl. PhD-thesis, University of Paris, 1966. 
[#] von Tischendorf, Konstantin, Anecdota sacra et profana ex Oriente et Occidente allata sive Notitia codicum Graecorum, Arabicorum, Syriacorum, Copticorum, Hebraicorum, Athiopicorum, Latinorum, Leipzig: Sumptibus Hermanni Fries, 1861.
Contains a description of Tischendorf’s codices, some of them containing early biblical books in Arabic.  
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, RNL, A. N.S. 327 and Leipzig, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. Tisch. 31 and 37.</mssGroup>
[#] Tisserant, Eugene, Specimina Codicum Orientalium, Bonn: A. Marcus et E. Weber, 1914.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Barberini Or. 1 (p. xiii, pl. 1) and Or. 2 (p. xlvii, pl. 80), Ar. 4 (p.xlii, pl. 61b), Ar. 18 (p. xxxiii, pl. 45a), Ar. 581 (p.xli, pl. 59a), Ar. 788 (p. xli, pl. 59c), Borg. Ar. 48 (p. xlii, pl. 61d), Borg. Ar. 71 (pp. xxxix-xl, pl. 56b), Borg. Ar. 95 (p. xxxix, pl. 55), and Borg. Ar. 129 (p. xxxviii, pl. 53.</mssGroup>
[#] Vida, Girgio Levi della, “Manoscritti arabi di origine spagnola nella Biblioteca Vaticana,” in Collectanea Vaticana in Honorem Anselmi M. Card. Albareda a Bibliotheca Apostolica, Vatican: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1942, pp. 133- 189, (reprinted in Note di storia letteraria arabo-isponica, Rome: Instituto per l’Oriente, 1971, pp. 1-54).
Deals with Arabic manuscripts of Iberian provenance in the BAV, among them some biblical codices are mentioned. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Borg. Ar. 67, Borg. Ar. 129, Ar. 5, Lat. 12900 (formerly Chapter of the Cathedral of Siguenze, Ms. 150) and Lat. 13001</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Add. 9060.</mssGroup>
[#] Vajda, Georges, Album de Paléographie Arabe, Paris: Librairie d’Amérique et d’Orient, 1958. 
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 6725 (pl. 4).</mssGroup>
[#] Westwood, John Obadiah, Palaeographia sacra pictorial, being a series of illustrations of the ancient versions of the Bible, copied from Illuminated Manuscripts, executed between the fourth and sixteenth Centuries, 	London: Smith, 1845. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Add. 11856 (p. 29)</mssGroup>
[#] Weitzmann, Kurt, “An Early Copto-Arabic Miniature in Leningrad,” Ars Islamica 10 (1943), pp. 119-134. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ar. NS. 327</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Diez A 41.</mssGroup>
Part Two
Christian-Arabic
Generalia
[#] Blau, Joshua, “Sind uns Reste arabischer Bibelübersetzungen aus vorislamischer Zeit erhalten geblieben?,” Le Muséon 86 (1973), pp. 67-72. [reprint: 
For a Spanish translation by Magdalena López Pérez, see “¿Se conservan restos de traducciones árabes de la Biblia de época preislámica?,” Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 4 (2007): 359-364, available at http://www.uco.es/investiga/grupos/hum380/collectanea/sites/default/files/Translations_0.pdf.]
[#] Euringer, Sebastian, “Zum Stammbaum der arabischen Bibelhandschriften Vat. ar. 468 and 467,” Zeitschrift für Semitistik und verwandte Gebiete 7 (1929), pp. 259-273.
On the disput between [#] Vaccari and [#] Krachkovskii.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 467 and Ar. 468 and St Petersburg, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226.</mssGroup>
[#] Frantsuzov, S.A. “Pripiski k arabskoj rukopisnoj Biblii (D226) iz sobranija Instituta vostochnykh rukopisej RAN kak istoricheskij istochnik” [Marginal Notes in the Arabic Bible (St Petersburg, Oriental Institute, MS D226) as a Historical Source]. Vestnik PSTGU, III: Filologija. 3(17) (2009): 38-57 [with English summary].
G. Graf, Geschichte des christlichen arabischen Literatur, vol. 1 (Vatican City, 1944), pp. 85-195.
[#] Krachkovskii, Ignatii, “On a translation of the Bible into Arabic to the time of Caliph al-Maʾmūn” [in Russian], Christianskij Vostok 6 (1918), pp. 189-196.
[#]------. “Original vatikanskoj rukopisi arabskogo perevoda Biblii [The original of a Vatican manuscript of an Arabic translation of the Bible],” Doklady Akademii Nauk series B (1925), pp. 84-87 (reprinted in Original vatikanskoj rukopisi arabskogo perevoda Biblii (L’original du manuscrit de Vatican de la traduction arabe de la Bible). In : Izbrannye sochinenija (OEuvres choisies), t. VI. Moscou–Léningrad : Éditions de l’Académie des Sciences de l’URSS, 1960, pp.472–477
Also refered to in [#]------, Über Arabische Handschriften gebeugt. Erinnerung an Bücher und Menschen, Leipzig: Koehler & Amelang, 1949, pp. 54.
[#] Monferrer-Sala, J.P. “En torno a las versiones medievales ‘árabes cristianas’ del Antiguo Testamento: Hacia un estado de la cuestíon.” Pages 23-33 in M.A. García Peinado and E. Ortega Arjonilla, eds. Panorama actual de la investigación en traduccíon e interpretación. Málaga, 2003. Vol. II.
[#] Polosin, Val.V. “Starejshaja rukopis' polnoj Biblii na arabskom jazyke (vozvrash'enie k davnishnej diskussii)” [The Oldest Integral Manuscript Copy of the Arabic Bible: Revisiting an Old Debate]. Khristianskij Vostok. New Series. 5(XI) (2003-2008): 76-85.
I. Shahid, “The Problem of an Arabic Bible and Liturgy before the Rise of Islam,” in Samir Khalil Samir (ed.), Acts du premier congrès international d’études chrétiennes, Goslar, September, 1980 (OCA 218; Rome, 1982), pp. 481-490.
Vaccari, A. “Una Bibbia araba per il primo Gesuita venuto al Libano,” in Mélanges de l’Université Saint-Joseph 10 (1925), pp. 79-104.
Pentateuch
[#] Bassal, Ibrahim, “Syriac-Aramaic words in an early Christian Arabic copy of the Pentateuch (Ms Sin Ar. 2),” Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 10 (2013), pp. 17-36.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 2, Ar. 3, and Ar. 10</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 9 and 14</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Copenhagen</place>, Royal Library, Ar. 75</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Munich</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 234.</mssGroup>
[#]-------, “Hebrew and Aramaic Words in Christian Arabic Bible Translations,” (eds.) Ayelet Oettinger & Danny Bar-Maoz in Mittuv Yosef, Yosef Tobi Jubilee Volume, (Haifa: University of Haifa, 2012), III, pp. 95-119.
[#]------, “Hebrew and Aramaic elements in the vernacular and written Christian Arabic,” in (eds.) Heltzer, Michael and Meir Malul Teshūrōt la-Avishur. Studies in the Bible and Ancient Near East, in Hebrew and Semitic Languages, (Tel-Aviv – Jaffa: Archaeological Center Publications, 2004), pp. 17-19 [in Hebrew]
[#] ------, Hebrew and Aramaic elements in the Vernacular Christian Arabic in Israel and in the Written Christian Arabic in the Holy Land, Syria and Lebanon, unpubl. PhD-Thesis, University of Haifa 
[#] L. Cheikho, “Deux anciens manuscrits arabes du Pentateuche,” in Mashriq 21 (1923), pp. 141-147.
 [#] R. Edelmann, “משהו על התרגומים הערבים של חמשה חומשי תורה” [Features in Arabic Translations of the Pentateuch], in Melilah 5 (1955), pp. 45-50.
Basically a Hebrew version of his English article [#], see there. 
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Copenhagen</place>, Royal Library, Ar. 75</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 377 (Warner 377) and Or. 230 (Scaliger Arab. 230). </mssGroup>
[#] Graf, Georg “Die arabische Pentateuchübersetzung in cod. Monac. arab. 234,” in Biblische Zeitschrift 15 (1919-21), pp. 97-115, 193-212, 291-330.
On an Iberian copy of an Arabic Pentateuch of East-Syriac provenance.
(compare [#] Monferrer-Sala)
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 234 and Ar. 238</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cambridge</place>, CUL, Add. 3289</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Dq. 106.</mssGroup>
[#] Holmes, Robert, and et al., eds. 1822. Vetus Testamentum ex versione Septuaginta interpretum. 3 vols. Glasgow: Ex Prelo Academico. 
On Ar. 1 and 2.
C.J. Hughes, De Lagardes Ausgabe der arabischen Übersetzung des Pentateuchs. Cod. Leid. arab. 377 nachgeprüft (Leipziger semitische Studien 7,3; Leipzig, 1920).
P.A. de Lagarde, Materialen zur Kritik und Geschichte des Pentateuchs, 2 vols. (Leipzig, 1867).
Vollandt. lindgren
O. Livne-Kafri, “A Note on the Energicus in a Coptic-Arabic Translation of the Pentateuch,” Acta Orientalia 62 (2009): 405-411.
[#] ------ "What is this which..." in a Blingual (Coptic and Arabic) Manuscript of the Pentateuch'; Acta Orientalia Hung. 65 (3), (2012), pp. 347-352. 
[#] ------“A Note on Some Hypothetical Clauses in a Coptic and Arabic MS of the Pentateuch: The Case of lawla,” Acta Orientalia Hung. 65 (2012), pp. 457-461.
His Hebrew articles.
[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro, “A Nestorian Arabic Pentateuch used in Western Islamic Lands,” in D. Thomas, ed., The Bible in Arab Christianity (Leiden — Boston, 2007), pp. 351-368.

[#]------, “¿Circularon textos cristianos orientales en al-Andalus? Nuevos datos a partir de una muestra véterotestamentaria andalusí”, in Cyrille AILLET, Mayte PENELAS & Philippe ROISSE (eds.), ¿Existe una identidad mozárabe? Historia,lengua y cultura de los cristianos de al-Andalus (siglos IX-XII) (Madrid, 2008), pp. 167-210.
Müller, D.H. Die Mehri- und Soqoṭri-Sprache, I, Texte (Südarabische Expedition, Bd. IV; Vienna, 1902), pp. 1-31. [Includes, alongside a translations into Mehri, Gen 37 and 39-45; see also below under Historical Books.]
[#] Paulus, Heinrich Eberhard Gottlob, Commentatio critica, exhibens e Bibliotheca Oxoniensi Bodlejana Specimina versionum Pentateuchi septem Arabicarum, nondum editarum, cum observationibus, Jena: apud Bibliop. Academicum, 1789.
[#] J.F. Rhode, The Arabic Versions of the Pentateuch in the Church of Egypt (Ph.D. Thesis, Catholic University of America, Washington, D.C., 1921).
[#] Rinck, Friedrich Theodor, “Über eine ungedruckte arabische Übersetzung des ersten Buchs Moses zu Mannheim,” in Johann Gottfried Eichhorn (ed.), Allgemeine Bibliothek der biblischen Litteratur, Vol. 3, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1790/91, pp. 665-669.
Malay? It is the manuscript kept in Munich today.
[see above, #] Tychsen, D.G., “Über die Quelle aus welcher die Handschrift der arabischen Version in den Polylotten geflossen ist,” in Johann Goffried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 10, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1782, pp. 95-110.
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF Ar. 1, Florence, BML Or. 112 (formerly 21).</mssGroup>
[see above, #] ------, “Untersuchung ob R. Saadjah Haggaon Verfasser der arabischen Uebersetzung des Pentateuchs in den Polyglotten sey,” in Johann Goffried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 11, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1782, pp. 82-112.
[#] Vollandt, Ronny, Christian-Arabic Translations of the Pentateuch from the 9th to the 13th centuries: A Comparative Study of Manuscripts and Translation Techniques, Unpubl. PhD-Thesis. University of Cambridge, 2011.
Offers a survey on the different translations of the Pentateuch and an in-depth study of Ms. Sinai, Ar. 2. 
Mss.: <mssGroup></mssGroup>
[#] Vollandt, Ronny, “2.5.8, Arabic versions, Pentateuch, secondary,” in Tov, Emmanuel (ed.), The Textual History of the Bible, Leiden: Brill, forthcoming.
[#] Vööbus, Arthur, Peschitta und Targumim des Pentateuchs. Neues Licht zur Frage der Herkunft der Peschitta aus dem altpalästinischen Targum, Stockholm: Etse, 1958, pp. 59-64, 118-123.
On the affinities of an alleged “old-Syriac” version on Arabic translations of the Pentateuch. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Diez A quart. 106</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 377</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 234.</mssGroup>
[#] Wevers, John William (ed.), Genesis: Septuaginta. Vetus Testamentum Graecum, Vol. 1 (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck&Ruprecht, 1974), pp. 44-46.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 9, Ar. 10, Ar. 11, and Ar. 16</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Poc. 219, and March 440</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 377 (Warner 377) and Or. 230 (Scaliger Arab. 230).</mssGroup>
[#]------, “The Textual Affinities of the Arabic Genesis of Bib. Nat. Arab 9,” in Wevers, John William and B.D. Redford, (eds.), Studies on the Ancient Palestinian World Presented to Professor F.W. Winnett (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1972), pp. 46-74.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 9, 10, 11, 16</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Leiden</place>, Oxford, Bodleian Library, Poc. 219, and March 440</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>University Library</place>, Or. 239 (Scalinger 239) and Or. 377 (Warner 377).</mssGroup>
________, “The Arabic Versions of Genesis and the Septuagint,” in Bulletin of the International Organization for Septuagint and Cognate Studies 3 (1970), pp. 8-11.
Al-Harith ibn Sinan
[#] Aldrich, Henry, “Testimonia aliquot Scriptorum Orientalium de LXXII interpretibus eoreumque Versione”, in Aristeae Historia LXXII interpretum accessere veterum testimonia de eorum Versione, Oxford: e Theatro Sheldoniano, 1692,  pp. 131-144.
With a Latin translation of the introduction. 
[#] Ceriani, Antonius Maria, Monumenta Sacra et Profana, xxxx :xxxx, xxxx, Vol. 2, pp. 107-108. 
Reproduces White’s [#] Latin translation of the introduction.
[#] Hody, Humfred, Bibliorum Textibus Originalibus, versionibus Graecis & Latina Vulgata, Oxford: e Theatro Sheldoniano, 1705, pp. 622-5. 
With a Latin translation of the introduction. 
[#] Nasrallah, Joseph, “Deux versions Melchites partielles de la Bible du IXe et du Xe siècles,” in OS 64 (1980), pp. 203-206.
Includes an account on al-Ḥārith, with all relevant primary and secondary sources. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 10</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 13 and Ar. 14</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Laud. Or. 258 (formerly A 147) and Laud. Or. 243 (formerly A 146)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Escurial</place>, Arabic 1857</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate</place>, Bibl. 14, Bibl. 19 and Bibl. 27</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>an unspecified manuscript from the collection Khūkāz</place>, Aleppo: St Sauveur, Ms. 224</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Birmingham</place>, Mingana, Arab. Chr. 121.</mssGroup>
[#] Nestle, Eberhard, “Jacob von Edessa über den Schem hammephorasch und andere Gottesnamen. Ein Beitrag zur Geschichte des Tetragrammaton,” in ZDMG 32 (1878), pp. 465-508.
Deals with al-Ḥārith’s description of the Hexapla in the introduction to his translations. Contains an excerpt of the Arabic text.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Laud. A 146 and A 147. </mssGroup>
[#] White, Joseph, A letter to the Right Reverend the Lord Bishop of London, Suggesting a Plan for a New Edition of the LXX. To which are added Specimens of some inedited Eastern Versions made from the Greek, and a Sketch of a Chart of Greek Mss. <mssGroup><place>By the Rev. Joseph White</place>, B.D. Fellow of Wadham College, Laudian Professor of Arabic, one of His Majesty's Preachers at Whitehall</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Editor and Translator of the Syriac Philoxenian Version of the Gospels</place>, Oxford : at the Clarendon-Press, 1779, pp. 8-29. </mssGroup>
Contains a full Latin translation of al-Ḥārith’s introduction, as preserved in the two copies of the Bodleian Library, specimens from Num 27, and a transcription of the closing formulas of each book. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Laud. A 146 and A 147. </mssGroup>
[#, see above] Vollandt, Ronny, “2.5.8, Arabic versions, Pentateuch, secondary,” in Tov, Emmanuel (ed.), The Textual History of the Bible, Leiden: Brill, forthcoming.
Mss.: <mssGroup></mssGroup>
Marqus ibn al-Qunbar
See [#] Wevers
[#] Breydy, Michael, “Les commentaires bibliques de Marcos Ibn Qanbar n'appartiennent ni à St. Ephrem ni au patrimoine liturgique des Maronites,” al-Manārah 27: (1986), pp. 367-380.
[#] Graf, Georg, “Ein Arabischer Pentateuchkommentar des 12. Jahrhunderts,” Biblica 23 (1924), pp. 113-138.
[#] Samir, Samir Khalil, “safīnat Nūḥ wa-l-waḥda al-masīḥiyya li-Marqus ibn Qunbar,” ṣadīq al-kāhin 12 (1972), pp- 286-294.
[#]------, “Note sur l'auteur du commentaire de la Genèse et ses recensions”, in Samir Khalil Samir (ed.) Actes du deuxième congrés international d'études arabes chrétiennes, Rome: Pont. Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1986, pp. 159-175.
[#]------, “Vie et Oevre de Marc ibn-Qunbar,” in xxx (ed.), Christianisme d'Égypte: hommages à René-Georges Coquin. Paris, Louvain: Peeters, 1995, pp. 123-158.
[#]------, “L'Esprit dans le Commentaire de la Genèse d'Ibn al-Qunbar (12e s.), ” in Samir Khalil Samir (ed.), L’Esprit-Saint dans la vie de l’Église. Actes du Deuxième. Colloque (27, 28 Février et 1er Mars 1998), Jounieh : Editions St-Paul, 2000, pp. 99-128.
[#]------, “La symbolique de l'Arche de Noé dans le commentaire allégorique de Marqus Ibn al-Qunbar (12e siècle),” in Ayoub Chahwan and Antoine Kassis ( eds), Bible et Patrimoine de l’Orient. Mélanges offerts au Père Paul Féghali, Beirut, 2002, pp. 265-317.
Contains an edition of Gen. 6:9-22
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Hunt. 112, Vatican, BAV, Ar. 33</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1330.</mssGroup>
[#] Swanson, Mark N., “Marqus ibn al-Qunba    r,” in David Thomas and Alexander Mallett (eds.), Christian-Muslim Relations. A Bibliographical History. Volume 4 (1200-1350), pp. 98-108, esp. 103-108. 
[#] Tābit, Yūḥannā (ed.), tafsīr li-sifr al-takwīn mansūb ilā al-qiddīs Afrām al-Suryānī, Kaslik: Université Saint-Esprit, 1982.
Despite the title, the book contains the translation and commentary of Ibn al-Qunbar [see]. Edition based on Ms. Oxford, Bodl. Hunt. 112.
[#]------, tafsīr li-sifr al-khurūj mansūb ilā al-qiddīs Afrām al-Suryānī, Kaslik: Université Saint-Esprit, 1983. 
Based on Ms. Vatican, BAV, Syr. 216.
[#]------,tafsīr li-sifr al-aḥbār mansūb ilā al-qiddīs Afrām al-Suryānī, Kaslik: Université Saint-Esprit, 1984.
Based on Ms. Oxford, Bodl., Hunt. 112 and Sharfeh, Syr. 1/7.
 [#] Feghali, Paul, “Note sur l'auteur du Commentaire de la Genèse attribué à saint Éphrem,” in Samir Khalil Samir (ed.), Actes du deuxième congrés international d'études arabes chrétiennes, Rome: Pont. Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1986, pp. 159-175.
[#, see above] Rhode
[#] Theiner, Johann Anton, Descriptio codicis manuscripti, qui versionem Pentateuchi arabicam continet, asservati in Bibliotheca Universitatis Vratislaviensis ac nondum editi, cum speciminibus versionis arabicae, commentatio bibliographica, Vratislaviae: Typis Universitiatis, 1822. 
Specimens of Gen 49, Ex 15, Num 23-24, and Deut 27. 
Pentateuch Catena
The text has been edited by [#, de Lagarde].
[#] Achelis, Hans, “Hyppolytus der Ausleger des Targum. Fragmente zum Pentateuch,“ Hippolytstudien, Leipzig: J.C. Hinrichs’sche Buchhandlung, 1897, pp. 113-120.
On the scholia brought in the name of Hippolytus.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 230 and Or. 2364</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 235</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl. Or. 324, Hunt. 84, Hunt. 363, Marsch 88, Marsh. 175</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Rich 7204</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 17.</mssGroup>
[#] Bardenhewer, Otto, Des heiligen Hippolytus von Rom Commentar zum Buche Daniel: ein literärgeschichtlicher Versuch, Freiburg im Breisgau: Herder’sche Verlagshandlung, 1877, pp. 32-34.
On the Hippolytus scholia.
[#] Davidson, Harold Sidney, De Lagardes Ausgabe der arabischen Übersetzung der Genesis (Cod. Leid. arab. 230) nachgeprüft (Leipzig, W. Drugulin, 1908).
Compare [#, De Lagarde]
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 230</mssGroup>
[#] Fabricius, Johann Albert, S. Hippolyti Episcopi et Martyris Operum Volum. II. inedita hactenus nonnulla illius complexum, Græce alia cum latina interpretatione: alia Arabice, litteris descripta syriacis ex catena in Pentateuchum MS. Bibl. Bodlej. cum versione V. C. Joann Gagnierii. Accedit Spicilegium Patrum, quorundam aliorum tertii a Christo nato sæculi atque in hoc Leonis Allatii Diatriba de Methodiis ac Methodiorum scriptis et Claudii Salmasii commentarius inchoatus in Arnobium nunc primum editus. Denique Appendicis loco Chalcidius in Timæum Platonis Philosophi, Hamburg: Liebezeit & Felginer, 1718, Vol. 2, pp. 37-44.
Excerpts from Ms. Oxford, Bodl, Hunt. 84 with Latin translation, in two columns, communicated to Fabricius by Jean Gagnier, Professor of Oriental Studies, University of Oxford.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl, Hunt. 84</mssGroup>
[#] McCollum, Adam, “An Arabic Scholion to Genesis 9:18–21 (Noah’s Drunkenness) Attributed to Philoxenos of Mabbug (13.2: 125-148)”, Hugoyeh: Journal of Syriac Studies 13.2 (2010), pp. 125-148.
[#] Migne, Jacques Paul (ed.), Romani pontifices saeculi iv ineuntis, S. Gregorius Thaumaturgus, S. Hippolytus Portuensis, Dionysius Alexandrinus, Julius Africanus, alii, Patrologiae cursus completus. Series Graeca 10, Paris: Petit-Montrouge, 1857, pp. 701-712
Reproduces the Latin translation of Fabricius [#].
 [#] Schulthess, Fried  rich, “Hyppolytos der Ausleger des Targum. Fragmente zum Pentateuch aus der Arabischen Katene,” in Achelis, Hans (ed.) Hippolytus Werke, Vol. 1.2 (Leipzig: J.C. Hinrichs, 1897), pp. 85-119
Gives a German translation of the scholia brought in the name of Hippolytus. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Bayrischen Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 235. </mssGroup>
[#, see above] White, Joseph, A letter to the Right Reverend the Lord Bishop of London, Suggesting a Plan for a New Edition of the LXX. To which are added Specimens of some inedited Eastern Versions made from the Greek, and a Sketch of a Chart of Greek Mss. <mssGroup><place>By the Rev. Joseph White</place>, B.D. Fellow of Wadham College, Laudian Professor of Arabic, one of His Majesty's Preachers at Whitehall</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Editor and Translator of the Syriac Philoxenian Version of the Gospels</place>, Oxford : at the Clarendon-Press, 1779, pp. 30-55</mssGroup>
Furnishes excerpts from Gen 7 and 11, as preserved in Ms. Oxford, Bodl. Marsh 88 and Hunt. 84.
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl. Marsh 88, Hunt. 84, and Arch. C 7.</mssGroup>
Historical Books
[#] Bengtsson, P.Å., Translation Techniques in Two Syro-Arabic Versions of Ruth (Studia Orientalia Lundensia, NS 3; Lund/Stockholm, 2003).
Published as an addition to the previous.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 23</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 449 and Ar. 468</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cambridge</place>, CUL, Add. 3044</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Beirut</place>, Bibliothèque Orientale, Ms. 419, Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate, Bibl. 32.</mssGroup>
Review: Heinrichs, Wolfhart, Journal of the American Oriental Society 128 (2008), pp. 565-567.
[#] ------, Two Arabic Versions of the Book of Ruth: Text Edition and Language Studies (Fil.Dr. dissertation, Lunds Universitet, 1995). 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1 and Ar. 23</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 449 and Ar. 468</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cambridge</place>, CUL, Add. 3044 and Kk. 6.3</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Beirut</place>, Bibliothèque Orientale, Ms. 419, Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate, Bibl. 32.</mssGroup>
Reviews: Grand’henry, Le Muséon, 111 (1998), pp. 458-462
Polliack, Meira, Vetus Testamentum 48 (), pp. 432-435.
Khan, Geoffrey, Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies 61 (1998), pp. 128-129.
 [#] Jacob, Anton, Septuagintastudien zu Ezra, Breslau: Buchdruckerei H. Fleischmann, 1912, pp. 20-22.
On the textual affinities of the book of Ezra in the Polyglots. 
[#] Klostermann, A., “Ezra und Nehemia,” in Realencyklopädie für Protestantische Theologie und Kirche, 3rd ed., Leipzig:J.C. Hinrichs’schen Buchhandlung, 1897, Vol. 5, pp. 500-523. 
Includes a discussion of the Arabic version of Ezra and Nehemia, as found in the Polyglots.
B. Knutsson, Studies in the Text and Language of Three Syriac-Arabic Versions of the Book of Judicum with Special Reference to the Middle Arabic Element (Leiden, 1974). 
Reviews: Samir, Samir Khalil, Bulletin d’Arabe Chretien 2 (1978), pp. 58-59.
-------, “Trois versions arabes du livre des Juges. Refléxions critiques sur un livre récent,” Oriens Christianus 65 (1981), pp. 87-101. 
Platti, Emilio, in: MIDEO 13 (1977), pp.443-444.
Müller, D.H. Die Mehri- und Soqoṭri-Sprache, I, Texte (Südarabische Expedition, Bd. IV; Vienna, 1902), pp. 31-59. [Includes, alongside translations into Mehri (and partly, Soqotri), Judges 8-16 and the book of Ruth in Arabic; see also above under Pentateuch.] pp. 1-31 
[#] Rödiger, Emil, De origine et indole arabicae librorum V.T. historicorum interpretationis libri duo, Halle: Kümmel, 1829.
Review : W.G., in Allgemeine Literaturzeitung 8 (1832), col. 57
[#] Rudolph, Wilhelm, Esra und Nehemia, samt 3. Esra, Tübingen: Verlag T.C.B. Mohr (Paul Siebeck), 1949, pp. xxi
On the textual affinities of the books of Ezra and Nehemia in the Polyglots. 
Prophets
See above [#] Hjälm and Vollandt. 
[#] Löfgren, Oscar, Studien zu den arabischen Danielübersetzungen mit besonderer Berücksichtigung der christlichen Texte. Nebst einem Beitrag zur Kritik des Peschittatextes (Uppsala Universitets Årsskrift 4;  Almqvist & Wiksell Boktryckeri: Uppsala, 1936).
	Contains a study and a categorization of over 40 manuscripts comprising Arabic translations of Daniel, extracts from Daniel chapters 1 and 3 from several versions, and a critical comparison with the Peshitta.
	Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Diez A fol. 41</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Bibliothek Paul Sbath: Ms. 920</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Birmingham</place>, University Library, Mingana Syr. 256, Syr. 624, Syr. 484 A</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>COP Bibl. 13</place>, Bibl. 55, Bibl. 77, Bibl. 79, Bibl. 80, Bibl. 81, Bibl. 82, Bibl. 86, Bibl. 87, Bibl. 88, Bibl. 89</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 59</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Istanbul</place>, Aya Sofia, 3367</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Harl. 5505, Or. 1314, Or. 1326, Or. 5918, Or. 8745</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Manchester</place>, John Rylands Library, Copt. 419, Copt. 420</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Milan</place>, Biblioteca Ambrosiana, C 58 inf.</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Libraries, Fraser (Or.) 257, Arch. Seld. A. 67</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1, Ar. 2, Ar. 25, Copt. 2, Copt. 96</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Rome</place>, Biblioteca Casanatense, 169, 2108</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 1, Ar. 539, Ar. 597</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Institute of Oriental Mss. <mssGroup><place>D226</mssGroup></mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 445, Ar. 468, Ar. 503.</mssGroup>

[#] Stapleton, Russel, An Edition of the Book of Daniel and Associated Apocrypha in Ms. Sinai Arabic I (unpubl. PhD-Thesis, Brandeis University, 1989).
Contains an edition and translation of Daniel, as preserved in Ms. Sinai, Ar. 1, with a discussion of linguistic features and the relation between Sinai Ar. 1 and a few related manuscripts.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Add. 26116</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Fraser 257, Arch. Seld. A67</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 1, Ar. 9, Ar. 448 (?), Ar. 513, Ar. 539</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Ar. 597</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 503.</mssGroup>

[#] Vaccari, Alberto, “Le versioni arabe dei Profeti” in Biblica 1 (1920), pp. 266-268; 2 (1921), pp. 401-424; 

[#] Vaccari, Alberto, “Le versioni arabe dei Profeti” in Biblica 2 (1921), pp. 401-424; 
Contains a classification of manuscripts containing a Greek-based version of the Prophets which the author attributes to a certain priest named al-ʿAlam. This version is used in the Paris and London Polyglots. Vaccari discusses the translator, time of composition as well as the date of the original Greek manuscript used as a Vorlage and offers reproductions from Isaiah 44 and 45.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1326, Or. 1314, Or. 1319</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Libraries, Arch. Seld. A. 67</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1, Ar. 25, Copt. 2</mssGroup>;  Vatican, BAV, Ar. 445

[#] Vaccari, Alberto, “Le versioni arabe dei Profeti” in Biblica 3 (1922), pp. 401-423.
Discusses the Syriac-based Arabic translation of Jeremiah, Isaiah and Ezekiel attributed to a certain Faṯyūn (Pethiōn) ibn Ayyūb, arguing for the identification of the translator with the Pethiōn mentioned in the Fihrist, offers a classification of extant manuscripts and some remarks on translation techniques.

Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Diez A fol. 41</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 59</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1314, Or. 1319, Or. 1326, and Or. 5918</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Libraries, Arch. Seld. A. 67</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Milan</place>, Ambrosiana, C 58</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1, Ar. 25, and Copt. 2</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Rome</place>, Casanatense, Ms 169</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 445, Ar. 495, and Ar. 503.</mssGroup>

Pethion ibn Ayyūb
See above [#] Vaccari
[#] Frank, Richard M. “The Jeremias of Pethion ibn Ayyūb al-Sahhār,” CBQ 21 (1959), pp. 136–70. 
Discusses the Syriac-based Arabic translation of Jeremiah attributed to a certain Faṯyūn (Pethiōn) ibn Ayyūb: it offers a classification of extant manuscripts, a discussion of style and translation techniques, as well as a reproduction of Jeremiah 1-6.

Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Diez A fol. 41</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Birmingham</place>, University Library, Mingana, Syr. 624</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 59</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, British Library, Or. 5918</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Milan</place>, Bibliotheca Ambrosiana, C58</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Libraries, Seld. Arch. 67</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Rome</place>, Bibliotheca Casanatense, Ms.169</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 503 and Ar. 495 (originally one manuscript).</mssGroup>

[#] ------, The Book of Jeremias and Lamentations in the Arabic translation of Pethion Ibn Ayyub Al Sahhar, unpubl. Dissertation, Catholic University of America, 1959.
[#] Schäfers, Joseph, Die äthiopische Uebersetzung des Propheten Jeremias (Freiburg, 1912), pp. 13-14.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Diez A fol. 41</mssGroup>
al-ʿAlam
See above [#] Vaccari. 
[#] Cornill, Carl Heinrich, Das Buch des Propheten Ezechiel (Leipzig: Hinrichs’sche Buchhandlung, 1886), pp. 49-57.
Disucusses the Arabic text of Ezekiel in the Paris Polyglot, which he shows is based on a Greek Vorlage, and notes that an Oxford manuscript is used in the London Polyglot to fill in gaps in the Paris Polyglot. 

Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Libraries, Seld. Arch. A. 67</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1. </mssGroup>

[#] Gehman, Henry S., “The Hesychian Influence in the Versions of Daniel,” JBL 48 (1929), pp. 329-332. 
On the Arabic version in the Paris and London Polyglots.
[#]------, “The ‘Polyglot’ Arabic Text of Daniel and its Affinities,” JBL 44 (1925), pp. 327-352.
Discusses the rendition of Daniel in the Paris and London Polyglots, its Vorlage, and common translation techniqes employed in it.

Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 5503(5?)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>,Bodleian Libraries, Arch. Seld. A 67.</mssGroup>

[see above, #] Jellicoe, Sidney, The Septuagint and Modern Study, Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1968 (reprint, Winona Lake, 1978), pp. 154-155.
On al-ʿAlam’s affinity to the Hesychian recension, as reflected in the Polyglots
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 445</mssGroup>

[#] Gesenius, Wilhelm, Der Prophet Jesaia: uebersetzt und mit einem vollständigen philologisch-kritischen und historischen Commentar begleitet (Leipzig: Friedr. Christ. Wilh. Vogel., 1820-1821), Vol. 1, pp. 98-106.
Discusses the Arabic rendition of Isaiah included in the Paris and London Polyglots with a focus on the translation’s relation with its Greek Vorlage  
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>

[#] Liebmann, E., “Der Text Jes. 24-27,” ZAW 22 (1902), pp. 14-24.

[#] Reinke, Laurenz, Der Prophet Haggai: Einleitung, Grundtext und Uebersetzung, nebst einem vollständigen philologisch-kritischen und historischen Commentar (Münster: Niemann 1868), pp. 34-37.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>
[#]------,Zur Kritik der älteren Versionen des Propheten Nahum (Münster: Niemann, 1867), pp. 65-70.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>
[#]------, Der Prophet Malachi. Einleitung, Grundtext und Uebersetzung, nebst einem vollständigen philologisch-kritischen und historischen Commentar (Gießsen: Ferber’sche Universitätsbuchhandlung, 1856), pp. 97-104.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>
[#] Reynolds, Stephen M., “Al-Alam's version of Zechariah,” Muslim World 33 (1943), pp. 273-275.
[#] Ryssel, V., “Die arabische Übersetzung des Micha in der Pariser und Londoner Polyglotte,” ZAW 5 (1885), pp. 102-138.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>
[#] ------, Review of F.S. Tiefenthal, Daniel explicatus, Paderborn: Schöningh, 1895, in Theologische Literaturzeitung 20 (1895), cols. 557-561 
Has a few details of Ryssel’s work on an Arabic version of Daniel.

 [#] Wald, Samuel Gottlieb, “Über die Arabische Übersetzung des Daniel in den Polyglotten,” in Eichhorn, Johann Gottfried (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 14, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1794, pp. 204-211.
Discusses the Arabic rendition of Daniel included in the Paris and London Polyglots with an emphasis on its Vorlage dependence which mainly reflects the Alexandrian reception of Theodotion.

Mss. <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>


Sapiential books
[#] Balda, Monica, “La versione araba della "Storia di Giobbe" secondo due manoscritti Arabo-Christiani,” Rivista di storria e letteratura religiosa 42 (2006), pp. 
[#] de Baudissin, Wolf Wilhelm Friedrich, Translationis antiquae arabicae libri Jobi quae supersunt nunc primum edita (Leipzig: Doerfling & Franke, 1870). 
Edition and Latin translation of an early Arabic version of Job, as preserved in a manuscript that was acquired by Tischendorf and is today found at London, British Library. It belongs with Sinai, Ar. 1. (cf. also [#, see above] Fleischer and [#, see below] Monferrer Sala.)
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Add. 26116, mentions several unspecified manuscripts. </mssGroup>
[#] Blackburn, Steven, The early Arabic versions of Job (first millennium C.E.), Ph.D-Thesis, University of St Andrews, 1999.
[#] Döderlein, Johan Christian, “Von arabischen Psaltern I,” in Johann Goffried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 2, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1778, pp. 151-179.
Tagging? 
[#] ------, “Von arabischen Psaltern II,” in Johann Goffried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 4, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1779, pp. 57-96.
[#] Frantsuzov, S.A., “Arabskie Psaltyri v Peterburge” [Arabic Psalters in St Petersburg Collections], in Vostochnye rukopisi: Materialy mezhdunarodnoj nauchnoj konferentsii (Sankt-Peterburg, 14-16 ijunia 2005 g.) (St. Petersburg, 2008), pp. 129-154.
[#]------, “Tolkovaja Psaltir 'Abdallaha ibn at-Tayyiba: Osobennosti jazyka i soderzhanija” [Abdallah ibn al-Ṭayyib's Commentary on the Psalter: Peculiarities of Language and Content]. Vestnik PSTGU, III: Filologija. 4 (14) (2008): 63-68.
A. Khater, “L’emploi des Psaumes en thérapie avec formules en caractères cryptographiques,”  in Bulletin de la Société d'Archéologie Copte 19 (1967), pp. 123-176.
W.D. McHardy, “The Arabic Text of Ecclesiasticus in the Bodleian ms. Hunt. 260,” in Journal of Theological Studies 46 (1945), pp. 39-41.
Juan-Pedro Monferrer-Sala, “Liber Job detractus apud Sin. Ar. 1: Notas en torno a la Vorlage siriaca de un manuscrito árabe christiano (s. IX),” in Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 1 (2003), pp. 119-142
Al-Harith 
[#] ------, .“‘Cantar de los cantares’ en árabe. Edición, traducción y estudio de la versión oriental conservada en la Biblioteca del Monasterio de El Escorial.” Anaquel de Estudios Árabes 9 (1998): 65-83.
[#] Monferrer-Sala and Ana Giner-Nicolás, “Una versión mutilada del ‘Cantar de los cantares’ contenida en el Vat. ar. 448. Edición y precisiones codicológicas,” Alfinge, 12 (2000), pp. 211-218.
Morozov, D.A. “Aleksandrijskaja Era v Ierusalime IX v.: K datirovke Porfirjevskoj Psaltiri” [The Alexandrian Era in Jerusalem in the Ninth Century and the Date of Porfirij Uspenskij’s Psalter]. In: Monfokon 1 (2007): 89-93 [in Russian, abstract in English, touches on the dating of two Christian Arabic manuscripts, copied by Stephen of Ramla].
J.G. Nisselius, ed., Canticum canticorum Schelemonois aethiopice et arabice (Leiden, 1656).
Polosin, Val. V., “A seventeenth-century Manuscript of an illuminated Psalter,” Manuscripta Orientalia 4 (1998), pp. 60-66.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, A 187 </mssGroup>
[#] N. Pigulevskaya, “Greko-siro-arabskaya rukopis’ IX veka” [A Greek-Syriac-Arabic Manuscript of the Ninth Century], in Palestinskii Sbornik 63 (1954), pp. 59-90.
Ps. 70:7-16; 73:4-14; 77:28-38; and 79:9-18
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Moscow</place>, State Library, Ms. 432.</mssGroup>
 [#] P. Saydon, “The Origin of the ‘Polyglot’ Arabic Psalms,” in Biblica 31 (1950), pp. 226-236.
[#] Schnurrer, Christian Friedrich, “Probe einer ungedruckten arabischen Übersetzung der Psalmen aus der Bodleyanischen Bibliothek”,in Johann Gottfried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 4, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1779, pp. 57-96.
Violet Fragment 
[#] Abbott, Nabia, Studies in Arabic literary papyri, 3. vols., Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1957-67, Vol. 1:67.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[#, see above] Blau, Joshua, A Handbook of Early Middle Arabic. Jerusalem: The Max Schloessinger Memorial Foundation ‒ The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 2002, pp. 68
[#]------, A grammar of Christian Arabic, based mainly on South-Palestinian texts from the first millennium, Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium Vol 267, 276, 279, 3 vols., Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1967-1966, Vol. 1, p. 31.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[#] Corriente, Federico, “The Psalter Fragment from the Umayyad Mosque of Damascus: a birth certificate of Nabaṭī Arabic,” in Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro (ed.), Eastern Crossroads: Essays on Medieval Christian Legacy, Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2007, pp. 303-320.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Violet fragment</place>,  </mssGroup>
[#] Haddad, Rashid, “La phonétique de l'arabe chrétien vers 700,” In Canivet, P. and J.-P. Rey-Coquais (eds.), La Syrie, de Byzance à l'Islam: VIIe-VIIIe siècles: actes du colloque international, Lyon - Maison de l'Orient méditerranéen, Paris - Institut du monde arabe, 11-15 septembre 1990, Damascus: Institut français de Damas, 1992, pp. 159-164.
[#] Hopkins, Simon, Studies in the grammar of early Arabic: based upon papyri datable to before 300 A.H./912 A.D, Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1984, pp. 1-2.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[#] Macdonald, Michael C.A., “Literacy in an oral environment,” in Literacy and identity in pre-Islamic Arabia, Aldershot: Ashgate, 2009, I. There at pp. 100-101.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[#] ------, “Reflections on the linguistic map of pre-Islamic Arabia,” in Literacy and identity in pre-Islamic Arabia, Aldershot: Ashgate, 2009, III. There at pp. 50, 68 n62.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[# ]------ , Old Arabic (Epigraphic),” in Versteegh, Kees, Encyclopedia of Arabic Language and Linguistics, Leiden: Brill, 2008, pp. 464-477.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[#] Mavroudi, Maria, “Arabic words in Greek letters: the Violet fragment and more,” in J. Lentin, Jérôme and Jacques Grand'Henry (eds.), Moyen Arabe et variétés mixtes de l'arabe à travers l'histoire. Actes du Premier Colloque International, Louvain-la-Neuve, 10-14 mai 2004, Louvain: Peeters, 2008, pp. 321-354.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
[#] Schulthess, F., Christlich-palästinische Fragmente aus der Omajjaden-Moschee zu Damaskus
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
Review: Brockelmann, Literaturzeitung 57 (1905), p. 469.
[#] B. Violet, “Ein zweisprachiges Psalmenfragment aus Damascus,” in Orientalistische Literaturzeitung 4 (1901), pp. 384-403, 425-441, 475-488.
Mss.: <mssGroup>Violet fragment</mssGroup>
Hafs al-Quti
[#] Dunlop, D.M., “Ḥafṣ ibn Albar—The last of the Goths,” Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society 3/4 (1954), pp. 137-151
[#] ------, “Sobre Ḥafṣ ibn Albar al-Qūṭī al-Qurṭubī,” al-Andalus 20 (1955), pp. 211-213.
[#] Gilson, The Mozarabic Psalter, London 1905.
[#] Koningsveld, P. Sj. Van, “Psalm 150 of the translation by Hafs ibn Albar al-Quti (fl. 889 A.D.[?]) in the Glossarium Latino-Arabicum of the Leyden University Library,” Bibliotheca Orientalis, XXIX nº 5/6 September-November, 1972, pp. 277-280.
[#]------, “New Quotations from Ḥafṣ al-Qūṭī’s translation of the Psalms,” Bibliotheca Orientalis 30 (1973), p. 315.
Monferrer-Sala, J.P. "Salmo 11 en versión árabe versificada: Unas notas en torno a las fuentes del Psalterio de Ḥafṣ b. Albar al-Qūṭī." Miscelánea de Estudios Árabes y Hebraicos [=Homenaje a Prof. Antonio Torres Fernández] 49 (2000): 303-319.
------, “Ibn Albar al-Qūṭī (Ḥafṣ b. Albar al-Qūṭī),” Lirola Delgado and Puerta Vílches, DAOA, Vol. 1, pp. 433-435
[#] Neubauer, Adolf, “Hafs al-Qouti,” REJ 30 (1895), pp. 65-69. 
[#] Schippers, Arie, “Hafs al-Qûtî’s Psalms in Arabic Ragaz metre (9th century): a discussion of translations from three Psalms (Ps. 50, 1 and 2)”, in (eds.) Vermeulen ,Urbain, and J. M. F. van Reeth, Law, Christianity and Modernism in Islamic Society: Proceedings of the Eighteenth Congress of the Union Européenne Des Arabisants Et Islamisants Held at the Katholieke Universiteit Leuven (September 3-September 9, 1996), Orientalia Lovaniensia, Analecta, 86 (Peeters: Leuven, 1998), pp.133-146.
On selected translation features, in comparison to Saadaiah’s version
M.T. Urvoy, Le Psautier mozarabe de Hafs Le Goth (Toulouse, 1994). [Edition and French translation.]
________, “Influence islamique sur le vocabulaire d’un psautier arabe d’Al-Andalus,” in Al-Qanṭara 15 (1994), pp. 509-517.
Al-harith ibn sinan
Sadan, Joseph, "In the Eyes of the Christian Writer al-Ḥāriṯ Ibn Sinān: Poetics and Eloquence as a Platform of Inter-Cultural Contacts and Contrasts." Arabica 56 (2009): 1-26. 
[on style of Scripture, in response to Muslim doctrine of i‘jāz of Koran]

Other old testament 
New Testament
Henk Jan De Jonge, “Joseph Scaliger's Greek-Arabic lectionary,”  Quaerendo 5, No. 2 (1975): 143 – 172.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Ms</place>, Leiden, Or. 243 (l.6)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vienna</place>, VNL?, K II 346</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1242,6</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl, Copt. c. 3</mssGroup>
The article traces the history of acquisition of Ms, Leiden, Or. 243 in the Scaliger collection of Leiden University Library. It also compares its paleographical features with other lectionaries manuscripts in order to identify its provenance.
[#] Déroche, François. “Les Manuscrits Arabes Datés du IIIe/IXe Siecle.” Revue des Études Islamiques (1987-1989).343-379.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Ms</place>, Sinai Ar. 72</mssGroup>;73; 151, 154; Sinai, NF, Parch. Ar. 7; St. Petersburg, A.N.S. 327; Paris, BNF, Or. 6725;
A survey of the paleography of some Islamic and Christian manuscripts from the 9th century along with some bibliography about them and sample pictures from these manuscripts

Gospels
[#] Bailey, Kenneth E., “Early Arabic New Testaments of Mt. Sinai and the Task of Exegesis (with special focus on Sinai Ar. 72 and Luke 15),” Near East Theological Review 12 (1991), pp. 45-62.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 54, Ar. 72, Ar. 74, and Ar. 97</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Borg. Ar. 95</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Or. Oct. 1108.</mssGroup>
[#] Arbache, Samir, Le tétraévangile Sinaï Arabe 72: Ses rubriques liturgiques et son substrat grec, Mémoire de Licence en Théologie, Université Catholique de Louvain, Juin 1975 
________, Une ancienne version arabe des Évangiles: langue, texte et lexique (Ph.D. dissertation, Université Michel de Montaigne, Bordeaux, 1994.
________, “Les versions arabe des évangiles,” in Mélanges des sciences religieuses 56 (1999), pp. 85-93.
________, and Ph. Roisse, “Versions anciennes de Syrie-Palestine et d'al-Andalus,” Mélanges de science religieuse 62 (2005): 65-78. [on diversity of early Arabic versions of Mk 1.1-11]
Chébli, A, إنجيل خط قديم [A copy of the Gospels in an ancient script], al-Machriq 46 (1952), pp. 425-433; 571-596.
On a karshuni copy from a private collection. 
Eric F.F. Bishop, “Two Readings from the Arabic Versions of the New Testament,” Anglican Theological Review 30 (1948): 176-179.
[#] Ehrhard, Albert, “Das griechische Kloster Mar-Saba in Palaestina. Seine Geschichte und seine litterarischen Denkmäler,” Römische Quartalschrift für die Christliche Altertumskunde und für Kirchengeschichte 7 (1893), pp. 32-79, there p. 78 and pl. XIV.2
Describes Paris, BNF, Suppl. Grec. 911, a fragmentary Greek-Arabic bilingual of the Gospels of Luke, originating from the monastery of Mar Saba (Compare Monferrer [#], Urban [#]) 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Suppl. Grec. 911.</mssGroup>
[#] Fleischer, Heinrich Leberecht, “Vermischtes,” ZDMG 15 (1861), pp. 381-396.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Leipzig</place>, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. Tisch. 31 and 37.</mssGroup>
[#]------ “Beschreibung der von Prof. Dr. Tischendorf im J. 1853 aus dem Morgenlande zurückgebrachten christlich-arabischen Handschriften ,” ZDMG 8 (1854), pp. 584-587 (reprinted in Kleinere Schriften, Leipzig: Verlag von S. Hirzel, 1888, Vol. 3, pp. 389-394)
On fragments of Christian Arabic manuscripts that were acquired by Tischendorf. Comp. [#] Tischendorf, [#] Delitzsch.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ar. N.S. 327</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leipzig</place>, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. Tisch. 31 and 37.</mssGroup>
Garland, Amy Galli, An Arabic Translation of the Gospel According to Mark [Sin. ar. 72], Unpublished MA Thesis, CUA, Washington, 1979.
[#] J. Gildemeister, De Evangeliis in Arabicum e Simplici Syriaca translatis (Bonn, 1865).
Leipzig, Tisch. 12 (Evangelien, Syr.-Ar.)
I. Guidi, “Le traduzioni degli Evangelii in arabo e in etiopico,” in Atti della Reale Academia dei Lincei, Memorie, anno CCLXXV, 4t series, Classe di scienze morali, storiche e filologiche, IV, Partie 1 (a), (Rome, 1888), pp. 5-76.
[#] Géhin, P. “Un manuscrit bilingue grec-arabe, BnF, Supplément Grec 911 (année 1043),” in Déroche, François and Francis Richard (eds.), Scribes et manuscrits du Moyen-Orient (Paris: Bibliothèque Nationale de France, 1997), pp. 162-175.
On a bilingual Greek-Arabic manuscript of the Gospel of Luke, dated 1043 CE, which is today divided between Paris, BNF and St Petersburg, RNL (Compare [#] )
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Supp. Grec. 911, St. Petersburg, RNL Gre. 290.</mssGroup>
[#] Gregory, C.R, Textkritik des Neuen Testamentes. Die Übersetzungen-die Schriftsteller-Geschichte der Kritik.Vol. 2. Leipzig: J.C. Hinrichs'sche Buchhandlung, 1902.
Vol. 2 is dedicated to Arabic versions 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Gregory 0136 and 0137</place>, St Petersburg </mssGroup>
[#] Harris, James Rendel, Biblical fragments from Mount Sinai, London: C.J. Clay and Sons, 1890, pp. xi, 25-26
Describes and edits a Greek-Arabic bilingual of Matt. 13:46-52 from St Catherines Monastery (Compare Lewis [#]).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Today?</place>, belongs with St Petersburg, Russian National Library, Gre. 290. </mssGroup>
[#] Juynboll, Theodoor Willem Johanne, Letterkundige Bijdragen. Vol. 2 Beschrijving van een Arabisches Codex der Franeker Bibliotheek, bevattende de vier Evangelien, gevolgd van eenige opmerkingen, welke de letterkundig geschiedenis van de arabische vertaling der Evangelien betreffen (Leiden: Luchtmans, 1838).
H. Kachouh, “The Arabic Gospel Text of Codex Beirut, Bibliothèque Orientale, 430: Is It Recent or Archaic?” Parole de l'Orient 32 (2007): 105-121.
________, “The Arabic Versions of the Gospels: A Case Study of John 1.1 and 1.18,” in Thomas, David (ed.), The Bible in Arab Christianity, Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2007, pp. 9-36.
________ [spelled Kashouh], The Arabic Versions of the Gospels: The Manuscripts and their Families, Arbeiten zur neutestamentlichen Textforschung 42 (Berlin , 2011). [Originally a Ph.D. thesis from the University of Birmingham, 2008.]
________, “Sinai Ar. N.F. Parchment 8 and 28: Its Contribution to Textual Criticism of the Gospel of Luke,” Novum Testamentum 50 (2008), pp. 28-57.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. N.F. Parchment 8 and 28. </mssGroup>
S. Khoury, and Samir Khalil Samir, L’Evangéliaire arabe rimé de Abdischu‘ de Nisibe, 2 vols. (Beirut, 2007).

 [#] de Lagarde, Paul, Die vier Evangelien arabisch aus der Wiener Handschrift herausgegeben (Leipzig, 1864).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Based on Vienna</place>, ÖNB, Or. 1544</mssGroup>
[#] B. Levin, Die griechisch-arabische Evangelien-Übersetzung Vat. Borg. ar. 95 und Ber. orient. oct. 1108 (Inaugural-Dissertation...zu Upsala (Uppsala, 1938).
[#] Lewis, Agnes Smith, “Some ancient MSS of the Arabic New Testament,” Transactions of the Ninth international Congress of Orientalists, Vol. 2, pp. 96-98.
[#] ------, Catalogue of the Syriac Mss. <mssGroup><place>in the convent of S. Catherine on Mount Sinai</place>, Studia Sinaitica 1, London: C.J. Clay and Sons, 1984, pp. 105-106. </mssGroup>
No. 9 contains the description and edition of a folio (previously edited by Rendel Harris), exhibiting Matt 13:46-52 in Greek and Arabic. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>What is the current shelfmark? [belongs with Ms. St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Gre 281].</mssGroup>
[#] Macdonald, D. B., “The Gospels in Arabic,” Hartford Seminary Record 3, no page numbers.
[#] Merx, Adalbert, “Die in der Peschito fehlenden Briefe des Neuen Testamentes in arabischer der Philoxeniana enstammender Uebersetzung. Nach der Abschrift eines Manuscripts des Sinai-Klosters von Frau A. Persis Burkitt veröffentlicht und mit Anmerkungen versehen,” Zeitschrift für Assyriologie und verwandte Gebiete 12 (1897), pp. 240-252, 348-381; 13 (1898), pp. 1-28. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 154 </mssGroup>

[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro and Ángel Urbán, “A membrum disjectum or the Reconstruction of a Lost Bifolio: St. Petersburg ‘grec 290’ from BnF ‘Suppl. gr. 911’. Edition and Commentary,” in Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro, Herman Teule and Sofía Toralles Tovar, Eastern Manuscripts and Their Written Heritage: Manuscripts, Scribes and Context. [Eastern Christian Studies 14] Leuven, Paris, Warpole, MA: Peetres, 2012, 115-134.
[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro, “Descripción lingüística de la columna árabe del BnF Suppl. grec. 911 (año 1043),” Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 2 (2005), pp. 93-139.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Supp. Grec. 911 and St Petersburg, RNL, Gre. 290.</mssGroup>
[#]------, “Un evangelio árabe oriental inédito en Toledo (Ms. 387 de la BRC–LM),” Anaquel de Estudios Árabes 16 (2005), pp. 173-192.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Toledo</place>, Biblioteca Regional de Castilla-La Mancha, Ms. 387</mssGroup>
[#]-----, “Por dentro de la traducción. Exégesis de un pasaje del Suppl. grec. 911 de la BnF (año 1043)”, Ḥikma 2 (2003), pp. 107-117.
[#]------, “Un manuscrito inédito, griego-árabe, del siglo XI del Evangelio de Lucas (Ms. BnF. Suppl. gr. 911). Una presentación,” Actas del V Congreso Andaluz de Lingüística General (Granada, 17-19 noviembre 2004)
[#]------, “Dos antiguas versiones neotestamentarias árabes surpalestinenses: "Sin. Ar. 72, Vat. Ar. 13" y sus posibles "Vorlagen" respectivas greco-Alejandrina y siríaca de la Peshitta,” Real monasterio de el escorial: La ciudad de dios, 213 (2000): 363-387
 [#, see above] Nasrallah, Joseph, “Deux versions Melchites partielles de la Bible du IXe et du Xe siècles,” in OS 64 (1980), pp. 203-206.
On Bishr b. Sirrī’s translation of the Pauline Epistles. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 151.</mssGroup>
[#] Renouf, P., “On the Supposed Latin Origin of the Arabic Version of the Gospels,” Atlantis: or Register of Literature and Science of the Catholic University of Ireland 4 (1863), p. 241-259.
[#] Peters, Curt, “Proben eines bedeutsamen arabischen Evangelientextes,” OC 11 (1936), pp. 188-211.
Contains an edition and translation of Mt 1:18-25, 5:23-45; Mark 12:1-12; Luke 4:1-13; John 19:28-42.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Borg. Ar. 71 and Ar. 467</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 225 and Or. 1571</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and St Petersburg</place>, Institut of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226.</mssGroup>
[#] ------, “Von arabischen Evangelientexten in Handschriften des Universitäts-Bibliothek Leiden,” Acta Orientalia 10 (1940): 131-135.
 [#] Urbán, Ángel, “Los intercambios vocálicos en un manuscrito greco-árabe inédito del Evangelio de Lucas (BnF, Suppl. gr. 911, s. XI),” Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 2 (2005), pp. 245-272.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Suppl. Grec. 911 and St Petersburg, RNL, Gre. 290.</mssGroup>
[#] ________, “Nomina sacra en un ms. inédito de Lucas (Ms BnF, Suppl. gr. 911, año 1043),” in Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 1 (2003), pp. 247-275.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Suppl. Grec. 911.</mssGroup>
[#] ________, “An Unpublished Greek-Arabic MS of Luke’s Gospel (BnF Suppl. grec 911, A.D. 1043): A Report,” in Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro (ed.), Eastern Crossroads: Essays on Medieval Christian Legacy (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2007), pp. 83-95.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Suppl. Grec. 911 and St Petersburg, RNL, Gre. 290.</mssGroup>
[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro and Ángel Urbán, “A membrum disjectum or the reconstruction of a lost bifolio: St. Petersburg ‘Grec 290’ from BnF ‘Suppl. Gr. 911’. Edition and commentary”, in Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro, Herman Teule, Sofía Torallas Tovar, Eastern Christians and Their Written Heritage. Manuscripts, Scribes and Context (Eastern Christian Studies 14, Lovaina/Paris /Walpole, MA: Peeters, 2012), pp. 115-134.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Suppl. Grec. 911</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, RNL, Grec 290</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 69 and Ar. 69.</mssGroup>
[#] Urban, Ángel and Juan-Pedro Monferrer-Sala, “Some regards on Textual Criticism in a Greek-Arabic Ms BnF Suppl. grec 911 (A.D. 1043),” in Parole de l’Orient 30 (2005), pp. 79-102.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Suppl. Grec. 911</mssGroup>
[#] J. Valentin, “Les évangéliaires arabes de la bibliothèque du Monastère Ste-Catherine (Mont Sinaï): Essai de classification d'après l'étude d'un chapitre (Matth. 28): Traducteurs, réviseurs, types textuels,” Le Muséon 116 (2003), pp. 415-477.
[#] Vööbus, Artus, Early Versions of the New Testament. Manuscript Studies, Stockholm: impr. de L. Durbecq, 1954, pp. 271-297.
Mss. <mssGroup><place>: Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13 (pl. 21), Ar. 17, Ar. 18, Borg. Ar. 71, Borg. Ar. 95 (pl. 23), and Copt. 9</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 82, Ar. 154, and Ar. 155</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Or. Quart. 2101</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Staatsbibliothek Ar. 238</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Ar. Suppl. 5</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, University Library, Or. 2378.</mssGroup>
G.C. Storr, Dissertatio Inauguralis Critica de Evangeliis Arabicis (Tübingen, 1775).
Diatesseron
See below on the quotations of the Arabic Diatesseron in al-Biqāʿī [Saleh], al-Ghazālī
[#] Baarda, Tjitze, “The Author of the Arabic Diatesseron,” in Tjitze Baara, Albertus Frederik Johannes Klyn, and Willem Cornelis van Unnik (eds.), Miscellanea Neotestamentica. Studia ad novum Testamentum praesertim pertinentia, Leiden: Brill, 1978, pp. 61-100.
[#] ------, “An Archaic Element in the Arabic Diatesseron,” Novum Testamentum 17 (1975), pp. 151-155. 
[#] Beeston, A.F.L., “The Arabic versions of Tatian’s Diatesseron,” JRAS (1939), pp. 608-610.
Presents a 18th century copy of the Arabic Diatesseron in the Bodleian Library, Oxford. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Ar. e. 63</mssGroup>
[#] Cheikho, Louis, “Lettre au sujet de l’auteur de la version arabe du Diatesseron,” Journal Asiatique 10 (1897), pp. 301-307.
Presents the Beirut fragments of the Arabic Diatesseron.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Beirut</place>, Bibliotheque Orientale, 429.</mssGroup>
[#] Ciasca, P.A., Tatiani Evangeliorum Harmoniae Arabice (Rome, 1888).
[#] ------, “De Tatiani Diatessaron Arabica Versione,” in Pitra, J.B. (ed.), Analecta Sacra Spicilegio solesmensi parata (Paris: xxxx, 1883), pp. 465-487.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 14 </mssGroup>
[#] Euringer, Sebastian, “Die Überlieferung der arabischen Übersetzung des Diatessarons,” Biblische Studien 17 (1912).
[#] Hill, James Hamlyn, The Earliest Life of Christ Ever Compiled from the Four Gospels, Being the Diatessaron of Tatian (circ. A.D. 160) Literally Translated from the Arabic Version and containing the Four Gospels woven into One Story (Edinburgh: T&T Clark, 1903)
The translation is based on Ciasca edition and draws heavily from his Latin translation.
[#] Higgins. A. J. B, “Luke 1-2 in Tatian's Diatsseron,” The Society of Biblical Literature 103 (1994), pp. 193-222.
[#]------, “The Persian and Arabic Gospel Harmonies,” in Studia Evangelica (Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 1959), pp. 793-810
On the textual affinities of the Persian and Arabic Harmonies
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 14 and Borg. Ar 250</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo 202</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Ar. e. 163.</mssGroup>
[#]------, “Tatian’s Diatesseron and the Arabic and Persian Harmonies,” Elliott, J.K. (ed.), Studies in New Testament Language and Text: Essays in honour of George D. Kilpatrick (Leiden: Brill, 1976), pp. 246-261.
On the textual affinities of the Persian and Arabic Harmonies
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vienna</place>, ÖNB, Or. 1544</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 14 and Borg. Ar. 250</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo 202 (COP)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Sbath 1020</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Ar. e. 163</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or 3382.</mssGroup>
[#] Hogg, Hope W., The Diatesseron of Tation, Edinburgh: xxx, 1897.
[#] Joosse, Peter, “An Introduction to the Arabic Diatessaron,” OC 83 (1999), pp. 72-129. 

Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 14 and Borg. Ar 250</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo 202</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Ar. e. 163.</mssGroup>
------, The Sermon on the Mount in the Arabic Diatessaron (Amsterdam: Centrale Huisdrukkerij VU, 1997).
Review: Sepmeijer, F., in Novum Testamentum 41 (1999), pp. 297-300.
[#] Petersen, William L., Tatian’s Diatessaron. Its Creation, Dissemination, Significance, and History in Scholarship (Leiden: Brill, 1994), pp. 133-138.
[#] Kahle, Paul, The Cairo Genizah (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1959), pp. 297-304.
On the Arabic Diatesseron and al-Ghazālī’s quotations thereof, with notes on the Coptic reception. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 14 and Borg. Ar. 250</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo 202 (COP)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Sbath 1020</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Ar. e. 163</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or 3382.</mssGroup>
[#] Kirsopp Lake and Silva Lake, Studies and Documents 111, A Greek Fragment of Tatian's Diatessaron from Dura. Edited with Facsimile, transcription and Introduction by Carl H. Kraeling, London 1935, S. 12 f
[#] M. J. Lagrange in Revue biblique 44 (1935) 321-327.
[#] Leloir, L., “Le Diatesseron de Tatien,” L’Orient Syrian 1 (1956), pp. 216-227.
Contains a comparative table of the contents of the Persian, Arabic, Latin, Dutch, and Venetian Harmonies.
[#] Augustin-Sebastien Marmardji, Diatessaron de Tatien: Texte arabe établi, traduit en français, collationné avec les anciennes versions syriaques, suivi d’un évangile diatessarique syriaque et accompagné de quatre planches hors-texte (Beirut, 1935). 
Reviews: Baumstark, Anton in OC 33 (1936), pp. 235-245; D.S. Margoliouth in Journal of Theological Studies 38 (1937): 76-79; P. Benoit in Revue Biblique 46 (1937): 124-128.
[#] Pastorelli, David, “The Genealogies of Jesus in Tatian’s Diatesseron. The Question of their Absence or Presence,” in Clivas, Claire, et al. (eds.), Infancy Gospels, Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum Neuen Testament 281, Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2011, pp. 216-230.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 14 and Borg. Ar. 250</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo 202 (COP)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Sbath 1020 and 1280</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Ar. e. 163</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or 3382, Beirut Fragments?</mssGroup>
[#]Peters, Kurt, Das Diatessaron Tatians (Rome, 1939).
[#] Sellin, E, "Der Text des von A. Ciasca herausgegebenen arabischen Diatessaron", Forschungen zur Geschichte des neutestamentlichen Kanons und der altkirchlichen Literatur, Vol. 4 (Erlangen: Deichert, 1891), pp. 225-246.
An response to [#, Ciasa]
[#] Zahn, Theodor, Tatians Diatesseron (Erlagen:xxxx, 1881)
Chapter 4

Hibbatallah
[#] Bailey, Kenneth E., “Hibat Allāh Ibn al-‘Assāl and His Arabic Thirteenth Century Critical Edition of the Gospels (with special attention to Luke 16:16 and 17:10),” Near East Theological Review 1 (1978), pp. 11-26.
[#] Higgins, A.J.B. “Ibn al-ʿAssāl”, The Journal of Theological Studies 44 (1943), pp. 73-75.
[#] MacDonald, D.B., “Ibn al-‘Assāl’s Arabic Version of the Gospels,” in E. Saavedra, ed., Homenaje á D. Francisco Codera en su jubilación del profesorado: Estudios de erudición oriental (Saragosa:  1904), pp. 375-392.
Vevian
[#] Samir, Samir Khalil, “La version arabe des évangiles d’al As‘ad ibn al-‘Assāl,” PdO 19 (1994), pp. 441-451.
 [#] A. Wadi, “Al-Asʿad Ibn al-ʿAssal, Introduzioni alla traduzione dei quattro Vangeli” [in Arabic], Studia Orientalia Christiana Collectanea 39 (2006): 47-120.

Isaak Velasquez
See as well, Goussen [#], Gehman [#], Monferrer Sala [#], Koningveld [#].
[#] Baumstark, Anton, Markus Kap. 2 in der arabischen Uebersetzung des Isaak Velasquez, OC 9 (1934), pp. 226-239.
[#] Fraenkel, Siegmund, “Zu dem spanisch-arabischen Evangelienfragment,” ZDMG 57 (1903), p. 201.
Notes to [Vollers #]
[#] Á,C. López y López, "La traducción de los evangelios al árabe por Isaac ben Velasco de Córdoba en el siglo X a.D." Boletín Millares Carlo [Actas del Congreso “Agustín Millares Carlo: Maestro de medievalistas”] 13 (1994): 79-84.
[#] Roisse, Ph. "Los Evangelios traducidos del latín al árabe por Isḥāq b. Balašk al-Qurṭubī en 946 d.C." 147-164 in C. Castillo, I. Cortés and J.P. Monferrer-Sala, eds. Estudios árabes dedicados a D. Luis Seco de Lucena (En el XXV Aniversario de su muerte). Granada, 1999.
-------, “La circulation du savoir des Arabes chrétiens en Méditerranée médiévale. Approche des soruces manuscrites,” Collectanea Christiana Orientalia 1 (2004), pp. 219-223.
[#] Tisserant, Eugène, “Sur un manuscript mozarabe de Fès,” in Díaz, Romualdo (ed.), Miscellanea Biblica B. Ubach, Barcelona: Momtisserrati, 1956, pp. 15-26.
On an unspecified fragment from Fez, containing the Gospel translation of Velasquez.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Fes</place>, Al-Qarawiyyin University Library, Cod. 730</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Cod. 238.</mssGroup>
[#] Vollers, K. and E. von Dobschütz, “Ein spanisch-arabisches Evangelienfragment,” ZDMG 56 (1902), pp. 633-648.
Response to Fleischer ZDMG 8, p. 586. Deals with a fragment of Isaak Velasquez’s Gospel translation in Leipzig, acquired by Tischendorf [Compare Fleischer and Fraenkel #].
Ms.: Leipzig, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. Tisch. 31. 
 [#] Taeuschner, Franz, “Die monarchianistischen Prologe zu den vier Evangelien in der spanisch-arabischen Bibelübersetzung des Isaak Velasquez nach der Münchener Handschrift Cod. Arab. 238,” OC 10 (1935), pp. 80-99.
Edits and translates into German the Monarchian Prologues, as preserved in Ms. Munich, Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 238.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Bayrische Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 238. </mssGroup>
Other new testament 

[#] Gwynn, John, “On a Syriac MS. belonging to the Collection of the Archbishop Ussher,” Transactions of the Royal Irish Academy 27 (1877-1886), pp. 269-315.
On Sinai, Ar. 154
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 154</mssGroup>
[#]------, “xxxx,” Hermathena x (1890)
[#]------, “The Older Syriac Version of the four minor Catholic Epistles,” Hermathena 16 (1890), pp. 281-314. 
On Sinai, Ar. 154
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 154</mssGroup>
Acts
[#] Monferrer Sala, Juan Pedro, Scripta arabica orientalia: dos studios de la literatura árabe cristiana, Granada:Athos Pérgamos, 1999.
Includes an edition of the Acts of the Apostles, based on Vatican, BAV, Ar. 468.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL,. Or. 1326</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13 and Ar. 468</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 151</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Escorial Cod. Ar. 1625.</mssGroup>
The Pauline Epistles
One of the earliest codices was brought from Sinai by Tischendorf and is today preserved in its two membra disjecta Mss. <mssGroup><place>Leipzig</place>, Universitätsbibliothek, Cod. Tisch. 37 and St. Petersburg, RNL, Ar. N.S. 327. [cf. [#, see above] Fleischer and [#, see above] Tischendorf]</mssGroup>
[#] Bailey, K.,  Paul through the Mediterranean Eye: Cultural Studies in I Corinthians, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2011.
A Commentary on 1 Corinthians that builds upon its rhetorical pattern borrowed from the Hebrew Bible. The Middle Eastern Culture is used to explain some vague points in the text through old manuscripts of Arabic, Syriac, and Hebrew translations of 1 Corinthians.

     Mss.:Oxford, Bodl, Or. 712; Sinai, Ar. 73;151; 155; 310;Vatican, BAV, Ar. 13.
[#] Gibson, Mageret Dunlop, An Arabic Version of the Epistles of St Paul to the Romans, Corinthians, Galatians, with Part of the Epistle to the Ephesians from a Ninth Century MS. in the Convent of St Catharine on Mount Sinai, Studia Sinaitica 2 (London: C.J. Clay and Sons, 1894. 
On Sinai, Ar. 155, assigned to the ninth century CE. The Arabic translation was made from Greek. Includes Arabic text with some notes on the text and translation technique. (Comp. [# Boyd, Robert])
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 155.</mssGroup>

[#] Burkitt, F.  “The Palestinian Syriac Lectionary.” The Journal of Theological Studies 6, no. 21 (October, 1904) 91-98.
	An argument against the hypothesis that the Palestinian Syriac Lectionary is of Egyptian Bohairic Origin.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 155 (Gibson’s ed.)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Leiden</place>, UBL, Or. 217 (Erpenius ed.)</mssGroup>



[#] Staal, Harvey, Mt. Sinai Arabic Codex 151: I. Pauline Epistles (CSCO 452-453 = Scr. Arb. 40-41; Louvain, 1983). [Transcription of the manuscript’s text, with marginal comments, glosses, etc. The earliest colophon has the date 253 AH (= 867 CE). See also above by the same editor and translator under Acts. The editor claims to “have transcribed the original as carefully as possible” (452: 12) but has nevertheless modernized the orthography. Both the text and the translation have comments. Cf. the article by Féghali in this section.]
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 151</mssGroup>
[#]-------, Codex Sinai Arabic 151 Pauline Epistle, Studies and Documents 40, (Salt Lake City: University of Utah Press, 1969).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 151.</mssGroup>
[#] Féghali, Paul, Les épîtres de saint Paul dans une des premières traductions en arabe 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 151</mssGroup>
An examination of the Syriac origin of Sinai, Ar. 151 as well as its syntactical, morphological, and stylistic features.

[#] Krenkow, F. “Two Ancient Fragments of an Arabic Translation of the New Testament,” JRAS (1926), pp. 275-285. 
On Mss. <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL Or. 8605 and 8612, to both of which the author assigns a date prior to 1000 CE. A total of four facsimile pages are given, with transcription</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>these samples include parts of Jam</place>, 1 Pet, and Heb, but the complete manuscripts contain from Acts to the end of the New Testament.</mssGroup>
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL Or. 8605 and 8612.</mssGroup>

[#] Brock, S. “A Neglected Witness to the East Syriac New Testament Commentary Tradition: Sinai, Arabic Ms 151,” in Studies on the Christian Arabic Heritage in Honour of Father Prof. Dr. Samir Khalil Samir, ed. Rifaat Ebied & Herman Teule, Eastern Christian Studies, Vol. 5 (Leuven: Peeters, 2004)
Investigating the origins of the exegetical annotations on the text of the Pauline Epistles in Sinai, Ar. 151. They have common sources with East Syriac exegetical materials, Mainly, with Isho‘dad and Theodore of Mopsuestia commentaries. 

Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 151</mssGroup>

I Corinthians
[#] Boyd, Robert Henry, The Arabic text of I Corinthians in "Studia sinaitica no. II "; a comparative linguistic, and critical study, unpubl. Dissertation, Princeton University, 1942. 
Galatians
[#] de Bruyne, Donatien and Eugène Tisserant, “Une feuille arabo-latine de l’épître aux Galates,” Revue Biblique n.s. 7 (1910): 321-344. 
Chapter of the Cathedral of Siguenze 150, one plate of which precedes the article; ms dated to around 900 CE on the basis especially of the Latin script. No Arabic text, but a literal French translation of Gal. 1:1-15 with commentary.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Lat. 12900 (formerly Chapter of the Cathedral of Siguenze, Ms. 150).</mssGroup>
[#] Lourdes Bonhome Pulido, “A Fragmentary Arabic Version of the Epistle of Galatians Kept in the Royal Library of the Monastery of the Escorial,” in Graeco-Latina et Orientalia Studia in Honorem Angeli Urbani Heptagenarii, Syro-Arabica, Vol. 2, ed. Samir Khalil and Juan Pedro Monferrer-Sala, Cordoba: CNERU-CEDRAC, 2013.
An edition and English translation of the text. A description of the manuscript and a comparison with Sinai, Ar. 151 and a Greek version.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Madrid</place>, Esc, Ar. 1625</mssGroup>
Philemon
[#] G. Troupeau, “Une ancienne version de l’épître à Philémon,” in Mélanges offerts à M. Dunand, Mélanges de l'Université Saint Joseph 46 (1970), pp. 343-351. Reprint, in Études sur le christianisme arabe au Moyen Age (Aldershot, 1995). [On BnF arabe 6725, in Kufic (or early Naskh) script on parchment, copied in Jerusalem in 902 CE. Offers a brief textual comparison with the text of the letter from the Peshitta and in Greek. After a brief discussion of the linguistic peculiarities, Troupeau presents the Arabic text with French translation, the latter accompanied by some textual notes reflecting the comparison with the Syriac and Greek texts.]

[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan-Pedro, “The Pauline Epistle to Philemon from Codex Vatican Arabic 13 (Ninth Century CE): Transcription and Study,” Journal of Semitic Studies LX/2: (2015), 341-371.	
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13	 	</mssGroup>
A transcription of the Arabic text of Philemon of Vatican, BAV, Ar. 13 along with an examination of the paleographical and 	linguistic features of the text. This is followed by an analysis of the text that suggests a Greek Vorlage with some Syriac influence.			
				
			
Hebrews
[#] Staal, Harvey, “Pauline authorship of the Epistle to the Hebrews according to Mt Sinai Arabic manuscript 151,” Reformed Review 21 (1967), pp. 51-53.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 151.</mssGroup>
A short introduction and translation of the first Arabic defence of the Pauline authorship to the Hebrews epistle in Ms, Sinai, Ar. 151. 

[#] Stenij, Edv, Die altarabische Übersetzung der Briefe an die Hebräer, an die Römer und an die Corinther. Aus einem in St. Petersburg befindlichen Codex Tischendorfs vom Jahre 892 n. Chr. Helsingfors: Frenckellska Tryckeri-Aktiebolaget, 1901.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St. Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ar. N.S. 327</mssGroup>
[#] Delitzsch, Frantz, “Über eine alte arabische Handschrift des Hebräerbriefes,” Commentar zum Briefe an die Hebräer: mit archäologischen und dogmatischen Excursen über das Opfer und die Versöhnung, Leipzig: Dörffling & Franke, 1857, pp. 764-769.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St. Petersburg</place>, RNL, Ar. N.S. 327</mssGroup>
James
Monferrer Sala, Juan Pedro, “Un manuscrito árabe oriental de la ‘Epistola de Santiago’, guardado en la Biblioteca de El Escurial,” Al-Andalus-Magreb 7 (1998), pp. 231-233.
[#]------, “Un fragment inédito y olvidado de la ‘Epístola de Santiago’, guardado en la Biblioteca de El Escorial,” Qurṭuba 3 (1998): 231-233 [on Escorial Codex Ar. 1625].
Johannine Epistles 
[#] Monferrer Sala, Juan Pedro, “An Eastern Arabic version of the three Epistles of Saint John (codex ar. 1625) kept in the Monastery of El Escorial (Madrid),” Samir, Samir Khalil (ed.), Actes du IIum Symposium Syro-Arabicum (Sayyidat al-Bīr, septembre 1998), Vol. 1, Études arabes chrétiennes, Parole de l’Orient 27 (2002), pp. 30-32.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Madrid</place>, Esc, Ar. 1625</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 72</mssGroup>; 151;Vatican, BAV, Ar. 13.
A short history of the Christian Arabic manuscripts in Spain, especially the biblical ones. Then, a description of the physical and orthographical characters of Ms, Madrid, Esc, Ar. 1625 and a comparison with the Greek Vorlage. Finally, a transcription of the Arabic text of the Johannine epistles and an English translation of them.
Revelation 
[#] Graf, Georg, “Arabische Übersetzungen der Apokalypse,” Biblica 10 (1929), pp. 170-194.
[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan-Pedro. “Una versión árabe del ‘Apocalipsis’ contenida en el Cod. Ár. 1625 de la Biblioteca de El Escorial: Estudio y edición,” Qurṭuba 5 (2000), pp. 147-180 
Includes edition of the Arabic text.
Ms. Escurial, Ar. 1625.
Apocrypha/Pseudoepigrapha
The Mythological Acts of the Apostles Transcribed from an Arabic Ms. in the Convent of Deyr-es-Suriani, Egypt, and from Mss. <mssGroup>in the Convent of St Catherine on Mount Sinai and in the Vatican Library.</mssGroup>
Évangiles Apocryphes II: L’Évangile de l’Enfance. Rédactions syriaques, arabe et arméniennes traduites et annotées. Textes et documents pour l’étude historique du christianisme. Translated by Peeters, Paul. Paris: Auguste Picard, 1914.
[#] Bezold, C., “Das arabisch-äthiopische Testamentum Adami”, in Orientalischen Studien Th. Nöldeke, Giessen, 1906, pp. 898-909. 
[#] Barnes, William Emery, “The Testaments of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob (Extracts from the Arabic Version),” in James, Montague Rhodes, The Testament of Abraham. The Greek Text, edited with Introduction and notes. Texts and Studies II, 2, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1892, pp. 133-154. 
Contains an English translation of excerpts from Ms. Paris, BNF, Ar. 132.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 132. </mssGroup>
[#] Battista, A and B. Bagatti, Il combattimento di Adamo, Studii Biblici Franciscani Collectio Minor 29, Jerusalem: xxxx, 1982.
[#]------, La Caverna dei Tresori, Jerusalem: xxx, 1979, pp. 46-51.
Contains an Italian translation of the Arabic version of the Testament of Adam.
[#]------, Edizione critica del testo arabo della ‘Historia Iosephi fabri lignarii’ e ricerche sulla sua origine, Studii Biblici Franciscani Collectio Minor 20, Jerusalem: xxxx, 1978. 
[#] Bausi, Alessandro, “A first evaluation of the arabic version of the apocalypse of Paul,” Parole de l’Orient 24 (1999), pp. 131-164.
[#] Bratke, E., “Handschriften Überlieferung und Buchstücke der Arabisch-Äthiopischen Petrusapokalypse,” ZWT 1(1893), 493
[#] Burmester, O.H.S., “Fragments from an Arabic Version of Two Infancy Gospels,” Studia Orientalia Christiana Collectanea 7 (1962), pp. 105-114.
[#] Charlesworth, James H. (ed.), The Old Testament Pseudepigrapha, Vol. 1, Apocalyptic Literature and Testaments, New York: Doubleday&Company, Inc., 1983. 
Refers to several Arabic translations of Pseudepigrapha: Fourth Book of Ezra (pp. 519), Testament of Abraham (p. 871), Testament of Isaac (pp. 903-911), Testament of Jacob (pp. 913-918), Testament of Adam (pp. 989-990).
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 132</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Or. 251</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 462</mssGroup>; 
S.A. Cook, “An Arabic Version of the Prologue to Ecclesiasticus,” in Proceedings of the Society of Biblical Archaeology 28 (1902), pp. 173-184.
[#] Cowper, B.H., The Apocryphal Gospels, London: xxxx, 1881. 
Contains an English translation of the Arabic Infancy Gospels, bases on Sike’s edition [#].
[#] Delcor, Mathias, Testaments d’Abraham. Introduction, traduction du texte grec et commentaire de la recension grecque longue, suivie de la traduction des Testaments d’Abraham, d’Isaac et de Jacob d’après les versions orientales, Studia in Veteris Testamenti Pseudoepigrapha 2, Leiden: Brill, 1973, pp. 17, 242-247. 
Contains a translation of the texts from Ms. Paris, BNF, Ar. 132 (by Marius Chaîne). 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 132. </mssGroup>
Review: Samir Khalil Samir, BAC 2 (1978), pp. 20-21. 

[#] Drint, Adriana, “Some Notes on the Arabic Versions of IV Ezra and the Apocalypse of Baruch in Ms Mount Sinai Arabic 589,” Parole de l’Orient 24 (1999), pp. 165-178.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 589.</mssGroup>
[#] ------, “The Mount Sinai Arabic version of IV Ezra : characteristics and relevance of an early Arabic translation of the Syriac text,” Orientalia Christiana Periodica 58 (1992), pp. 401-422.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 589 and Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Spreng. 30.</mssGroup>
[#] van Esbroek, Michel, “Les Actes syriaques de Philippe à Carthagène en version arabe,” OC 79 (1995), pp. 120-145.
An edition and translation of the Actes of Philipp in Arabic, based on Ms. Cambridge, CUL, Or. 1287. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Cambridge</place>, CUL, Or. 1287</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl. Nicoll 49</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 694, Sbath, 68</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 397, Ar. 469, and Ar. 553.</mssGroup>
[#] ------, “Les actes apocryphes de Thomas en version arabe,” Parole de l’Orient 14 (1987), pp. 11-77.
[#] Evetts. B., History of the Patriarchs of the Coptic Church of Alexandria, PO 1 (1904), pp. 120-134. 
GCAL 1, pp. 245-246
De sacerdotio Christi in Arabic. 
[#] Evetts, B. Patrologia Orientalis 1 (1904), pp. 134-140. 
Acta Marci
[#] Ewald, E.G.A., “Das vierte Ezrabuch nach seinem Zeitalter, seinen arabischen Übersetzungen und einer neuen Wiederherstellung,” Abhandlungen der königlichen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen 11 (1864), pp. 133-230.
[#] ------, “Über eine arabische Bearbeitung des vierten Ezrabuches,” Nachrichten von der G.A. Universität und der königlichen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen 11 (1863), pp. 163-180.
[#] Fabricius, Johann Albert, Codex Apocryphus Novi Testamenti, 4 Vols, Hamburg: xxxx, 1719. 
Vol. ?, pp. 309-36.Contains a Latin translation of an Arabic version of the “History of Joseph the Carpenter.”
Vol. 1, pp. 168 “Infancy Gospels” 
[#] Féghali, Paul, “Versions arabes de Ben Sira,” Parole de l’Orient 30 (2005), pp. 65-78.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 1</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Add. 30851</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 5</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Ar. 238</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Sinai</place>, Ar. 155. </mssGroup>
Galbiati, Giovanni, Iohannis Evangelium Apocryphum Arabice
	Review
	Löfgren, Oscar, Det bortglömda evangeliet, Svenska Dagbladet 7 Oct. 1960.
	------, “Das apokryphe Johannesevangelium”, Orientalistische Literaturzeitung 56 (1961), cols. 229-233.
[#] Frantsouzoff, Serge, “L’édition du Livre arabe des Macchabées dans les Polyglottes de Londres et la Bible manuscrite de St. Pétersbourg,” in Travaux de symposium international Le Livre. La Roumanie. L’Europe. Troisième édition – 20 à 24 Septembre 2010, Vol. 2, La deuxième section – Bibliothéconomie et les sciences de l’information (Bucarest: Éditeur Bibliothèque de Bucarest, 2011), pp. 85-94.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Institute of Oriental Manuscripts, D 226 and Vatican, BAA, Ar. 468. </mssGroup>
[#] Gauguine, Maurice, The Falasha Version of the Testaments of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, unpubl. PhD-Thesis, Manchester, 1965. 6.52
Treats a literal and freer translation of Arabic version into Ge’ez. 
[#] Garitte, Gérard, ““Protoevangelii Iacobi” Versio arabica antiquior,” Le Muséon 86 (1973), pp. 377-396.
Protoevangelium of James
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 436, Ar. 535, and Ar. 556.</mssGroup>
 [#] Genequand, Charles, “Vie de Jésus en Arabe,” in Bovon, François and Pierre Geoltrain, Écrits apocryphes chrétiens, Paris: Gallimard, 1997, pp. 207-238.
Introduction and French translation of the Infancy Gospels in Arabis. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Or. 350</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Florence</place>, BML, Or. 32</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Vatican</place>, BAV, Syr. 159. </mssGroup>
Gildemeister, J., Esdras Liber Quartus Arabice, Bonn, 1877. 
Contains an edition of IV Ezra, based on Mss. <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, Ar. 462 and Oxford, Bodleian Library, Hunt. 260. </mssGroup>
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Spreng. 30, Vatican, Ar. 462 and Oxford, Bodleian Library, Hunt. 260.</mssGroup>
[#] Giles, J.A., Codex Apocryphus Novi Testamenti. The uncanonical Gospels and other Writings, London: xxxx, 1852, i?
The History of Joseph the Carpenter  
[#] Gottheil, Richard, “An Arabic Version of the ‘Revelation of Esdras’,” Hebraica 4 (1887/1888), pp. 14-17
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 107 (check)</mssGroup>
[#] Guidi, Ignazio, “Gli atti apocrifi degli Apostoli nei testi copti, arabi ed etiopici,” Giornale della Società Asiatica Italiana 2 (1888), pp. 1-66.
[#] Hilgenfeld, , Messias Judaerum (), pp. xl-xli
On Ms. Oxford, Bodleian Library, Or. 251, containting IV Ezra. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Or. 251</mssGroup>
[#] James, Montague Rhodes, The Testament of Abraham. The Greek Text, edited with Introduction and notes. Texts and Studies II, 2, (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1892), pp. 34-49.
Comp. [#,Barnes, William Emery]
[#] Heide, Martin, Das Testament Abrahams: Edition und Übersetzung der arabischen und äthiopischen Versionen, Aethiopistischen Forschungen 76, Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 2012. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 132 and Ar. 4785</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>COP</place>, Bibl. 185 and Hist. 54</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Hist. 485</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Macarius</place>, Hag. 38</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Vatica</place>, BAV, Syr. 199. </mssGroup>
[#] ------, “The Coptic, Arabic and Ethiopic Versions of the Testament of Abraham and the Emergence of the Testaments of Isaac and Jacob,” in Charlesworth, James H., and Lee Martin MacDonald (eds.), “Non-canonical” Religious Texts in Early Judaism and Early Christianity (London: T&t Clark, 2012), pp. 61-72. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 132 and Ar. 4785</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Museum, Hist. 485</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Macarius</place>, Hag. 38</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>and Vatica</place>, BAV, Syr. 199.</mssGroup>
[#]------, “Yaʿǝqob: Gädla Yaʿǝqob,” in Encyclopaedia Aethiopica, Vol. 5, p. x.


OLS Da AFR äth 10-1


[#]------, “Yǝsḥaq: Gädla Yǝsḥaq,” in Encyclopaedia Aethiopica, Vol. 5, p. x.
	OLS Da AFR äth 10-1
[#]-------, “The Tradition and Transmission of the Ethiopic Testaments of the Three Patriarchs,” in Raunig, W. and S. Wenig (eds.), Afrikas Horn. Akten der Ersten Internationalen Littmann Konferenz 2. Bis 5. Mai 2002, meroitica 22 (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 2005), pp. 190-198.
Contains references to the Arabic versions. 
[#]------, “Abrǝham: Gädla Abrǝham,” in Encyclopaedia Aethiopica, Vol. 1, p. 49. 
Mentions several Ge’ez versions based on the Arabic. 


OLS Da AFR äth 10-1
[#] -------, Die Testamente Isaaks und Jakobs – Edition und Übersetzung der arabischen und äthiopischen Versionen, Aethiopistischen Forschungen 76, Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 2000.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 132 and Ar. 4785</mssGroup>;; Cairo, Coptic Museum, Hist. 485; and Vatica, BAV, Syr. 199.
Review: 	[#] Bausi, Alessandro, in Journal for the Study of Judaism 34 (2003), pp. 86-92.
		Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 4785 and Cairo, Coptic Museum, Hist. 485</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Macarius</place>, Hag. 38 and 44.</mssGroup>
[#] Bodgan, Burtea, in Orientalistische Literaturzeitung 97 (2002), pp. 586-590.
[#] Kleiner, Michael, in Aethiopica 5 (2002), pp. 271-275. 
[#] Wagner, Ewald, in Wiener Zeitschrift für die Kunde des Morgenlands 92 (2002), pp. 278-281. 
[#] Hofmann, Josef, “Der arabische Einfluß in der äthiopischen Übersetzung der Johannes-Apokalypse,” OC 43 (1959), pp. 24-53 und 44 (1960), pp. 25-39.
[#] Klijn, A.F.J., The Acts of Thomas: Introduction, Text, Commentary (Leiden:Brill, 1962), p. 9.
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Birmingham</place>, Mingana, Chr. Arab. 94.</mssGroup>
[#] van Koningsveld, P.Sj., “An Arabic Manuscript of the Apocalypse of Baruch,” Journal for the Study of Judaism 6 (1975), pp. 205-207. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 589</mssGroup>
[#] Krachkovskii, Ignatii, “Ein neutestamentliches Apokryph in einer arabischen Handschrift 885-886 n.Chr.,” Byzantinisches Jahrbuch 14 (1907/09), pp. 246-275. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, Russian National Library, Ar. NS 263.</mssGroup>
Also refered to in [#, see above]------, Über Arabische Handschriften gebeugt. Erinnerung an Bücher und Menschen, Leipzig: Koehler & Amelang, 1949, pp. 11-12.
[#] van Lantschoot, A, “,” Le Muséon 68 (1955), pp. 219-233.
[#] Leemhuis, F., “The Mount Sinai Arabic Version of the Apocalypse of Baruch,” Samir, Khalil Samir (ed.), Actes du deuxième congrès international d’études arabes chrétiennes (Osterhesselen, septembre 1984) (Rome: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1986), pp. 73-79.
[#]------, “The Arabic Version of the Apocalypse of Baruch: a Christian Text?,” Journal for the Study of Pseudoepigrapha 4 (1989), pp. 19-26.
[#] Leslau, Wolf, Falasha Anthology (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1951).
Touches on the Arabic source text of the Ethiopic Testaments of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 132.</mssGroup>
[#] Löfgren, Oscar, “Zur Charakteristik des apokryphen Johannesevangeliums,” Orientalalia Suecana 9 (1960), pp. 107-130, republished in Gustav Karlsson and Nils Simonsson (eds.), Studia Orientalia memoriae Erici Gren dedicta, Uppsala: xxx, 1961, pp. ???.
[#] ------, “Ergänzendes zum apokryphen Johannesevangelium,” Orientalia Suecena 10 (1961), pp. 137-144.
[#] ------, Det apokryfiska Johannesevangeliet. I översättning från den enda kända arabiska handskriften i Ambrosiana, Apokryfiska evangelier, Stockholm: Natur och Kultur, 258, pp. 
[#] ------, “An Arabic Recension of the ‘Vitae Prophetarum’,” Orientalia Suecana 25-26 (1976-1977), pp. 77-105.
[#] Mader, F., “L’apocalypse arabe de Daniel publiée, traduit et annotée”, Revue de l’Histoire des Religions 49 (1904), pp. 265-305.  
Byzantinische Zeitschrift 14 (1905), p. 690.
[#] Mingana, Alphonse, “The Apocalypse of Peter,” Woodnbrook Studies 3 (1931), pp. 93-152, 209-282, 349-407
Review: James, M.R. in JthSt 33 (1923), pp. 311
[see above, #] Monferrer Sala, Juan Pedro, Scripta arabica orientalia: dos studios de la literatura árabe cristiana, Granada:Athos Pérgamos, 1999.
Includes an edition of 1 Esdras, based on London, BL, Or. 1326.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 1326</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 13 and Ar. 468</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 151</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Escorial Cod. Ar. 1625.</mssGroup>
[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan-Pedro and Ph. Roisse, “Una versión árabe andalusí de la ‘Epístola apócrifa a los Laodicenses,” Qurṭuba 3 (1998): 113-151.
[#] Mopsik, Charles (ed.), Les Évangiles de l’ombre, Paris: Lieu Commun, 1983, pp.79-105.
For a French translation of the Arabic Infancy Gospels 
[#] Moraldi, L., Apocrifi del Nouvo Testamento, xxxx : xxxx, 1971, Vol. 1, 1971, pp. 281-311. 
Italian translation of the Arabic Infancy Gospels.
[#] Peeters, P. “A propos de la vie de Jésus en arabe. Le manuscrit de J. Gollius,” Analecta Bollandiana 41 (1923), pp. 132-134.
[#] ------, Évangiles apocryphes, 2. L’Évangile de l’Enfance. Rédactions syriaques, arabes et arméniennes traduites et annotées, Paris: xxx, 1914.
French translation of the Arabic Infancy Gospels, based on the edition of Sike [#].
[#] Provera, M., Il Vangelo arabo dell’Infanzia second ail MS. Laurenziano orientale n. 387, Jerusalem : xxxx, 1973.
[#] Tischendorf, Evangelia Apocrypha, Leipzip : xxxx, 1876, pp. xxxii-xxxvi, 122-139.
Fleischer in Tischendorf, Evangelia Apocrypha, Leipzip : xxxx, 1876, pp. 171-202. 
On infancy gospels in Arabic

Latin from Arabic, “The Story of Joseph the Carpenter”
[#] Rießler, Paul, Altjüdisches Schrifttum außerhalb der Bibel (Augsburg : xxx, 1928).
Contains a German translation of the Testament of Isaac. 
K. Samaan, Sept traductions arabes de Ben Sira (Frankfurt am Main, 1994).
[#] Sawyer, John. F., “Arabic Infancy Gospels,” in A Concise Dictionary of the Bible and its Reception, Louisville: Westminster John Knox Press, 2009, p. 20.
[#] Schneemelcher, Wilhelm, Neutestamentliche Apokryphen in deutscher Übersetzung, 2 vols. (Tübingen: J.C.B. Mohr (Paul Siebeck), 1997), Vol. 1, p. 335; Vol. 2, pp.150-151, 291, 388-389, 397, 402, 404-405, 412, 419-420, 421, 424, 431, 432-433, 435, 563 (Translated New Testament Apocrypha (Louisville: xxx, 1991), Vol. 1, pp. 419, 425, 456-57, by Wilson)
Mentions Arabic versions of the Acts of John, Acts of Thomas, Acts of John by Prochorus, Acta Petri et Pauli, Acta Andreae et Bathololmaei, Acta Thomae, Martyrium Marci, Passio Lucae, Acta Philippi et Petri, Acta Iacobi, Acta Simonis, Acta Thaddaei, and Revelation of Peter.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Ar. 171, Ar. 694, Syr. 199</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 539.</mssGroup>
Vol. 2, p. 398 
 [#] Scot Watson, W., “A Syriac Arabic Narrative of Miracles of Jesus,” American Journal of Semitic Languages and Literatures 16 (1899-1900), pp. 37-46.
[#] Sike, Henricus, Evangelium Infantiae vel liber apocryphus de infatia Salvatoris, ex manuscripto editit ac latina versione et notis illistravit, Utrecht: Trajectum ad Rhenum, 1697. 
The edition is based on a manuscript, acquired by Golius in Turkey in 1625. It was sold to the Bodleian Library, where it is preserved today under the shelf mark Ms. Oxford, Bodl., Or. 350. With Latin translation. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Or. 350. </mssGroup>
[#] Smith Lewis, Agnes, Acta mythologica Apostolorum, Horae Semiticae 3 (London: C.J. Clay and sons, 1904). 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 539</mssGroup>
[#]------,Acta mythologica Apostolorum, Horae Semiticae 4 (London: C.J. Clay and sons, 1904). 
[#] Steiner, H., “Der arabische Auszug des ‘Propheten Ezra’, nebst Berichtigungen zu der arabischen Uebersetzung,” Zeitschrift für wissenschaftliche Theologie 11 (1868), pp. 396-433.
[#] Stone, Michael E., “A New Manuscript of the Syro-Arabic Version of the Fourth Book of Ezra,” Journal for the Study of Judaism 8 (1977), pp. 183-184.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Arabic 589</mssGroup>
[#] de Strycker, Émile, La forme la plus ancienne du Protévangile de Jacques, Recherches sur le Papyrus Bodmer 5, avec une édition critique du texte grec et une traduction annotée (Brussels: Société des Bollandistes, 1961), p. 46.
Mentions the Arabic versions of the text briefly, with reference to [] Thilo.  
[#] Thilo, J.C., Codex Apocryphus Novi Testamenti, Leipzig : xxxx, 1832, Vol. 1, pp. xv-xxvi, 1-61. 
Contains a Latin translation of “The History of Joseph the Carpenter” in Arabic, alongside Rödiger’s revisions of Wallin’s Arabic text []. The translation is based on Sike’s edition [#].
[#] Tisserant, Eugène. “La version mozarabe de l’épître aux Laodicéens,” Revue Biblique n.s. 7 (1910): 249-253. [On Vat. Borg. arab. 67. Only the colophon is published. The same translation as in the article by de Vaux above.]
[#] Troupeau, Gérard, “Une version arabe du «Testament d’Adam»,” in Cramer, Patrick (ed.), Mélanges Antoine Guillaumont, Cahiers d’Orientalisme 20, Geneve, 1988, pp. 3-14.
[#] Ockley, Simon, appendix to Whiston, William, Primitive Christianity reviv’d, Vol. 4, An Account of the Faith of the two First Centuries (London: The Author, 1711).
Contains a translation of IV Ezra, as preserved in Ms. Oxford, Bodleian Library, Or. 251.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodleian Library, Or. 251.</mssGroup>
[#] Violet, Bruno, Die Ezra-Apokalypse () p. xxxix
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Paris</place>, BNF, Ar. 51</mssGroup>
The Epistle to the Laodiceans
de Vaux, Carra. “L’Épitre aux Laodicéens en arabe.” Revue Biblique 5 (1896): 221-226. [BnF arab. 80. Translated from Latin. Arabic text with commentary.]
Wallin, G. Historia Iosephi fabri lignarii. Liber apocryphus ex manuscripto Regiae Bibliothecae Parisiensis nunc primum arabice editus, nec non versione latina et notis illustrates, Leipzig
Compare the corrections on this text by Rödiger [#].
[#] Wetzel, E., Ein weiteres Bruchstück des Protoevangelium Jacobi im Cod. Sin. Ar. 436, unpubl. PhD-Thesis, Ludwig-Maximilian-Universität, Munich, 1990.

Biblical quotations in Christian Arabic writings

ʿAmmār al-Baṣrī 	 	 	
[#] Hayek, M., “ʿAmmār al-Baṣrī. La première Somme de théologie chrétienne en langue arabe, ou deux apologies du christianisme”, Islamochristiana 2 (1976), 69-133.
	
Abū Rāʾiṭa al-Takrītī, Ḥabīb b. Khidma	 	 	
[#] Keating, Sandra, “The Use and Translation of Scripture in the Apologetic Writings of Abū Rāʾiṭa al-Takrītī”, in: David Thomas (ed.), The Bible in Arab Christianity, Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2007, 257-274.
[#] Keating, Sandra, “Refuting the charge of taḥrīf: Abū Rāʾiṭa (d. ca. 835) and His ‘First Risāla On the Holy Trinity’,” in Günter, Sebastian (ed.), Ideas, Images, and Methods of Portrayel: Insights into Classical Arabic Literature and Islam, Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2005, 41-56.

	Dimitrie Cantemir
[#] Feodorov, Ioana, Dimitrie Cantemir, Salvation of the Sage and Ruin of the Sinful World, Bosten/Leiden: Brill, 2016.
	Contains a section on biblical quotations.

Peter of Bayt Raʾs (Kitāb al-Burhān)
[#] Chachia, Pierre and W.M. Watt (eds.), Eutychius of Alexandria: The Book of the Demonstration (Kitāb al-Burhān), Part I, Louvain: Secrétariat du Corpus SCO, 1960 [Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium, vols 192-193; Scriptores Arabici, vols. 20-21].
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 75 (fols 102-223)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Ar. 441 (fols 121-227)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Ar. 436 (?)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Vatican</place>, Biblioteca Vaticana, Ar. 491</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Ar. 645 (fols 184-192)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Jerusalem</place>, St. Anne, 33</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Cairo</place>, Coptic Orthodox Patriarchate, Theol. 209 (Simaika 238)</mssGroup>
Arab. text CSCO 192; Eng. trans. CSCO 193. The Kitāb al-Burhān was ascribed to St. Athanasius in the manuscript tradition. Following Graf [#], Chachia and Watt take Eutychius (Saʿīd ibn al-Biṭrīq) to be the author. The oldest Ms (Sinai, Ar. 75, fol. 102b), however, names Peter of Bayt Raʾs (Buṭrus al-Shammās ibn Nasṭās al-Bayt Raʾsī) as its author. Books II and III (§§ 401ff.) consist of testimonia catalogues.
[#] Graf, Georg, “Ein bisher unbekanntes Werk des Patriarchen Eutychios von Alexandrien,” in Oriens Christianus N.S. 1 (1911), 227-244; 2 (1912), 136-137.
[#] Swanson, Mark, “Ibn Taymiyya and the Kitāb al-burhān. A Muslim controversialist responds to a ninth-century Arabic Christian apology,” in Haddad, Y.Y. and W.Z. Haddad (eds.), Christian-Muslim encounters, Gainesville, FL: University Press of Florida, 1995, 95-107.
	 	 	 	
Al-Kitāb al-Jāmiʿ Wujūh al-Īmān bi-Tathlīth Waḥdaniyyat Allāh wa-Taʾannus Allāh al-Kalima min al-Ṭāhira al-ʿAdhrāʾ Maryam (The Compilation of the aspects of the faith in the Tri-unity of God and the Incarnation of God the Word from the pure one, the Virgin Mary = Summa Theologiae Arabica)
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Beirut</place>, Bibliothèque orientale, Ar. 552</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Birmingham</place>, Mingana, Chr. Ar. 170 (= Chr. Add. 140)</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, British Library, Or. 4950</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Munich</place>, State 	Library, Cod. Ar. 1071</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Sinai</place>, Ar. 330</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Ar. 431</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Ar. 448</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>Ar. 483</mssGroup>; <mssGroup>St. Andrews</place>, University Library, 14.</mssGroup>
[#] Griffith, Sidney H., The Church in the Shadow of the Mosque. Christians and Muslims in the World of Islam, Princeton/Oxford: Princeton University Press, 2008.
	 	 	 	
On Summa Theologiae Arabica [#]: pp. 52-53; 57-60; 82-83; 90.
[#] Swanson, Mark N., “Al-Kitāb al-jāmiʿ wujūh al-īman bi-tathlīth waḥdaniyyat Allāh wa-taʾannus Allāh al-kalima min al-ṭāhira al-ʿadhrāʾ Maryam,” in Thomas, David and Barbara Roggema (eds.), Christian-Muslim Relations. A Biographical History. Volume 2 (600-900), Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2009, pp. 793-798.
	On [#], with comprehensive bibliography.

Fī Tathlīth Allāh al-Wāḥid (On the Trinune Nature of God)
[#] Gallo, Maria, Palestinense anonimo. Omelia arabo-cristiana del'VIII secolo. Rome: Città Nuova Editrice, 1994.
	Italian translation of Gibson's edition [#].	 
[#] Gibson, Mageret Dunlop, An Arabic Version of the Acts of the Apostles and the Seven Catholic Epistles from an Eighth or Ninth Century MS. in the Convent of St Catherine on Mount Sinai, with a Treatise on the Triune Nature of God, and Translation form the Same Codex, Studia Sinaitica 7, London: C.J. Clay and Sons/Cambridge University Press, 1899. - Repr.: Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2004. - Repr.: Cambridge etc.: Cambridge University Press, 2012.
Ms.: Sinai, Ar. 154, fols. 99r-139v.
The third section of the text contains a list of 34 Old Testament testemonia. 	 	 	 	
[#] Griffith, Sidney H., The Bible in Arabic. The Scripture of the “People of the Book” in the Language of Islam, Princeton/Oxford: Princeton University Press, 2013.
	PP. ###### on [#].
[#] Griffith, Sidney H., The Church in the Shadow of the Mosque. Christians and Muslims in the World of Islam, Princeton/Oxford: Princeton University Press, 2008.
	On Fī Tathlīth Allāh al-Wāḥid [#]: pp. 53-57; 89-90; 167-68.
[#] Harris, James Rendel, “A tract on the triune nature of God”, in American Journal of Theology 5 (1901), pp. 75-86.
[#] Samir, Khalil S., “The Earliest Arab Apology for Christianity”, in Samir, Khalil S. and Jørgen S. Nielson (eds.), Christian Arabic Apologetics during the Abbasid Period (750-1258), Leiden: Brill, 1994, pp. 57-114.
[#] Samir, Khalil S., “Une apologie arabe du christianisme d'époque umayyade?”, in Parole d'Orient 16 (1990-91), 85-106.
[#] Swanson, Mark N., “Fī tathlīth Allāh al-wāḥid”, in Thomas, David and Barbara Roggema (eds.), Christian-Muslim Relations. A Biographical History, vol I:600-900, Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2009, pp. 330-333.
[#] Swanson, Mark N., “Apologetics, catechesis, and the question of audience in 'On the triune nature of God' and three treatises of Theodore Abū Qurrah”, in Tamcke, M. (ed.), Christians and Muslims in Dialogue in the Islamic Orient of the Middle Ages, Beirut/Würzburg: Ergon, 2007, 133-134.

Testimonia 	 	
[#] Bertaina, David, “The Development of Testimony Collections in Early Christian Apologetics with Islam”, in Thomas, David (ed.), The Bible in Arab Christianity, Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2007, 151-174.
[#] Frantsuzov, S.A., “Об одной новозаветной цитате в арабо-мусульманских сочинениях” [A Quotation from the New Testament in Arab Muslim Writings], in: Vestnik PSTGU III.1 (7) (2007), 99-106.
On 1 Cor 2:9, compares Christian Arabic translations with Muslim 	testimonies. 
[#] Graf, Georg, “Christlich-arabische Texte; Zwei Disputationen zwischen Muslimen und Christen” in Bilabel, Friedrich and Adolf Grohmann (eds.), Griechische, koptische und arabische Texte zur Religion und religiösen Literatur in Ägyptens Spätzeit, Heidelberg: Verlag der Universitätsbibliothek, 1934, pp. 1-31.
On the oldest Christian Arabic apologies preserved in several papyrus 	fragments. Fragmentary quotes of #######.
[#] Griffith, Sidney H., The Bible in Arabic. The Scripture of the “People of the Book” in the Language of Islam, Princeton/Oxford: Princeton University Press, 2013.
	PP. ####### on testimonia.	 	 	 	
[#] Suerman, Harald, “The Use of Biblical Quotations in Christian Apocalyptic Writings of the Umayyad Period,” in Thomas, David (ed.), The Bible in Arab Christianity, Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2007, 69-90.

Theodore Abū Qurrah 	 	 	
[#] Eskhult, Mats, “Some Remarks on the Biblical Quotations in Abū Qurrah’s Tract On the Veneration of the Holy Icons”, in Parole d’Orient 39 (2014), 19-31.
[#] Mihoc, V.O., “Der Schriftgebrauch im christlich-islamischen Kontext. Ein Beispiel der Intertextualität bei Theodor Abū Qurrah”, in Journal of Eastern Christian Studies 65.1-2 (2013), 1-20.
[#] Rissanen, S., “Der richtige Sinn der Bibel bei Theodor Abu Qurra”, in Kvist, Hans-Olof (ed.), Bibelauslegung und Gruppenidentität. Vorträge der vierten Finnisch-deutschen Theologentagung (Makarios-Symposium) im Kloster Neu-Valamo, Finnland 28.-30.8.1991, Åbo: Åbo Akademis Förlag, 1992, 79-90.
[#] Samir, K. S., “Notes sur les citations bibliques chez Abū Qurrah”, in Orientalia Christiana Periodica 49 (1983), 184-91.
[#] Tritton, Arthur S., “The Bible Text of Theodore Abu Qurrah”, in Journal of Theological Studies 34 (1933), pp. 52-54.

Timothy I
[#] Caspar, R., “Les versiones arabes du dialogue entre le patriarche Timothée I et le calife al-Mahdî (II/VIII siècle): ‘Mohammed a suivi la voie des prophètes’”, in Islamochristiana 3 (1977), 107-175.
[#] Cheikho, Louis [Luwīs Šayḫū], “The religious dialogue which occured between the Caliph al-Mahdi and Timothy the Patriarch”, in Al-Machriq 19 (1921), pp. 359-374; pp. 408-418. [in Arabic]	 	
[#] Putnam, H., L’église et l’Islam sous Timothée I (780-823): étude sur l’église nestorienne au temps des premiers ʿAbbāsides: avec nouvelle édition et traduction du Dialogue entre Timothée et al-Mahdi, Beirut: Dār al-Machreq éditeurs, 1975. 	 	


Judaeo-Arabic 
general
J. Blau, “On karaite translations of the Bible into Arabic from the tenth and eleventh centuries” [in Hebrew], Tarbiz, 67.3 (1998): 417-430.
[#] Blau, Joshua and Simon Hopkins,. “Ancient Bible Translations to Judeo-Arabic” (in Hebrew), Peʿamim 83 (2000), pp. 4-14. 
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>St. Petersburg</place>, RNL, Yevr. II C 1/2</mssGroup>
[#] J. Blau and S. Hopkins. ניצני פרשנות המקרא בערבית-היהודית על סמך גלוסר קדום לספר תהילים,in M. Bar-Asher, S. Stroumsa, S. Hopkins and B. Chiesa (eds.), דבר דבור על אופניו (Jerusalem: Ben Zvi Institute. 2007):235-284.
[#] Dukes, Leopold, “Literaturhistorische Mittheilungen ueber die ältesten hebräischen Exegeten, Grammatiker und Lexicographen”, in Heinrich Ewald und Leopold Dukes (eds.), Beiträge zur Geschichte der Aeltesten Auslegung und Spracherklärung des Alten Testaments, Stuttgart: Verlag von Adolph Krabbe, 1844, Vol. 2.
[#] Gallego, María Ángeles, "De Sa'adia al-Sarh: Traducciones de la biblia al judeo-árabe," in Martínez Delgado, José (ed.), El viaje lingüístico de la Biblia. Granada, 2011, pp. 169-179.
 [#] Polliack, Meira, “Arabic Bible translations in the Cairo Genizah collections,” in Haxen, U., H. Trautner-Kromann and K. L. Goldschmidt Salamon (eds.), Jewish studies in a new Europe : proceedings of the Fifth Congress of Jewish Studies in Copenhagen 1994 under the auspices of the European Association for Jewish Studies, Copenhagen: C.A. Reitzel, 1998, pp. 595-620
M. Polliack, “Medieval Karaite Methods of Translating Biblical Narrative into Arabic,” in Vetus Testamentum 48 (1998), pp. 375-398.
M. Polliack, “suge na-targumim ha-ʿaraviyim la-miqra be-genizat qahir ʿal-pi qatalog ha-ḥomer ha-ʿaravi T-S Arabic,”‬ Te'udah (1999) 15:109-125.
Polliack, Meira, and Sasson Somekh.. שני גלוסרים מקראיים עבריים-ערביים מגניזת קהיר. Pe'amim 83 (2001), pp. 15-47.
M. Steinschneider, Die arabische Literatur der Juden (Frankfurt, 1902), pp. 283-289.
Pentateuch
________, The Karaite Tradition of Arabic Bible Translation. A Linguistic and Exegetical Study of Karaite Translations of the Pentateuch from the Tenth and Eleventh Centuries C.E. Études sur le Judaïsme Médiéval 17 (Leiden, 1997). [Rev. A. Shivtiel in VT 50 (2000): 275-276; S. Hopkins in JQR n.s. 89 (1999): 426-431.]
Israelson, Samuel ben-Hofni
Early non-saadianic 
Y. Tobi, "Seridei Targum ‘Aravi la-Torah Qodem le-Tafsir Rav Saadiah Gaon" [Fragments of a pre-Sa'adian Arabic Translation of the Torah]. Mesorot 7 (1993) 87-127.
Y. Tobi, "Targum ‘Aravi-Yehudi 'Ammami Nosaf la-Torah" [An Additional Popular Judeo-Arabic Translation of the Torah]. In: Meḥqārīm be-Lašon ha-ʿIvrit uve-Lešonot ha-Yehūdīm Mugašīm le-Shelomo Morag, ed. M. Bar-Asher (Jerusalem, 1996), pp. 481-501.
Y. Tobi, "‘Al Qadmuto shel Tirgumei ha-Miqra be-'Aravit Yehudit ve-Qeta‘ mi- Tirgum ‘Aravi-Yehudi Qadum la-Miqra" [On the antiquity of Judeo-Arabic translations of the Bible and on a fragment of an ancient Judeo-Arabic translation of the Bible]. in Bein 'Ever le-'Arav, ed. Y. Tobi (Tel Aviv, 2001), pp. 17-60.
Saadiah
[#] J. Blau, “Saadya Gaon’s Pentateuch Translation and the Stabilization of Mediaeval Judaeo-Arabic Culture.” In Jože Krašovec, ed., The Interpretation of the Bible. The International Symposium in Slovenia, Journal for the Study of the Old Testament Supplement Series 289 (Sheffield, 1998), pp. 393-398.
[#] ________, “The Linguistic Character of Saadia Gaon’s Translation of the Pentateuch,” Oriens 36 (2001): 1-9. 
[#] J. Blau, “Iyyunim bi-Ketav Yad Mizrahi mi-Tehilat ha-Meʾah ha-11 shel Targum Rasag la-Torah" [Observations on an Eastern early 11th century Manuscript of Sa'adya's Translation of the Pentateuch] Leshonenu 51 (1998) 111. 
[#] J. Blau, “Some Instances Reflecting the Influence of Saadya Gaon's Bible Translation on Later Judeo-Arabic Writings,” in Occident and Orient: A Tribute to the Memory of Alexander Scheiber, ed. R. Dan (Leiden, 1988), PAGES
[#] David Freidenreich, “The Use of Islamic Sources in Saadiah Gaons Tafsīr of the Torah,” JQR 93:3-4 (2003): 353-395.
C.J. Hughes, De Lagardes Ausgabe der arabischen Übersetzung des Pentateuchs. Cod. Leid. arab. 377 nachgeprüft (Leipziger semitische Studien 7,3; Leipzig, 1920).
M. Katten and Samir Khalil Samir, “Untersuchungen zu Saadjas arabischer Pentateuchübersetzung,” in Parole de L’Orient 32 (2007), pp. 23-74.
link to Katten's original publication 
Henry Malter, Saadia Gaon: His Life and Works (Philadelphia, 1921), pp. 308-329. [An overview of the remnants of Saadia Gaon’s Judeo-Arabic translation.]
Mutius, x von, Targum and Saadia
+ other mutius on Judaeo-Arabic
[#] Schwarzstein, J. 1886. Targum Arvi: Die arabische Interpretation des Pentateuchs von Rabbi Saadiah hagaon Karlsruhe: Verlag von A. J. Hofmann 
[#] Vollandt, R. "The Arabic Pentateuch of the Paris Polyglot: Saadiah Gaon’s Advent to the Republic of Letters." In S. Binay and St. Lederer, eds. Proceedings of the Conference on Linguistic and Cultural Aspects of Arabic Bible Translation. Beirut (forthcoming).
[#] Zwick, Süssie, Die Pentateuchübersetzung des Saadia und das Targum Onkelos, Wien: xxx, 1901. 
YbE
Marjena
YbY
M. Polliack, “Alternate Renderings and Additions in Yeshu‘ah ben Yehudah’s Arabic Translation of the Pentateuch,” in Jewish Quarterly Review 84 (1993-94), pp. 209-225.
AbS
Skoss, Solomon L., Arabic commentary of ben Suleimān the Karaite on the book of Genesis, edited from the unique manuscripts and provided with critical notes and an introduction (Philadelphia, 1928).
Others 
J. Hirsch, Fragment einer arabischen Pentateuch-Übersetzung (Leipzig, 1900).
Sharh
[#] Bar-Asher, Moshe, לשון לימודים לרבי רפאל בירדוגו 3 vols. Jerusalem: The Hebrew University, 2001.
[#]------, מסורות ולשונות של יהודי צפון-אפריקה, Jerusalem: Academy of Hebrew Language 1998.
[#] ———, השרח המערבי למקרא ולספרות יהודית אחרת. טיבו ודרכי גיבושו. In מחקרים בלשונות היהודים, edited by M. Bar-Asher. Jerusalem: Misgav Yerushalaym, 1988pp. 3-33.
Historical Books
N. Schorstein, ed., Der Kommentar des...Jephet ben ‘Ali zum Buche Rûth, zum ersten Male nach drei Mss. <mssGroup><place>ediert</place>, mit Einleitung und Anmerkungen versehen (Inaugural-Dissertation zu Heidelberg</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, 1903).</mssGroup>
M. Peritz: Zwei alte arabische Uebersetzungen des Buches Ruth (Berlin, 1900)
Prophets
P. Birnbaum, ed., The Arabic Commentary of Yephet ben ‘Ali the Karaite on the Book of Hosea (Philadelphia, 1942).
O. Löfgren, Studien zu den arabischen Danielübersetzungen mit besonderer Berücksichtigung der christlichen Texte. Nebst einem Beitrag zur Kritik des Peschittatextes (Uppsala Universitets Årsskrift 4; Uppsala, 1936).
D.S. Margoliouth, ed., A Commentary on the Book of Daniel by Jephet ibn Ali (Anecdota Oxoniensia; Oxford, 1889).
S. Munk, Notice sur R. Saadia Gaon et sa version arabe d’Isaïe (Paris, 1838).
Sabih, Joshua A., Japheth ben Ali's Book of Jeremiah: A Critical Edition and Linguistic Analysis of the Judaeo-Arabic Translation (London / Oakville, CT, 2009).
[#] Schröter, R., “Die in Cod. Hunt. 206 aufbewahrte arab. Uebersetzung der kleinen Propheten, herausgeben und mit Anmerkungen verdeutscht: Hosea” in Archiv für die wissenschaftliche Erforschung des Alten Testaments, ed. Adalbert Merx, Halle: Verlag der Buchhandlung des Waisenhauses, 1869, Vol. 1, pp. 28-54; 153-194
Deals with a Judaeo-Arabic commentary of Hosea and furnishes an edition text in Arabic letters, as well as a German translation. 
Ms.: Oxford, Bodl. Hunt. 206
[#] ------, “Die in Cod. Hunt. 206 aufbewahrte arabische Uebersetzung der kleinen Propheten herausgegeben und mit Anmerkungen verdeutscht: Joel”, in Archiv für die wissenschaftliche Erforschung des Alten Testaments, ed. Adalbert Merx, Halle: Verlag der Buchhandlung des Waisenhauses, 1869, Vol. 2, pp. 1-38. 
As the previous, for Joel. 
Ms.: Oxford, Bodl. Hunt. 206
[#] Spiegel, Hermann, Saadia al-Fajjumi's arabische Danielversion : nach einem Manuscript der kgl. Bibliothek in Berlin, Berlin : Druck von H. Itzkowski, 1906.
J.B. van Zijl, “The British Library MS Or. 2211 of Saadia Gaon’s Arabic Translation of Isaiah.” JSS 37 (2001): 1992-57-63.

Sapiental Books
[#] Baron, Sally, Saadia Al-fajjûmi's arabische Psalmenübersetzung und Commentar (Psalm 50-72), Berlin: M. Poppelauer, 1900.
Review: Friedländer, J., ZfHB 6 (1901), pp. 40-41.
[#] Baumstark, Anton, “Minbar = Thron, und älteste arabische Psaltertexte,” in Orientalistische Literaturzeitung 46 (1943), pp. 337-341.
Mss. <mssGroup><place>Violet fragment and Bryn Mawr College Library</place>, BV 47 (formerly Zurich Or. 94).</mssGroup>
[#] J. Blau, “On a Fragment of the Oldest Judaeo-Arabic Bible Translation Extant,” in: Genizah Research after Ninety Years: The Case of Judaeo-Arabic, eds. J. Blau and S. Reif (Cambridge, 1992), pp. 31-39. 
Additional fragments have been published/announced in (Hopkins) 
J.J.L. Bargès, ed., Libri Psalmorum...versio a R. Yapheth ben Heli (Paris, 1861).
________, ed. Rabbi Yepheth abou [sic] Aly...in Canticum Canticorum commentarium arabicum (Paris, 1884).
Cohn, John, Das Buch Hiob: Cap. 1-5. Übers. u. erl. von Gaon Saadia, Altona:xxx, 1889.
R. Ecker, Die arabische Job-Übersetzung des Gaon Saadja ben Josef al-Fajjûmî (Studien zum alten und neuen Testaments 4; Munich, 1962).
Eisen, Ernst, Saʻadja al-Fajjûmî's arabische Übersetzung und Erklärung der Psalmen. Psalm 90-106, Leipzig : Teicher, 1934
[#] Ewald, Heinrich, “Ueber die arabisch geschriebenen Werke Jüdischer Sprachgelehrten mit einer Abhandlung ueber den gegenwärtigen Zustand der alttestamentlichen Wissenschaft”, in Heinrich Ewald und Leopold Dukes (eds.), Beiträge zur Geschichte der Aeltesten Auslegung und Spracherklärung des Alten Testaments, Stuttgart: Verlag von Adolph Krabbe, 1844, Vol. 1.
On Saadiah’s translation of the Psalms and Saadiah’s and ibn Gikatila’s translations of Job.
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl. Poc. 281, and ?</mssGroup>
[#] Hanneberg, Daniel, “Ueber die in einer Münchener Handschrift aufbehaltene arabische Psalmenübersetzung des R. Saadia Gaon : mit einer Probe”, in Abhandlungen der Philosophisch-philologischen Klasse der Königlich-Bayerischen Akademie der Wissenschaften 3 (1841), pp. 354-410.
Hofman, Über die in einer Münchener Handschrift auf- behaltene arab. Psalmenübersetzung d. R. Saadia Gaon, 1891)
[#] Hoffmann, Theodor, Die korachitischen Psalmen aus Saadias arabischer Übersetzung und Erklärung der Psalmen, Stuttgart : Druck der J.B. Metzlerschen Buchdruckerei, 1891.
[#] Galliner, Siegfried, Saadia Alfajjûmi's arabische Psalmenübersetzung und Commentar (Psalm 73-89). Nach einer Münchener, einer Berliner und einer Oxforder Handschrift herausgegeben und mit Anmerkungen versehen, Berlin: Druck von H. Itzkowski, 1903.
Review: Eppenstein, ZfHB 8 (1904), pp. 98-99.
[#] Lauterbauch, Jacob Zallel, Saadja's Al-fajjûmi's arabische Psalmenübersetzung und Commentar. Psalm 107-124 . Herausgegeben, übersetzt und mit Anmerkungen versehen, Berlin: xxx, 1903.
[#] Lehman, S., Saadia al-Fajûmî’s arabische Psalmenübersetzung: Psalm 21-24, Berlin, 1901. 
[#] Marwich, Lawrence, Arabic commentary of Salmon ben Yeruham the Karaite on the book of Psalms, chapters 42-72. Edited from the unique ms. in the State Public Library in Leningrad (Philadelphia, 1956).
[#] Merx, Adalbert, Die Saadjanische Uebersetzung des hohen Liedes ins arabische nebst andern auf das hohe Lied bezüglichen arabischen Texten herausgegeben, Heidelberg : Winter, 1882.
[#] Margulies, Samuel Hirsch, Saadia al-Fajûmî’s arabische Psalmenübersetzung, Breslau:xxx, 1884.
[#] Riese, Moshe I., The Arabic Commentary of Solomon ben Yeruham the Karaite on Ecclesiastes (Ann Arbor, 1973).
[#] Schreier, Bernard, Saadja Al-fajjûmi's arabische Psalmenübersetzung und Commentar (Psalm 125-150), Berlin: Druck von Itzkowski, 1904. 
[#] M. Wechsler, “The Arabic Translation and Commentary of Yefet ben ‘Eli on Proverbs 31:1–9,” Revue des études juives 161 (2002): 393-409.
________, “An Early Karaite Commentary on the Book of Esther,” Hebrew Union College Annual 72 (2002): 101–37.
[#] Zafrani, Haim and André Caquot, L'Ecclésiaste et son commentaire: “le livre de l'ascèse”: la version arabe de la Bible de Sa'adya Gaon (Paris, 1989).
Other old testament 
[#] M. Wechsler, The Arabic Translation and Commentary of Yefet ben ‘Eli the Karaite on the Book of Esther: Edition, Translation, and Introduction (Ph.D. dissertation, University of Chicago, 2006).
________, The Arabic Translation and Commentary of Yefet ben ‘Eli the Karaite on the Book of Esther  (Karaite Texts and Studies 1 / Études sur le judaïsme médiéval 36; Leiden: Brill, 2008).
________, From Persia with Love: The Arabic Translation and Homiletical Commentary of Salmon ben Yeruḥam on the Book of Esther (Karaite Texts and Studies 6 / Études sur le judaïsme médiéval 47; Leiden: Brill, 2011).

Samaritan 
See above [#] Bloch.
[#] Björnstahl, J.J., “Über eine Samaritanische Triglotte in der Barberinischen Bibliothek,” in Johann Goffried Eichhorn (ed.), Repertorium für biblische und morgenländische Litteratur, Vol. 3, Leipzig: Weidmann, 1778, pp. 84-102.
On the Barberini Triglot, which belonged to Peiresc and was given to Barberini
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Vatican</place>, BAV, Barberini Or. 1.</mssGroup>
 [#] A.D. Crown, The Samaritan Scribes and Manuscripts (Tübingen, 2001), pp. 22-25
[#] G. Schwarb, “Samaritan Acquaintance with Qaraite Bible Translations: Fact or Fiction,” Journal of Intellectual History in the Islamicate World 1 (forthcoming, 2013).
Check the bibliography there. 
 [#] T.G.J. Juynboll, “Commentatio de versione Arabico-Samaritana, et de scholiis, quae codicibus Parisiensibus n. 2 et 4 adscripta sunt,” in Orientalia 2 (1846), pp. 113-157.
[] von Gall, xxx, Der Hebräische Pentateuch der Samaritaner, Giesen: xxx, 1918.
[#] A.S. Halkin, “The Scholia to Numbers and Deuteronomy in the Samaritan Arabic Pentateuch,” JQR 34, new series (1943-44): 41-59.
[#] A.C. Hwiid, Specimen ineditae versionis Arabico-Samaritanae, Pentateuchi e codice manuscripto Bibliothecae Barberinae (Rome, 1780). [Pp. 28-63 have the text of Gen 49 in Samaritan characters and Arabic characters, together with the Polyglot version for comparison, along with some annotations.]
[#, see above] Kahle, Paul, The Cairo Genizah. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1959, pp. 54-57.
He regarded the Samaritan translations into Arabic dependent on Saadiah’s version and was followed by his pupils [Katten, Algermissen]
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Berlin</place>, Staatsbibliothek, Petermann 3</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>London</place>, BL, Or. 7562</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>St Petersburg</place>, NRL, Sam 179</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Oxford</place>, Bodl., Or. 139</mssGroup>; <mssGroup><place>Uss. II</place>, John Ryland. </mssGroup>
 [#] A. Kuenen, Libri Exodi et Levitici secundum arabicam Pentateuchi Samaritani versionem ab Abu-Saido conscriptam. Leiden, 1854.
[#] ________, Specimen e literis orientalibus exhibens librum Geneseos, secundum arabicam Pentateuchi samaritani versionem ab Abu-Saido conscriptam. Leiden, 1851.
[#] ________, Specimen theologicum continens Geneseos libri capita triginta quatuor priora ex Arabica Pentateuchi Samaritani Versione nunc primum edita cum prolegomenis (Leiden, 1851).

R. Macuch, “On the Problems of the Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch,” Israel Oriental Studies 9 (1979): 147-173.
[#] Ramon Díaz, J., “Las versions árabes del Pentateuco entre los Samaritanos,” Estudios Bíblicos 18 (1959), pp. 299-301.
E. Robertson, “The Relationship of the Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch to that of Saadya,” in E.I.J. Rosenthal, ed., Saadya Studies (Manchester, 1943), pp. 166-176.
S. de Sacy, “Mémoire sur la version arabe des livres de Moïse à l’usage des Samaritains et sur les manuscrits de cette version,” in Mémoires de l’Académie Royale des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres 49 (1808), pp. 1-149, 783-786.
H. Shehadeh, “The Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch,” in A.D. Crown, ed., The Samaritans (Tübingen, 1989), pp. 481-516.
________, The Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch [in Hebrew], PhD thesis, Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 1977.
________, “The Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch” [in Hebrew], Tarbiz, 52.1 (1982): 59-82.
________, The Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch edited from Manuscripts, vol. 1, Genesis-Exodus [Hebrew, Arabic, and English] (Jerusalem, 1989).
________, The Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch Volume II: Leviticus, Numbers, Deuteronomy, Jerusalem: The Israel Academy of Science and Humanities, 2002.
________, “Arabic Versions of the Pentateuch,” in A. Crown, R. Pummer, and A. Tal, eds., A Companion to Samaritan Studies (Tübingen, 1993), pp. 22-24.
________, “The Classification of the Versions of the Samaritan Arabic Translation of the Pentateuch and Identifying Nomenclature of the Fauna” [in Hebrew, English summary], Leshonenu, 48-49.1 (1984): 35-48.
________, “The Groups of the Samaritan Manuscripts of the Arabic Translation of the Pentateuch,” in J.-P. Rothschild and G.D. Sixdenier, eds., Études samaritaines, Pentateuque et Targum, exégèse et philologie, chroniques (Paris, 1988), pp. 205-218.
________, “A New Group of Manuscripts including an Arabic translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch (ATSP),” In A. Tal and M. Florentin, eds. Proceedings of the First International Congress of the Société d’ Études Samaritaines, Tel-Aviv, April-13, 1988. Tel-Aviv, 1991. Pp. 275-292.
________, “A New Unknown Version of the Arabic Translation of the Samaritan Pentateuch?” in M. Macuch, et al., eds., Studia Semitica necnon Iranica Rudolpho Macuch septuagenario (Wiesbaden, 1989), pp. 303-327.
Vloten, W. van. Specimen philogicum continens descriptionem codicis MS Bibliothecae Lugduno-Batavae partemque inde excerptam versionis Samaritano-arabicae Pentateuchi Mosaici. 1803.
Zhamkochian, A.S. Neopublikovannye fragmenty arabskikh versij samaritianskogo Piatiknizhija iz sobranija RNB [Newly Identified and Unpublished Fragments of the Arabic Versions of the Samaritan Pentateuch from the collection of the National Library of Russia]. PhD Dissertation. Yerevan University, 1994.
Zhamkochian, A.S. “Samaritiano-arabskie rukopisi Knigi Iisusa syna Navina v Rossijskoj Natsional’noj biblioteke” [Samaritan Arabic manuscripts of the Book of Joshua in the National Library of Russia], in: Arabskij mir v kontse XX veka: Materialy I-oj konferentsii arabistov IV RAN. Moscow, 1996.
Zhamkochian, A.S. Vnov’ identifitsirovannye i neopublikovannye fragmenty arabskikh versij samaritianskogo Piatiknizhija iz sobranija Rossijskoj Natsional’noj biblioteki [Newly Identified and Unpublished Fragments of the Arabic Versions of the Samaritan Pentateuch from the collection of the National Library of Russia]. Moscow, 2001.

Muslim reception 
Nikolai on Christian Poets 
Im ordner 
[#] Accad, M. "The Gospels in the Muslim Discourse of the Ninth to the Fourteenth Centuries: An Exegetical Inventorial Table." Islam and Christian-Muslim Relations 14 (2003): 67-91, 205-220, 337-352, 459-479. 
Im ordner
[#] Adang, Camilla, “A rare case of biblical ‘testimonies’ to the Prophet Muḥammad in Muʿtalizī literature: Qutations from Ibn Rabban al-Ṭabarī's Kitāb al-dīn wa-l-dawla in Abū l-Ḥusayn al-Baṣrī’s Ghurar al-adilla, as preserved in a work by al-Ḥimmaṣī al- Rāzī,” in A Common Rationality: Muʿtazilism in Islam and Judaism, edited by C. Adang, S. Schmidtke and D. Sklare. Würzburg: Ergon Verlag in Kommission, 297–330.
[#] ------, Muslim writers on Judaism and the Hebrew Bible: from Ibn Rabban to Ibn Hazm (Islamic philosophy, theology and science ; v. 22; New York: Brill, 1996.
T. Baarda, ‘Het ontstaan van de vier Evangelien volgense Abd al-Djabbar,” Nederlands Theologisch Tijdschrift 28 (1974): 215-38.
[#] Bacher, Wilhelm, “Muhammedanische Weissagungen im Alten Testament,” ZAW 15 (1895), pp. 309-311.
[#] Baumstark, Anton, “Eine frühislamische und eine vorislamische arabische Evangelienübersetzung aus dem Syrischen,” in Atti del XIX congresso internazionale degli Orientalisti 1938
________, ‘Das Problem eines vorislamischen christlich-kirchlichen Schrifttums in arabischer Sprache,’ Islamica 4 (1929-1931): 565-66.
________, “Zu den Schriften al-Kirmani’s,” Der Islam 20 (1932): 308-13.
________, “Eine altarabische Evangelienuebersetzung aus dem Christlich Palaestinensischen,” Zeitschrift für Semitistik 8 (1932): 201-09.
Beumont, M. “Muslim Readings of John’s Gospel in the ‘Abbasid Period.” Islam and Christian Muslim Relations 19.2 (2008): 179-197.
[#] Brockelmann, Carl, “Muhammedanische Weissagungen im Alten Testament,” ZAW 15 (1895), pp. 135-42.
 [#] Cheikho, P.L., “Quelques Legendes Islamiques Apocryphes”, Mélanges de la Faculté Orientale 4 (1910), pp. 33-56. 
On the influence of biblical and apocryphal material Jāhilī poets, Qurʾān, and early Muslim authors. Contains references to Muslim Pseudo-Scriptures (see below). 
Cook, David, “New Testament Citations in the Ḥadīth Literature and the Question of Early Gospel Translations into Arabic.” In Emmanouela Grypeou, Mark N. Swanson, and David Thomas, eds., The Encounter of Eastern Christianity with Early Islam (Leiden, 2006), pp. 185-223.
[#] Déclais, Jean-Louis, "L'Évangile selon Wahb ibn Munabbih et sa famille," MIDEO 28 (2010), 127-203
[#] Gabrieli, G., “Ebbero gli Arabi prima di Maometto una versione araba dell Vangelo?,” Studi Religiosi 1 (1901), pp. 355-357.
[#] Goeje, M. J. de, “Quotations from the Bible in the Qoran and the Tradition”, in George Alexander Kohut (ed.), Semitic studies in memory of Rev. Dr. Alexander-Kohut, Berlin: S. Calvary & Co., 1897, pp. 495-513.
Reprint in Gesammlete Schriften. Islamische und jüdisch-islamische Studien, pp. 347-365.
Goldenstein, M., “Sa‘adya Tafsir in Light of Muslim Polemic against Ninth-Century Arabic Bible Translations,” Jerusalem Studies in Arabic and Islam 36 (2009): 173-199.
[#] Goldziher, Ignaz, “Matth. VII, 5 in der muhammedanischen Literatur,” ZDMG 31 (1877), pp. 765-767.
[#]------, “Ueber muhammedanische Polemik gegen Ahl al-Kitāb,” ZDMG 32 (1878), pp. 341-378.
[#]------, “Ueber muhammedanische Polemik gegen Ahl al-Kitāb,” ZAW 13 (1893), pp. 315-321.
Identical?
 [#][#]------, “Neutestamentliche Elemente in der Traditionsliteratur des Islam,” OC 2 (192), pp. 390-397.
Melanges judeo-arabes REJ 44 und 45
[#] Hussein, Mohammad al-Sadeq, “Les Psaumes 1 a 25 traduits en arabe,” MIDEO 5 (1958), pp. 1-46
A new translation of Psalms 1-25.
[see above, #] Karoui, Said, “Die arabische Bibel und ihre Rezeption in der arabischen Literatur – Eine bibliographische Skizze,” Oriens Christianus, 83 (1999), pp. 130-146.
R.G. Khoury, “Quelques réflexions sur la première ou les premières Bibles arabes,” in T. Fahd, ed., L’Arabie préislamique et son environnement historique et culturel (Actes du Colloque de Strasbourg 24-27 juin 1987) (Leiden, 1989), pp. 551-561.
[#] ------,”Quelques Réflexions sur les citations de la Bible dans les premières générations islamique du et du deuxième siècle de l'Hégire”, Bulletin d'études orientales 29 (1989), pp. 269-278.
On Wahb b. Munabbih, Kaʿb al-Aḥbār, and xxx.
[#] Massignon, Louis, “Le "hadith al-ruqya" musulman. Première version arabe du "Pater"”, Revue de l'histoire des Religions x (1941), pp. 57-62.
Reprinted in Opera Minora. Textes recueillis, classes et presentés avec une bibliographic par Y. Moubarac. Sous le Patronage du Centre d'Etudes Dar El-Salam.
[#] Monferrer-Sala, Juan Pedro, “Yā-btā l-lāḏī fī l-samāwāt... Notas sobre antiguas versions árabes del Padre Nuestro,” Al-Qanṭara 21 (2000), pp. 277-305.

Pines, Shlomo (1987), 'Gospel quotations and cognate topics in 'Abd al-Jabbār's
Schreiner, Martin (1886), 'Zur Geschichte der Aussprache des Hebräischen ', ZATW, 6, 213-59.
[#] ------, “Zur Geschiche der Polemik zwischen Juden und Muhammedanern,” ZDMG 42 (1888), pp. 591-675.
[#] ------, “Beiträge zur Geschichte der Bibel in der arabischen Literatur”, in George Alexander Kohut (ed.), Semitic studies in memory of Rev. Dr. Alexander-Kohut, Berlin: S. Calvary & Co., 1897, pp. 495-513.
Stieglecker, Hermann, “Die muhammedanische Pentateuchkritik zu Beginn des 2. Jahrtausends,” Theologisch-Praktische Quartalschrift 88 (1935), pp. 72-87, 282-302, 472-486. 
Suermann, Harald, The Use of Biblical Quotations in Christian Apocalyptic Writings of the Umayyad Period, in: David Thomas (Hrsg.), The Bible in Arab Christianity = The History of Christian-Muslim Relations 6, Leiden, Bosten 2007, 69-90
D.S. Margoliouth, “Old and New Testaments in Muhammadanism,” in Encyclopedia of Religion and Ethics, ed. J. Hastings, vol. 9 (Edinburgh — New York 1908-1926), pp. 480-483.
[#] Purgstall, Baron Hammer, “On the First Translation of the Gospels into Arabic,” Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland 4 (1837), pp. 172-173.
On Warqā b. Nawfal and his alleged translation of the Gospels
Ibn Barrajān of Seville
Casewit, Yousef, “A Muslim Scholar of the Bible: Prooftexts from Genesis and Matthew in the Qur’an Commentary of Ibn Barrajān of Seville (d. 536/1141)”, Journal of Qur’anic Studies 18.1 (2016), pp. 1-48.
	Also on other AT and NT texts.
ibn al-Layth
Muslim-Christian 
al-jahiz
[#] Bacher, Wilhelm, “Zu der von al-Gahiz citierten Übersetzung aus Jesaja,” JQR 13 (1901), pp. 542-544.
ibn al-rabban
[#]Taeschner, Franz, “Die alttestamentlichen Bibelzitate, vor allem aus dem Pentateuch, in Aṭ-Ṭabarī’s Kitāb ad-Dīn wad-Daula und ihre Bedeutung für die Frage nach der Echtheit dieser Schrift,” in Oriens Christianus, 3d ser., 9 (1934): 23-39.
Khalife, A. and Kutsch, W. (1959), 'ar-radd ala-n-Nasara de Ali at-Tabari ', MUSJ, 36,
115-48.

al-yaʿqūbī (d. 897/98) 
Dwight M. Donaldson, “al-Ya’qûbî's Chapter about Jesus Christ,” in The Macdonald Presentation Volume (New York, 1933), pp. 89-105.
[#] Ferré, André L., "L''Histoire Sainte' selon Yaʿqūbī: les sources, notamment la Bible, et leur interprétation," in Belo, Caterina and Jean-Jacques Pérennès (eds.), Mission in Dialogue. Essays in Honour of Michael L. Fitzgerald. Louvain, Paris: Editions Peeters, 2012, pp. 149-162.
Ferré, André (1977), 'L’historien al-Ya’qûbî et les Evangiles ', Islamochristiana 3, 65-83.
Klamroth, M. (1885), 'Der Auszug aus den Evangelien bei dem arabischen Historiker Ja'qûbî', Festschrift zur Einweihung des Wilhelmsgymnasium in Hamburg
(Hamburg ), 117-28.
al-Tabari
[#] Qasim-Draz , Ceza, “Text  Generation and the  Saturation of  Meaning”  (Arabic  with  English  summary), Alif 7 (1988), pp. 30-81.
On the quotations from the book of Job in al-Ṭabarī’s 
Abū Nuʿaim
C. Peters, “Arabische Psalmenzitate bei Abū Nu‘aim,” in Biblica 20 (1939), pp. 1-9.
Ibn Hazm
Adang, Camilla, “Some hitherto Neglected Biblical Material in the Work of Ibn Ḥazm,” in Al-Masāq. Studia Arabo-Islamica Mediterranea V (1992), pp. 17-28.
[#] E. Algermissen, Die Pentateuchzitate Ibn Ḥazms. Ein Beitrag zur Geschichte der arabischen Bibelübersetzungen (Diss., Munich, 1933).
S-M. Behloul, Ibn Hazms Evangelienkritik: eine methodische Untersuchung (Islamic philosophy, theology, and science 50; Leiden — Boston, 2002).
Ebied, R. Y. and Wickham, L. R. (1970), 'al-Yakubi's account of the Israelite Prophets
and Kings ', JNES, 29, 80-98.
[#] Monferrer-Sala, J.P. "A Gospel Quotation of Syriac Origin in the Fiṣal by Ibn Ḥazm." Journal of Middle Eastern and North African Intellectual and Cultural Studies 1.1 (2002): 127-146.

Ibn Qutayba

[#] Lecomte, G., “Les citations de l’Ancien et du Nouveau Testament dans l’oeuvre d’Ibn Qutayba,” Arabica (1958), 34-46.
[#] R. Köbert, “Die älteste arabische Genesisübersetzung,” in R. Altheim-Stiehl, Die Araber in der Alten Welt, vol. 2 (Berlin, 1965), pp. 333-343.
Vajda, Georges (1935), 'Judaeo-Arabica : observations sur quelques citations bibliques chez Ibn Qotayba', Revue des Études Juives 99, 68-80.
Lecomte, Gérard (1950), 'Les citations de l’ancien et du nouveau testament dans
l’oeuvre d’Ibn Qutayba', Arabica 5, 34-46.
A. Isteero, ‘Abdullah Muslim ibn Qutayba’s Biblical Quotations and Their Source: An Inquiry into the Earliest Existing Arabic Bible Translations (Ph.D. dissertation, Johns Hopkins University, 1991).
al-Ghazali
[#] Chidiac, Robert (ed.), al-Ghazālī, Réfutation excellente de la Divinité de Jésus-Christ d’après les Evangiles, Paris: xxx, 1939, pp. 71-77.
On the New Testament quotations.
[#] Padwick, C.E., “Al-Ghazali and the Arabic Versions of the Gospels: An Unsolved Problem,” Moslem World 29 (1939), pp. 130-40.
al-Biqāʿī
[#]Saleh, Walid, “Reflections on Muslim Hebraism: Codex Vindobonensis Palatinus and al-Biqa‘I,” in Conklin Akbari, Suzanne and Karla Mallette, A Sea of Languages: Rethinking the Arabic Role in Medieval Literary History (University of Toronto Press, 2013), pp. 
[#] ------, “A Fifteenth Century Muslim: Al-Biqāʿī and his Defense of Using the Bible to Interpret the Qurʾān,” Speculum 83 (2008), pp. 629-654.
[#] ------, In defense of the Bible: a critical edition and an introduction to al-Biqā‘ī’s Bible treatise, Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2008.
 [#] ------, “Sublime in its Style, Exquisite in its Tenderness: The Hebrew Bible Quotations in al-Biqāʿī’s Qurʾān Commentary,” in Tvi Langermann and Josef Stern (eds.), Adaptations and Innovations, Paris: Peeters, 2007, pp. 331-347. 
[#] Saleh, Walid and Kevin Casey, “An Islamic Diatesseron: Al-Biqāʿī’s Harmony of the Four Gospels,” in Binay, Sara and Stefan Leder (eds.), Translating the Bible into Arabic: historical, text-critical and literary aspects, Beiruter Texte und Studien 131, Beirut: Ergon Verlag Würzburg in Kommission, 2012, pp. 85-115.
ibn Khaldun
Baumstark, Anton, ''Der Bibelkanon bei Ibn Chaldûn'', Oriens Christianus 4:2 (1904): 393-398.
Pseudo-Scriptures
What do I mean with that, in intro. 
[#] Jeffery, Arthur, “A Muslim Torah from India,” in Muslim World 15 (1925), pp. 232-239.
Deals with a booklet of forty-five pages, lithographed at Bombay and entitled "The Book of the Torah which God sent down to Moses." Contains a translation of the first chapters (Ar. sura).
Keywords: Pentateuch, India
[#] Cheikho, P.L., “Quelques Legendes Islamiques Apocryphes”, Mélanges de la Faculté Orientale 4 (1910), pp. 33-56. 
Describes an unspecified Ms. from Mosul, containing Muslim Pseudo-Psalms (zabūr), and unspecified Mss. <mssGroup><place>from Beirut</place>, containing the ṣuḥuf of Abraham and Moses. </mssGroup>
Check
Zabur in EI
Guenzburg and von Rosen published a copy of the Suhuf of Abraham in the Annual of the St. Petersburg Institute of Oriental Languages. 
Cheikho published selection of a zabur (discovered at Mosul) in Melanges de la Faculte Orientale de Beyrouth in 1910.

rest
كتاب الدر الثمين في شرح سفر التكوين (Cairo, 1895). [At the expense of Ghaṭṭās Yūsuf Khoury and Buṭrus Mikhā’īl Al-Miṣrī. Ibn al-Qanbar?]
Poetical Books (including the Psalter)
A. Baumstark, “Der älteste erhaltene griechisch-arabische Text von Psalm 110 (109),” in Oriens Christianus 31 (1934), pp. 55-66.
= Bryn Mawr College Zurich 94 (Hiersemann)
Mss.: <mssGroup><place>Bryn Mawr College Library</place>, BV 47</mssGroup>
________, “Minbar = Thron, und älteste arabische Psaltertexte,” in Orientalistische Literaturzeitung 46 (1943), pp. 337-341.
H. Fleischer, in ZDMG 18 (1864), pp. 288-291.
C. Karalevsky, in Χρυσοστομικά (Rome, 1908), pp. 604ff.
On the editions of Abdallah ibn al-FAdl. 
E. Mittwoch, “Aus einer arabischen Übersetzung und Erklärung der Psalmen,” in Zeitschrift für die Alttestamentliche Wissenschaft 23 (1903), pp. 87-93.

J. Faultless, “The Two Recensions of the Prologue to John in Ibn al-Ṭayyib’s Commentary on the Gospels,” in D. Thomas, ed., Christians at the Heart of Islamic Rule: Church Life and Scholarship in ‘Abbasid Iraq (Leiden — Boston, 2003), pp. 177-198. 
P. Féghali, “Le commentaire de Matthieu de Denys bar Salibi en langue arabe,” Parole de l'Orient 32 (2007): 75-103.

Other New Testament
Graf, G. “Sinaitische Bibelfragmente.” Oriens Christianus 12-14 (1922-24): 217-220. [Refers to Mss. <mssGroup><place>containing parts of Acts</place>, the Pauline and General Epistles.]</mssGroup>
 [Arabic text, with text-critical notes, of the letters in question, from Sinai no. 154 (Gibson’s no.). The second and third installments of the article offer a careful description of the manuscript itself and then a focus on each letter with attention to the underlying Greek and Syriac texts.]



The Epistles of John

S.J. Davis, “Introducing an Arabic Commentary on the Apocalypse: Ibn Katib Qaysar on Revelation,” Harvard Theological Review 101 (2008): 77-96.
Talia, S. Bûlus al-Bûši’s Arabic Commentary on the Apocalypse of St. John: An English Translation and a Commentary  (Ph.D. dissertation, Catholic University of America, 1987).


Quotations
________, “Arabische Übersetzung eines altsyrischen Evangelientextes und die in Sure 21:105 zitierte Psalmenübersetzung,” Oriens Christianus 3, Ser. 9 (1934): 165-88.
Neue orientalistische Probleme biblischer Textgeschichte, ZDMG 89 (1935), pp. 107-109.
Böwering, “The Light Verse: Text and Ṣūfī Interpretation,” in Oriens 36 (2001) [FS Rosenthal], pp. 113-144.  [Includes discussion of the Sufi Abū Tābit Šams al-Dīn Daylamī quoting from the Hebrew Bible.]
D.M. Dunlop, “A letter of Harun ar-Rashid to the Emperor Contantine VI,” in M.Black
and G. Fohrer (eds.), In Memoriam Paul Kahle (Berlin, 1968), pp. 106-15.

------, “La vie de Jésus dans les Annales de Tabarî,” Islamochristiana Roma 5 (1975), pp. 7-29

R.M. Frank, “A ‘Citation’ from the Prophet Jeremias in Ibn Qutaiba and Tabari,” CBQ 17 (1955): 379-402.
S.A. Frantsuzov, “Ob odnoj novozavetnoj tsitate v arabo-musul’manskikh sochinenijakh” [A Quotation from the New Testament in Arab Muslim Writings]. Vestnik PSTGU III.1 (7) (2007): 99-106. [on 1 Cor. 2:9]

Khalidi, T. The Muslim Jesus: Sayings and Stories in Islamic Literature. Cambridge, MA, 2001. also Khalidi’s collection of the same texts in Arabic
Khoury, R. G. (1989), 'Quelques réflexions sur la première ou les premières Bibles
arabes ', in Toufic Fahd (ed.), L'Arabie préislamique et son environnement
historique et culturel, 549-61.
--- (1989 ), 'Quelques Réflexions sur les citations de la Bible dans les premières
générations islamiques du premier et du deuxième siècle de l'Hégire ', Bulletin d'études
orientales 29, 269-78.
Kraus, P (1930), 'Hebräische und syrisch Zitate in Ismailitischen Schriften ', Der Islam,
19, 143-63. [repr. in idem, Alchemie, Ketzerei, Apokryphen im frühen Islam, ed. R. Brague, Hildesheim/Zürich/NY: Georg Olms Verlag, 1994]
Lazarus-Yafeh, Hava (1992), Intertwined worlds : medieval Islam and Bible criticism
(Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press) xiii,178p.
Matteo, I. di (1921-1923), 'Confuzione contro I Christiani dello Zaydita al-Qasim b. Ibrahim ',
Rivista degli Studi Orientali 9, 301-64.
J.P. Monferrer-Sala, “An Arabic-Muslim Quotation of a Biblical Text: Ibn Kathīr’s al-Bidāya wa-l-nihāya and the Construction of the Ark of the Covenant,” in: Ebied and Teule, Studies on the Christian Arabic Heritage, pp. 263-278.
Franz-Christoph Muth: 'Sichtungen' des Christlichen bei arabischen Historikern: die Evangelienauszüge bei al-Ya'qubi (gest. um 292/905), in: Kreikenbom, D. et al., eds. Arabische Christen, Christen in Arabien. Frankfurt, 2007, pp. 85ff.
Peters, Curt (1939), 'Arabische Psalmenzitate bei Abū Nu'aim ', Biblica 20, 1-9.
--- (1940), 'Psalm 149 in Zitaten islamischer Autoren ', Biblica, 21, 138-51
Tathbit in Relation to Early Christian and Judaeo-Arabic readings and Traditions
', JSAI 9, 195-251.
S
Schmidtke, S. "Abū al-Ḥusayn al-Baṣrī and His Transmission of Biblical Materials from Kitāb al-Dīn wa-al-Dawla by Ibn Rabban al-Ṭabarī: The Evidence from Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī's Mafātīḥ al-Ghayb." Islam and Christian-Muslim Relations 20 (2009): 105-118.
Smit, G. (1907), Bijbel en Legende bij den Arabischen schrijver Ja'kubi (Leiden ).
Sourdel, D. (1966), 'Un pamphlet musulman anonyme d’époque Abbaside contre les
chrétiens ', Revue des Etudes Islamiques 34, 1-34
Stern, S. M. (1967), 'Quotations From Apocryphal Gospels in Abd al-Gabbar ', Journal
of Theological Studies, 18, 34-57.
Tabari, Ali ibn Sahl Rabban (1923), 'The book of religion and empire : a semi-official
defence and exposition of Islam', in Alphonse Mingana (ed.), (Manchester , New
York: University Press Longmans Green), 144 p.
quotations.enl Page 3
Tritton, A. S. (1933), 'The Bible Text of Theodore Abu Kurra', Journal of Theological Studies
34, 52-54


UNCLASSIFIED
S. Arbache, “Bible et liturgie chez les Arabes chrétiens (VIe-IXe siècle),” in D. Thomas, ed., The Bible in Arab Christianity (Leiden — Boston, 2007), pp. 37-48.
J. Blau, “On a Fragment of the Oldest Judaeo-Arabic Bible Translation Extant,” in J. Blau and S.C. Reif, eds., Genizah Research after Ninety Years: The Case of Judaeo-Arabic (Cambridge, 1992), pp. 31-39. 
S.H. Griffith, “The Gospel in Arabic: An Inquiry into its Appearance in the First Abbasid Century,” in Oriens Christianus 69 (1985), pp. 126-167.
C. Padwick, “The Arabic Gospel,” in The Muslim World 29 (1939)), pp. 130-140.
A. Vaccari, “The Hesychian Recension of the Septuagint,” in Biblica 46 (1965), pp. 60-66.
M. Cramer, “The Vienna Folio and Fragments of a Coptic-Greek-Arabic Holy Week Lectionary from Scetis,” in Bulletin de la Société d’Archéologie Copte 19 (1967), pp.49-55. [on Pss21:21ff. and 66:2]
J. Nasrallah, “La liturgie des Patriarcats melchites de 969 à 1300,” in Oriens Christianus 71 (1987), pp. 156-181.
and New Testaments in the Arabic Language (Newcastle upon Tyne, 1811).

New Testament
Complete
(London, 1829). [Text of Erpenius.]
Ed. Faustus Nairon, (Rome, 1703) [Garshuni.]
De Sacy (Paris, 1824).
E.M. Quatremère (Paris, 1824). [Text of Erpenius in Garshuni, with Syriac.]

Gospels
	
Athanasius IV Dabbās, ed. (Aleppo, 1706)


</root>
